<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethics on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/ethics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ethics on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 08:31:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/ethics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Are Psychiatric &#39;Diagnoses&#39; Defamatory Statements?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-diagnoses-defamatory-statements/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 08:31:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-diagnoses-defamatory-statements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article by Sonja Grover, PhD, CPsych, of Lakehead University, Ontario, Canada.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Reification-of-Psychiatric-Diagnoses-as-Defamatory-Implications-for-Ethical-Clinical-Practice.pdf&#34;&gt;Reification of psychiatric diagnoses as defamatory: Implications for ethical clinical practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yobluemama2&#34;&gt;Becky on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an old article (2005), but definitely deserves another look.  It was published in the journal Ethical Human Psychology and Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;While the mental health professional generally has beneficent motives and an honest belief in the DSM diagnoses assigned to clients, such diagnoses may yet be defamatory when communicated to third parties. Mental health diagnoses invariably lower the individual&#39;s reputation in the eyes of the community. At the same time, DSM diagnoses are but one out of a myriad of possible interpretive frameworks. DSM descriptors for the client&#39;s distress thus cannot be said to capture the essence of the client&#39;s personhood. When a diagnosis is published as if it captured a definitive truth about an individual psychiatric client, it is, in that important regard, inaccurate. That is, such a communication meets the criterion for a reckless disregard for the truth or an honest belief but without reasonable basis insofar as it is considered to be anything more than a working hypothesis. Hence, in certain cases, DSM labeling may constitute defamation.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
