<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>DSM-5 on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/dsm-5/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DSM-5 on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 05:30:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/dsm-5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intermittent Explosive Disorder:  The &#39;Illness&#39; That Goes On Growing</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/intermittent-explosive-disorder-the-illness-that-goes-on-growing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 05:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/intermittent-explosive-disorder-the-illness-that-goes-on-growing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the APA, intermittent explosive disorder is characterized by angry aggressive outbursts that occur in response to relatively minor provocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular label has an interesting history in successive editions of the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSM I  (1952)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intermittent explosive disorder does not appear as such in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/dsm-1952.pdf&#34;&gt;first edition of DSM&lt;/a&gt;, but the general concept is clearly discernible in &amp;ldquo;passive-aggressive personality, aggressive type&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;A persistent reaction to frustration with irritability, temper tantrums, and destructive behavior is the dominant manifestation.&#34; (p 37)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justina Pelletier: The Case Continues</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-case-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 05:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-case-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 25, Joseph Johnston, Juvenile Court Justice in Boston, Massachusetts, issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://c.o0bg.com/rw/Boston/2011-2020/2014/03/25/BostonGlobe.com/HealthScience/Graphics/SCAN.pdf&#34;&gt;disposition order&lt;/a&gt; in the case: Care and protection of Justina Pelletier.  The background to the case is well-known.  Justina is 15 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Johnston did not return Justina to the care of her parents, but instead granted permanent custody to the Massachusetts Department of Children and Families (DCF), with a right to review in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In paragraph 4, the disposition order states: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  Dimensionality:  Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-dimensionality-conflicts-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 06:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-dimensionality-conflicts-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/23/dsm-5-dimensional-diagnoses-more-conflicts-of-interest/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;DSM-5 – Dimensional Diagnoses – More Conflicts of Interest?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; which I posted on December 23, 2013, I drew attention to the fact that David Kupfer, MD, in his position as head of the DSM-5 Task Force, was vigorously promoting a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;dimensional&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; model of assessment while at the same time was positioning himself to benefit financially if such a system were to be adopted by psychiatry generally.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating DSM-5: A Debate at Harvard</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/evaluating-dsm-5-a-debate-at-harvard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 06:10:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/evaluating-dsm-5-a-debate-at-harvard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://petrieflom.law.harvard.edu/events/details/evaluating-the-revised-DSM-5&#34;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; on this topic scheduled for 12:00 p.m., March 11, 2014, at Wasserstein Hall, Cambridge, Massachusetts.  The event is free, and open to the public.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate is sponsored by the Petrie-Flom Center For Health Law Policy, Biotechnology, and Bioethics at Harvard Law School.  This is the same group that produced the recent symposium on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ethics.harvard.edu/lab/featured/325-jlme-symposium&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption and Pharmaceutical Policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate will be moderated by I. Glen Cohen, Professor Law at Harvard and Co-Director of the Petri-Flom Center.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affluenza: A New Mental Illness?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/affluenza-a-new-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 05:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/affluenza-a-new-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A short editorial piece by James Bradshaw in the current issue (Jan/Feb) of the National Psychologist discusses the trial of a 16-year-old male who killed four people and severely injured two others while driving under the influence of Valium (diazepam) and alcohol.  He had stolen the alcohol from a store earlier, and his blood alcohol level was three times the legal adult limit.  He was driving 70 mph in a 40 mph zone at the time of the incident.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Compelling Critique of Psychiatric &#39;Diagnosis&#39;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-compelling-critique-of-psychiatric-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 05:48:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-compelling-critique-of-psychiatric-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just read a very interesting and insightful article on this topic.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/Research/Digest/Diagnosis/AfterDSM-5Lacasse2013.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;After DSM-5: A Critical Mental Health Research Agenda for the 21st Century&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It was written by Jeffrey Lacasse, PhD, and is a guest editorial published in Research on Social Work Practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;At times, it has seemed that the APA has behaved very much like a corporation seeking profit and influence rather than a scientific organization charged with the crucially important task of defining mental disorders.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 05:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 20, JAMA Psychiatry (formerly Archives of General Psychiatry) published an interesting letter.  It was headed: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleID=1780020&amp;amp;utm_source=Silverchair%20Information%20Systems&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=JAMAPsychiatry%3AOnlineFirst11%2F20%2F2013&#34;&gt;Failure to Report Financial Disclosure Information&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and was signed by Robert D. Gibbons PhD, David J Weiss PhD, Paul A. Pilkonis PhD, Ellen Frank, PhD , and David J. Kupfer MD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is an apology for failing to disclose a financial interest in an article, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3551289/&#34;&gt;Development of a Computerized Adaptive Test for Depression&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; that had appeared in Archives of General Psychiatry a year earlier (November 2012).  The article described a computerized questionnaire for depression (the CAT-DI) and was generally positive with regards to the potential usefulness of the test in clinical settings.  In the article, the authors had clearly stated that they had &lt;i&gt;no conflicts of interest&lt;/i&gt;, but that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Allen Frances – Lucy Johnstone Debate</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 05:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Allen Frances, MD, Chairperson of the DSM-IV task force, published an article on Psychology Today.  It is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201310/does-it-make-sense-scrap-psychiatric-diagnosis-0&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Does It Make Sense To Scrap Psychiatric Diagnosis?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and is essentially a response to the British Psychological Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Clinical Psychology&amp;rsquo;s (DCP) call to abandon the medical model in situations where it is not appropriate, and to embrace a psychosocial approach.  You can see a copy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;DCP&amp;rsquo;s May 13, 2013, statement here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: How to Salvage a Shipwreck</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 05:48:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 was published on May 18, 2013, amidst great criticism.  The fundamental criticism was, and is, that the &lt;b&gt;problems listed in the manual are not &lt;i&gt;illnesses&lt;/i&gt; in any ordinary sense of the term&lt;/b&gt;.  Other critics focused on the pathologizing of normality, the expansion of the diagnostic net by the lowering of thresholds, and the lack of reliability of the so-called diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response from the psychiatric community has been mixed.  Some, probably most, psychiatrists are keeping their heads down, getting on with the business of selling pills, and hoping that the gravy train won&#39;t derail.  Others are busy at damage control&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Doesn&#39;t Get It</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 3-4 June, the Institute of Psychiatry in London hosted an international conference to mark the publication of DSM-5.  On June 10, Sir Simon Wessely, a department head at the Institute, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slam.nhs.uk/our-blog/brcu/dsm-5-at-the-iop&#34;&gt;DSM-5 at the IoP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The paper is a summary of the conference proceedings, and also, in many respects, a defense of DSM-5.  The article touches on many issues that are central to the current anti-psychiatry debate, and for this reason, I thought it might be helpful to take a close look at the piece.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autism Prevalence Increase Questioned</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/autism-prevalence-increase-questioned/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2013 05:55:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/autism-prevalence-increase-questioned/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago (June 12) I posted &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/06/12/autism-prevalence-increasing/&#34;&gt;Autism Prevalence Increasing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article drew attention to a post by Kelly Brogan, MD, called &lt;i&gt;See No Evil, Hear No Evil&lt;/i&gt; which had appeared on Mad in America on June 9.  Dr. Brogan&amp;rsquo;s article had cited an alarming increase in the incidence of autism over the past few decades, and mentioned some possible causative factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I checked the figures against the DSM and CDC prevalence estimates and found they were broadly in line.  I mentioned the possibility that diagnostic expansion, particularly as embracing milder presentations, might be a confounding factor, but that given the reported increase (1 in 5000 to 100 in 5000) over 38 years, I expressed the view that this was a bit of a stretch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autism Prevalence Increasing</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/autism-prevalence-increasing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 06:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/autism-prevalence-increasing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On two occasions in the past week or so, I have been involved in discussions on the increasing prevalence of autism.  In the more recent of these, the individual with whom I was talking expressed the concern that the recent DSM enlargement of &lt;i&gt;autism disorder&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;autism spectrum disorder&lt;/i&gt; might be an APA-pharma designed artifact to draw attention away from the steady increase in the incidence of autism in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Science</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 08:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 27, David Brooks, a New York Times columnist, wrote a piece on psychiatry called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/28/opinion/brooks-heroes-of-uncertainty.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Heroes of Uncertainty&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting and somewhat contradictory article.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As the handbook’s [DSM-5] many critics have noted, psychiatrists use terms like &#39;mental disorder&#39; and &#39;normal behavior,&#39; but there is no agreement on what these concepts mean.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;What psychiatrists call a disease is usually just a label for a group of symptoms.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Attempt to Defend DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 06:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 April, The Conversation ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/mental-disorders-debunking-some-myths-of-the-dsm-5-12047&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental disorders: debunking some myths of the DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Perminder Sachdev, MD.  Dr. Sachdev is a psychiatrist, and was a member of the DSM-5&amp;rsquo;s Neurocognitive Disorders Work Group.  He works at the School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Australia.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davetraxson&#34;&gt;Dave Traxson&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANALYSIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the title.  &amp;ldquo;…debunking some myths of the DSM-5.&amp;rdquo;  This sounds good.  You might get the impression that he&amp;rsquo;s going to address the myth of mental illness – the myth that all human problems are illnesses and are best treated by drugs.  But – alas – you would be mistaken.  Dr. Sachdev lists four myths that he plans to debunk.  He refers to these as the &amp;ldquo;…four key criticisms about DSM-5…&amp;rdquo;  Let&amp;rsquo;s examine what he says about these one by one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Psychiatric Side-shuffle Continues</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-psychiatric-side-shuffle-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 05:18:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-psychiatric-side-shuffle-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Joel Paris, MD, is an eminent psychiatrist, and is also a Professor of Psychiatry at McGill University in Montréal.  He has recently written a very timely book titled: &lt;i&gt;The Intelligent Clinician&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;, published by Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have placed an order for this book through our local inter-library loan system, and when it comes in, I&amp;rsquo;ll publish a review.  But in the meantime, Dr. Paris has posted on Oxford University Press&amp;rsquo;s website a &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.oup.com/2013/05/clinician-guide-to-dsm-5/&#34;&gt;brief essay to promote the book&lt;/a&gt;.  The essay has lots of interesting aspects, and I thought it might be helpful to examine it in some detail.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Still Fighting Back: Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 11:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, is president-elect of the APA, and is scheduled to take over the reins from Dr. Dilip Jeste this month.  Never in its history has the APA been subject to such scrutiny or criticism from such diverse sources, and one might reasonably have expected Dr. Lieberman to open on a conciliatory note, promising investigations, reforms, etc….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no!  He&amp;rsquo;s in the ring slugging furiously from the opening bell.  Two days ago (May 20) he published an article in Scientific American titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/mind-guest-blog/2013/05/20/dsm-5-caught-between-mental-illness-stigma-and-anti-psychiatry-prejudice/&#34;&gt;DSM-5: Caught between Mental Illness Stigma and Anti-Psychiatry Prejudice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Live Video Chat: DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/live-video-chat-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 08:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/live-video-chat-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I received the following email from Emily Underwood, a reporter with Science Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;I am a reporter with Science magazine -- after reading your Twitter feed and blog I thought you might be interested in a live video chat I’m hosting this week on the controversy surrounding the DSM V. My guests are Allen Frances of Duke University, William Eaton of Johns Hopkins University, and Frank Farley of Temple University; given their different takes on the subject it promises to be a lively conversation!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Still Under Fire</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-still-under-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 21:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-still-under-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mental Health Europe (MHE) is a non-governmental organization &amp;ldquo;… committed to the promotion of positive mental health and well-being, the prevention of mental health problems, the improvement of care, advocacy for social inclusion and the protection of the human rights of (ex)users of mental health services and their families and carers.&amp;rdquo;  It is composed of associations, organizations, and individuals who are active in the mental health field, including users and ex-users of services, volunteers, and professionals.  MHE subscribes to the following values: dignity and respect; equal opportunities; freedom of choice; non-discrimination, social inclusion, democracy and participation.  You can read more about them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mhe-sme.org/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with DSM</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 08:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the NY Times Sunday review.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/12/opinion/sunday/why-the-fuss-over-the-dsm-5.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It was written by Sally Satel MD, a psychiatrist, currently a resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is called:  &amp;ldquo;Why the Fuss Over the DSM-5?&amp;rdquo;  Dr. Satel&amp;rsquo;s central point is that psychiatrists only treat &lt;i&gt;symptoms&lt;/i&gt; anyway and pay little attention to the DSM.  She expresses the belief that the manual&amp;rsquo;s diagnoses are &amp;ldquo;…passports to insurance coverage, the keys to special education and behavioral services in school and the tickets to disability benefits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Anxiety Disorder: Now Also for Adults</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of separation anxiety disorder has been around since DSM-III.  In DSM-IV it is defined as &amp;ldquo;…excessive anxiety concerning separation from the home or from those to whom the person is attached.&amp;rdquo;  (DSM-IV-TR p 121).  The APA&amp;rsquo;s prevalence estimate is 4%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is listed under the heading: &amp;ldquo;Other Disorders of Infancy, Childhood, or Adolescence.&amp;rdquo;  One of the criteria is that the problem must begin before age 18, and in practice the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; was generally confined to children under the age of 10 or so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bereavement Exclusion and DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 14:09:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of major depressive &lt;i&gt;disorder&lt;/i&gt; is based on the presence of a major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;, in turn, is defined by the presence of five or more items from the following list during a two-week period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) depressed mood most of the day, nearly every day, as indicated by either subjective report (e.g., feels sad or empty) or observation made by others (e.g., appears tearful). Note&lt;b&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; In children and adolescents, can be irritable mood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Blood Test for Depression</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 07:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of Talla Trialogue on Twitter, I have read an article by Shari Roan called &lt;i&gt;Blood Test for Depression Proves It&amp;rsquo;s Not All In Your Head&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.takepart.com/article/2013/01/25/major-depression-can-be-diagnosed-blood-test&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article appears to be an interview with Lonna Williams, the CEO of Ridge Diagnostics.  This company is reportedly introducing a blood test for depression.  The test is called MDDScore and is expected to cost $745.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article tells us that:  &amp;ldquo;You get a numerical score that suggests how likely it is that you have depression. Studies show that MDD Score is about as accurate at making a diagnosis as the most rigorous evaluations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric Spin</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-spin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 09:43:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-spin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago (March 23), the New York Times did a feature on &amp;ldquo;Defining Mental Illness.&amp;rdquo;  They invited Ronald Pies, MD (a psychiatry professor at SUNY Upstate Medical University and Tufts University) to submit a brief paper on this topic.  Various people with opposing views were allowed to respond, and finally Dr. Pies presented a much longer summary and rebuttal.  You can see the entire print version &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/24/opinion/sunday/sunday-dialogue-defining-mental-illness.html?ref=opinion&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Somatic Symptom Disorder in DSM-5: You&#39;re Crazy to Worry about Your Health</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 09:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, there is a category called Somatoform Disorders, the common feature of which is a preoccupation with &amp;ldquo;… physical symptoms that suggest a general medical condition …and are not fully explained by a general medical condition…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four of the &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; in this category will be retired in DSM-5 and will be replaced by a new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo;:  &lt;em&gt;somatic symptom disorder&lt;/em&gt;.  The four superseded &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;1.  somatization disorder
2.  hypochondriasis
3.  pain disorder
4.  undifferentiated somatoform disorder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Inter-Rater Reliability is Low</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/the-dsm-5-field-trials-inter-rater-reliability-ratings-take-a-nose-dive/&#34;&gt;article by Jack Carney&lt;/a&gt;, DSW, on this topic on Mad in America.  Jack refers to the DSM-5 field trials published earlier this year in the American Journal of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inter-rater reliability is measured by a statistic called a kappa score.  A score of 1 means perfect inter-rater agreement; a score of 0 indicates zero agreement.  In psychosocial research a kappa score of 0.7 or above is generally considered good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petition on Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting new article by Paula Caplan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/comedy-history-and-the-future-mental-disorder-labels&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It discusses the harmful effects of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the fact that because of these labels, people have lost their &amp;ldquo;… jobs, custody of children, health insurance, and the right to make decisions about their medical and legal affairs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paula also mentions a petition she created in December 2011 calling for &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Congressional Hearings about Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  The petition is still up. You can find it&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.change.org/petitions/everyone-who-cares-about-the-harm-done-by-psychiatric-diagnosis-endorse-the-call-for-congressional-hearings-about-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – the Pseudoscience</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 15:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As most readers of this website are aware, there is a great deal of resistance to the soon-to-be-released DSM-5.  There is even a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/dsm-5-boycott-launched/&#34;&gt;Boycott DSM-5 Committee &lt;/a&gt;established by Jack Carney, and many people are suggesting that practitioners use the World Health Organization&amp;rsquo;s (WHO&amp;rsquo;s) International Classification of Diseases (ICD) instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the general context of this debate, I have come across an article by Philip Thomas, M.D. – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/pinball-wizards-and-the-doomed-project-of-psychiatric-diagnosis/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pinball Wizards and the Doomed Project of Psychiatric Diagnosis.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  Dr. Thomas points out that &amp;ldquo;…it’s hard to imagine that the criticisms raised about DSM-5 won’t also apply to the ICD.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 16:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Nick Stuart, a regular commenter on this website, drew my attention to Dr. Steven Novella.  Dr. Novella is a strong supporter of the standard psychiatric system, and routinely refers to those of us who challenge these concepts as &amp;ldquo;mental illness deniers.&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;(Mental Illness Denial Part I)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick referred me to some of Dr. Novella&amp;rsquo;s articles, and I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/01/27/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/#.USVHtKWG0eU&#34;&gt;brief response&lt;/a&gt;.  I have been giving these matters some thought, however, and I think the subject matter warrants more attention. This is because Dr. Novella does indeed marshal some compelling arguments in other areas, and also because he routinely condemns us &amp;ldquo;deniers&amp;rdquo; as illogical employers of &amp;ldquo;…semantic misdirection and evasion…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism of DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 10:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane, author of &lt;i&gt;Shyness: How Normal Behavior Became a Sickness,&lt;/i&gt; has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201302/dsm-5-has-gone-press-containing-major-scientific-gaffe&#34;&gt;new post&lt;/a&gt;, in which he attacks the APA for including somatic symptom disorder (SSD) in the upcoming DSM-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lane quotes from Allen Francis (former DSM guru who has now seen the light) and Suzy Chapman, a UK health advocate.  Both of these commentators attack the new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; as invalid, unreliable, and potentially over-inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  More of the Same - Turf Expansion</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 19:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until now, I’ve pretty much steered clear of DSM-5.  My reason for this is that the upcoming revision represents, to my mind, a distraction from the central issue, i.e., that the whole notion of mental illness is spurious, destructive nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position is that the purpose of DSM is to expand psychiatric turf and to legitimize the pushing of mood/behavior-altering pharmaceuticals. In the US (and I believe in most developed countries) you can’t prescribe a drug without a diagnosis.  And the APA has never neglected its primary mission in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Cracks in the Sandcastle</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 14:36:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane has a post up on Psychology Today (May 14 2012) called:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201205/dsm-5-is-diagnosed-stinging-rebuke-the-apa&#34;&gt;DSM-5 Is Diagnosed, With a Stinging Rebuke to the APA.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, the APA announced the new “diagnoses” that they proposed to include in the upcoming DSM-5.  This kind of expansion is nothing new.  The APA has been engaged in the medicalization of every conceivable human problem for the past 50 or 60 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on this occasion, some of their more creative and potentially damaging creations generated a good deal of fairly vocal opposition.  The upshot of this is a decision by the APA to drop two of the more contentious “diagnoses:”  - “attenuated psychosis syndrome” and “mixed anxiety and depression.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Too Much Sex?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/too-much-sex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 11:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/too-much-sex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane recently published an interesting&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201204/american-sex-and-american-psychiatry&#34;&gt; article &lt;/a&gt;on Psychology Today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article covers a number of topics, including the APA’s proposal to include “hypersexual disorder” in the upcoming DSM-5.  The implications of this proposed “diagnosis” are that if you think about sex too much or engage in sexual activity too much, then you have a mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 60’s, when I was at college, I would frequently find myself chatting with a group of fellow students on a wide range of topics, including sex.  Often someone would cite the old statistic that the average young adult male thinks about sex 171 times a day (or whatever), to which the chorus of replies was always – “no way; it’s much more often than that.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eccentricity</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/eccentricity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 21:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/eccentricity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I received the following email from a reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“What’s your stance on eccentricity? How do you relate to the general view in the APA that deviation from cultural norms is pathological? And, have you ever read about David Weeks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;I consider myself an eccentric person with many quirks and some fetishes. While I have many friends who share the same interests or many of them, I still feel a little bad about psychiatrists labeling eccentricity with SPD or Schizoid personality disorder. I am 19, and my friends are from the 18-25 years of age, and we share a common love for anime and cartoons. Maybe not always the same but sometimes we share two or more common cartoons. Some of them also are collectors of stuffed animals and figurines like me, and some of them engage in masturbation with those objects as me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Normal&#34; Bereavement</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/normal-bereavement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 22:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/normal-bereavement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a nice article in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736%2812%2960248-7/fulltext&#34;&gt;Lancet&lt;/a&gt; last month.  The article posed the question: “When should grief be classified as a mental illness?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author criticized the APA’s draft version of DSM-5 for blurring the distinction and for making it more likely that people in bereavement will be “diagnosed” as depressed and, of course, “treated” with prescription drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a good deal of criticism against the APA on this issue, and it is likely that the final version of DSM-5 will reflect some retreat in this matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s New?  APA Threats, Xanax, Etc.</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-s-new-apa-threats-xanax-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 11:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-s-new-apa-threats-xanax-etc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Daniel Carlat’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://carlatpsychiatry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; carries an &lt;a href=&#34;http://carlatpsychiatry.blogspot.com/2012/01/apa-threatens-to-sue-dsm5watch-website.html&#34;&gt;interesting item&lt;/a&gt;.  It seems that a lady named Suzy Chapman started a site called dsm5watch, in which she expressed criticism of the DSM.  Well, the APA didn’t like this and sent her a cease and desist letter, claiming that the string “DSM-5” is trademarked, and that she was infringing their rights.  She complied, changing the name of her site to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dxrevisionwatch.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;dxrevisionwatch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find interesting here is that the APA claim to be interested in public comment.  I guess as long as it doesn’t get too critical.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 00:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing this post as a response to a comment posted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://drpullen.com/&#34;&gt;medical blog&lt;/a&gt; in my previous post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2011/02/24/more-on-so-called-bipolar-disorder/#comments&#34;&gt;More on So-called Bipolar Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2001 I became very ill.  The symptoms were exhaustion and mild nosebleeds. I went to three different practitioners, but they all were dismissive of my concerns, assured me that I was in good health, and sent me on my way.   On August 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of that year I was admitted to the hospital in Greeley, Colorado with complete kidney failure.  The nephrologist at the hospital gave me the &lt;em&gt;diagnosis&lt;/em&gt; that had eluded the earlier doctors:  Wegener’s Granulomatosis - a rare autoimmune disease that attacks lungs, kidneys, and airways. I have been on dialysis every since.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
