<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posttraumatic Stress Disorder on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2009 17:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post was edited and updated on July 7, 2013 in the light of comments from readers.  I am grateful for their input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anxiety disorders listed in DSM-IV is posttraumatic stress disorder. The criteria for this condition are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. The person has been exposed to a traumatic event in which both of the following were present:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) the person experienced, witnessed, or was confronted with an event or events that involved actual or threatened death or serious injury, or a threat to the physical integrity of self or others
(2) the person&#39;s response involved intense fear, helplessness, or horror. Note: in children, this may be expressed instead by disorganized or agitated behavior&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
