<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Research Corruption on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/research-corruption/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research Corruption on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 05:30:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/research-corruption/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Responds:  Antidepressants Really Work.  Really?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-responds-antidepressants-really-work-really/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-responds-antidepressants-really-work-really/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 25, 2017, Fredrik Hieronymus et al published a meta-analysis in Molecular Psychiatry.  The study is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/Hieronymus-mp2017147a.pdf&#34;&gt;Efficacy of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors in the absence of side effects: a mega-analysis of citalopram and paroxetine in adult depression&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Elias Eriksson, PhD, Head of the Department of Pharmacology, University of Gothenburg, Sweden, is the principal author, but as Fredrik Hieronymus is the first author listed, I will refer to the article as Hieronymus et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FDA:  The Fox Guards the Hen House</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 05:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In their Fall 2013 issue, the Journal of Law, Medicine, and Ethics published a symposium of papers by members of the Harvard&amp;rsquo;s Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics.  The symposium was called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ethics.harvard.edu/lab/featured/325-jlme-symposium&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption and Pharmaceutical Policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The symposium focuses on pharmaceutical products generally, but all the material is relevant and important in the context of psychiatric drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will highlight one of these papers:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Light-et-al-document-from-Safra-Institue-on-corruption-1.pdf&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption of Pharmaceuticals and the Myth of Safe and Effective Drugs&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by Donald W. Light, Joel Lexchin, and Jonathan J. Darrow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 05:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In January of this year, Steven Hyman MD, former Director of NIMH and currently a leading psychiatric researcher at MIT and Harvard, published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/npp/journal/v39/n1/full/npp2013181a.html&#34;&gt;Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; in Neuropsychopharmacology.  The article is in the journal&amp;rsquo;s commentary section and is essentially an opinion piece.  Here&amp;rsquo;s Dr. Hyman&amp;rsquo;s summary:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite high prevalence and enormous unmet medical need, the pharmaceutical industry has recently de-emphasized neuropsychiatric disorders as &#39;too difficult&#39; a challenge to warrant major investment.  Here I describe major obstacles to drug discovery and development including a lack of new molecular targets, shortcomings of current animal models, and the lack of biomarkers for clinical trials.  My major focus, however, is on new technologies and scientific approaches to neuropsychiatric disorders that give promise for revitalizing therapeutics and may thus answer industry&#39;s concerns.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAFÉ Study: Real Science or Marketing Exercise?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/caf%C3%A9-study-real-science-or-marketing-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 05:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/caf%C3%A9-study-real-science-or-marketing-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 8,  I received the following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/06/u-of-minnesota-faculty-senate-vote-to-review-dan-markingsons-death/&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; from a reader:  (The subject matter is the controversial CAFÉ – Comparisons of Atypicals in First Episode of Psychosis - study.  This was the study in which Dan Markingson committed suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;It appears that there was no head-to-head with a control group taking a placebo pill. Nor was there a control group featuring &#39;old&#39; types of &#39;antipsychotic&#39;. If that was the case then it is very poor study. If you are just looking at 3 &#39;new&#39; subtypes of a &#39;new&#39; class - then what on earth can you hope to show from the data.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U of Minnesota Faculty Senate Vote To Review Dan Markingson&#39;s Death</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/u-of-minnesota-faculty-senate-vote-to-review-dan-markingson-s-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 10:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/u-of-minnesota-faculty-senate-vote-to-review-dan-markingson-s-death/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2004, 26-year-old Dan Markingson committed suicide.  Since then, numerous concerns have been expressed about the events that led up to his death.  In particular, it has been claimed that he was coerced into the CAFE study, and that he was too delusional to understand what was involved.  It has also been reported widely that his mother, Mary Weiss, saw his condition deteriorate while he was taking the study drug - Seroquel (quetiapine) - and that she made numerous unsuccessful requests to the researchers to have him removed from the study.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children: Harvard&#39;s Shame</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 05:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2012, Mark Olfson, MD, et al, published an article in the Archives of General Psychiatry.  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22868273&#34;&gt;National Trends in the Office-Based Treatment of Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The authors collected data from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Surveys for the period 1993-2009, and looked for trends in antipsychotic prescribing for children, adolescents, and adults in outpatient visits.  Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;&lt;!--
table { 	border: 1px solid gray;     	border-collapse: collapse;      	width: 500px;   	cellspacing: 0; } th {     	background-color: #eee;          border: 1px solid black; }  th#blank {     	background- color: #FFF;  }  th.colOne {         width: 100px; } td {     	text-align: center;  	border: 1px solid black; } table#diagnosis th.data {         width: 120px; }
--&gt;&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;antipsychoticRX&#34; cellspacing=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;colOne&#34;&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Increase in no. of antipsychotic prescriptions per 100 population (1993-2009)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0-13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.24-1.83 (almost 8-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;14-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.78-3.76 (almost 5-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;21+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25-6.18 (almost 2-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;The authors provide a breakdown of the diagnoses assigned to the children and adolescents during the antipsychotic visits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jon Rappoport&#39;s Blog</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 05:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Jon Rappoport&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, please take a look.  Here are two quotes from his September 22 post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/2013/09/22/psychiatry-targets-college-students-for-destruction/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry targets college students for destruction&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The concept called &#39;mental disorder&#39; is a sales pitch backed up by extraordinary PR, money, academic gibberish, and government-granted official status.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;People need to wake up to the fact that the whole panoply of human suffering has been co-opted, taken over, redefined, re-translated into a lexicon of pseudoscience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Mobilizing Consumer Groups Over Drug Trials Data</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-mobilizing-consumer-groups-over-drug-trials-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 09:02:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-mobilizing-consumer-groups-over-drug-trials-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2013/jul/21/big-pharma-secret-drugs-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Big pharma mobilising patients in battle over drugs trials data&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt;in last Sunday&amp;rsquo;s Guardian, a UK newspaper.  It was written by Ian Sample, the Guardian&amp;rsquo;s science correspondent.  Here are the two opening sentences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The pharmaceutical industry has &#39;mobilised&#39; an army of patient groups to lobby against plans to force companies to publish secret documents on drugs trials.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs companies publish only a fraction of their results and keep much of the information to themselves, but regulators want to ban the practice. If companies published all of their clinical trials data, independent scientists could reanalyse their results and check companies&#39; claims about the safety and efficacy of drugs.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CAFE Study: Dr. Lieberman&#39;s High Moral Ground</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-cafe-study-dr-lieberman-s-high-moral-ground/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2013 06:10:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-cafe-study-dr-lieberman-s-high-moral-ground/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CAFE Study, conducted by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, et al between 2002 and 2005, has been the subject of much comment.  Carl Elliott, in particular, has written extensively on the matter, including his article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.motherjones.com/environment/2010/09/dan-markingson-drug-trial-astrazeneca?page=1&#34;&gt;The Deadly Corruption of Clinical Trials&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;in Mother Jones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to address the issues involved in the CAFE study, we must first take a brief look at the CATIE study.  This was also conducted by Dr. Lieberman et al (not the same et al as CAFE, but with some overlap).  CATIE was conducted between 2001 and 2004.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Payments to Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2013 05:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 12 of this year, the Los Angeles Daily News ran an article by Susan Abram titled:  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailynews.com/ci_22751458/california-doctors-report-prescription-drug-company-payments-speaking-engagements&#34;&gt;Doctors report big pharma payouts for drug endorsements&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It discusses the financial ties between physicians and drug companies in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;In fact, hundreds of physicians, psychiatrists, and medical school faculty members across California are on the payroll of major drug companies, earning tens of thousands of dollars for speaking to other medical professionals at events held by industry leaders that make drugs such as Advair, Cymbalta, Viagra and Zoloft.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma&#39;s Subtle but Pernicious Marketing</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alice Keys, MD, has recently written a short article for Mad in America.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/he-who-pays-the-piper/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Keys points out that to maintain a medical license, one must accumulate continuing education credits, and that these credits have to be approved by state licensing boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that pharmaceutical companies have largely hijacked this process in recent decades, and that their &amp;ldquo;educational&amp;rdquo; presentations might be better described as infomercials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lancet Gene Study</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lancet-gene-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 18:57:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lancet-gene-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday (February 28) the Lancet published a study called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(12)62129-1/fulltext&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Identification of risk loci with shared effects on five major psychiatric disorders: a genome-wide analysis.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  The study was conducted by the Cross-Disorder Group of the Psychiatric Genomics Consortium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Psychiatric Genomics Consortium (PGC) was formed in 2007.  Its purpose is &amp;ldquo;…to undertake meta-analyses of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) for psychiatric disorders…&amp;rdquo;  The authors state that they have no conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On their &lt;a href=&#34;https://pgc.unc.edu/&#34;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, the PGC state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Thoughts on Dr. Novella&#39;s Articles</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 09:55:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/#.USd7W6WG0eU&#34;&gt;Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;Mental Illness Denial Part I&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Novella makes the point that various parts of the brain enable us to do certain things, and that if we are doing these things dysfunctionally, or not well, or perhaps not at all, then clearly there is something wrong with that part of the brain.  The example he gives is the activity of paying attention – but I think this is provided as an example, and that Dr. Novella intended his comments to apply to the full range of problems embraced by the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corruption of Research by Drug Companies</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/corruption-of-research-by-drug-companies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 10:29:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/corruption-of-research-by-drug-companies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At present the pharmaceutical companies are responsible for testing the effectiveness and safety of their own products.  In recent years there have been numerous reports of dishonest practices in this area, including suppression of unfavorable results and massaging of data to create the impression that a drug is more effective than is actually the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, Christopher Lane publicized a particularly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201209/when-drug-treatments-fail&#34;&gt;egregious example&lt;/a&gt; of this from England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drug at the center of this scandal is reboxetine.  It is not available in the US, but is widely prescribed in the UK and in &lt;em&gt;sixty&lt;/em&gt; other countries for depression, panic disorder, and ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
