<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tell Your Story on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/tell-your-story/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tell Your Story on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 05:30:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/tell-your-story/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What Is Tragedy? How Just 2 Days of Paxil Sent My Life Into Chaos</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-is-tragedy-how-just-2-days-of-paxil-sent-my-life-into-chaos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 05:30:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-is-tragedy-how-just-2-days-of-paxil-sent-my-life-into-chaos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;by Michael Coughlin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I survived the tragic and sudden death of my 12-year-old brother, the near-death of my second brother, and the horrific suicide of my uncle, all with barely any medication. I became an extremely happy and high-functioning adult through holistic and spiritual growth. I loved life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Then a freak occurrence happened. I got a pinched nerve in my neck that caused anxiety, and my doctor prescribed Paxil, a dangerous antidepressant, without any screening, a formal diagnosis, or any fair warning of the risks or explanation of how long I would need to take the drug for. I was always against antidepressants because I studied them in college and I knew they were often overprescribed, and I let my guard down for just one day. After just two days of the drug, I couldn’t fall asleep naturally for weeks, something that never occurred in my entire life before. I developed hypomanic symptoms, sleeping only a few hours a night for three weeks, and my doctor was nowhere to be found to help.  He remained in denial. The BU Center for Anxiety &amp;amp; Related Disorders discharged me when I was in need of help.  The McLean Mental Hospital didn’t return my phone calls. I would later learn that I was suffering from Antidepressant-Associated Hypomania and no one could get me the care that I needed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE EX-PATIENT MOVEMENT</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-brief-history-of-the-ex-patient-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 09:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-brief-history-of-the-ex-patient-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;277&#34; height=&#34;234&#34; /&gt;
by  Philip A. Kumin
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Author&#39;s Note: The following article was originally written in 1991. Since then, Judi Chamberlin has died of cancer, and both national patients&#39; organizations have fallen into disarray due to constant infighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps concurrent with the gathering momentum of deinstitutionalization, the psychiatric inmates&amp;rsquo; liberation movement began in the early-to-mid 1970&amp;rsquo;s with sporadic protests by former inmates against human rights violations in institutions. Each summer, the founding matriarchs and patriarchs of this Movement gathered together in what came to be known as the International Conferences for Human Rights and Against Psychiatric Oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SELF-HELP &amp; ADVOCACY</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/self-help-advocacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 09:50:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/self-help-advocacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone  wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;277&#34; height=&#34;234&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Philip A. Kumin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Author&#39;s Note:  The following article was originally written in 1987.  Immediately before the start of the Alternatives &#39;87 Conference, a Constitutional Convention was held for the National Mental Health Consumers&#39;  Association.
&lt;p&gt;Persons whose names I used are in the public domain regarding their status as patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A DISCUSSION REGARDING THE EVOLUTION OF A SOCIAL MOVEMENT</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-discussion-regarding-the-evolution-of-a-social-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 12:37:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-discussion-regarding-the-evolution-of-a-social-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone  wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;307&#34; height=&#34;260&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Philip A. Kumin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone privy to the dynamics of the discussion surrounding the manifest destiny of the mental patients’ movement one thing is clear; those founding activists who survive are aggrieved at the loss of their native movement. In almost any venue in which these activists air their grievances, there is an aggregate atmosphere of nostalgia and bitterness. The perceived loss of vitality of this movement of the 1970’s is mourned. For sure, that decade was a landscape fertile for the launching of social movements, including one of deinstitutionalized and disgruntled mental patients. What then comes next?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CENSORSHIP IS A NO-NO</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/censorship-is-a-no-no/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 12:48:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/censorship-is-a-no-no/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;                                            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;275&#34; height=&#34;233&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Philip A. Kumin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;I’m a self-taught author, and a good one at that.  I tried for years to get my well written vignettes published in almost every publication imaginable including the great, the wonderful Rolling Stone Magazine.  I sought merely to partake of the joy of creative writing while simultaneously publicizing the existence and history of an unheard of, but thoroughly libertarian, movement of former mental patients.  I soon came to see that since I was revealing myself to be one of those activist patients in each piece I’d written, I was being censored accordingly.  For years afterwards, I couldn’t conceive of any rational, substantial reason why this was being done to me or any of the other patient authors, whom I had heard we’re also being censored.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Struggle with Mental Illness and Addiction</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-struggle-with-mental-illness-and-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-struggle-with-mental-illness-and-addiction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After suffering from severe mental illness for over 30 years, which started in 1989 when I was 19 years old, I am now experiencing true happiness and peace. I never thought I would ever feel this way. The following is my story, which I am telling with the hope that it might help others who are dealing with mental illness and/or addiction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I was a Victim and Came Back: My Empowerment Story</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/i-was-a-victim-and-came-back-my-empowerment-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 09:35:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/i-was-a-victim-and-came-back-my-empowerment-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;  &lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;               &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;                                              &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own story, some fortunate, some less so. Mine is a story of abuse, neglect and mental illness, and the long road back.  I offer it for whatever hope and guidance it may provide for others currently suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Me, A Victim &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1956 when I was thirteen and starting in middle school, my mother had the first of her several operations for intestinal cancer. She told me that she had “tumors,” but that meant one thing to me— cancer.  Around the same time, I, too, began having stomach pains along with constipation like hers. I always had problems getting along with other kids, being teased and harassed, and being nervous, and now I was in great distress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovery: Creating Your Personal Journey through Self-Honesty, Resilience and Hope</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recovery-creating-your-personal-journey-through-self-honesty-resilience-and-hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 05:33:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recovery-creating-your-personal-journey-through-self-honesty-resilience-and-hope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am in recovery from &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo;. I’ve always felt that the typical professional services were unable to provide the relief I needed. When I re-entered the workforce I focused my energy on these limitations. I became a peer specialist-a person in recovery trained in supportive counseling and advocacy. I also began earning my master’s degree in psychiatric rehabilitation, a field dedicated to the idea of recovery, and which takes a more holistic approach. I&amp;rsquo;ve become a constructive critic of the mental health field and found that these ideas already existed on the fringes. They continue to gain momentum and I’m excited to advocate for them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 05:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;Hi All,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phil, I agree with you on the dismal and almost criminal state of psychiatry, today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mixed feelings about Benzos, however, because of the almost unbearable chronic anxiety attacks I was having.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a pill and anxiety gone. It helped keep me alive at the time. But now, &lt;span class=&#34;aBn&#34; tabindex=&#34;0&#34; data-term=&#34;goog_1059705777&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;aQJ&#34;&gt;3 years later&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; I take a small dose of Benzos daily and I am an addict.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Borderline Personality Disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/borderline-personality-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 05:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/borderline-personality-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;My neice living in a townhouse complex - has reached the following stage:-
1-complete isolation from anybody even her sisters.
2-will not acknowledge her illness and will not accept any medication whatsoever.
3-will not allow anybody into her home.
4-all the symptons of Schizoid Personality Disorder
5-threatening to all and considers everyone responsible for her divorce that she went through several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I became a non-person and what happened afterwards.</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/how-i-became-a-non-person-and-what-happened-afterwards/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 05:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/how-i-became-a-non-person-and-what-happened-afterwards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late &amp;rsquo;90s I experienced some kind of distress of consciousness. My wife took me to the emergency room of a local hospital and I was told I had “bipolar disorder,” an incurable “mental illness” which meant I would have to be on psychiatric drugs the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know that the idea of chemical imbalances in the brain is a myth (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepuk.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34; data-saferedirecturl=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?hl=en&amp;amp;q=http://www.cepuk.org&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1475789650313000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGu704j_B60CNgPtfYGKNTpUpSpzg&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepuk.org&#34;&gt;http://www.cepuk.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). This simple story took away my humanity. How? It was a tragedy of errors. Nobody knows how consciousness arises from or is connected to the brain. It is one of the most complicated and fascinating questions of our modern age. (Start with “Conversations on Consciousness” by Susan Blackmore (2005) and go from there.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Your article on &#34;No mental illnesses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/your-article-on-no-mental-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 05:30:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/your-article-on-no-mental-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you very much for your article in regards to the validity of Bi-polar Disorder. my mother claimed to have that and other mental disorders to qualify for SSDI. Of course she had physicians who were all to eager to verify her &amp;ldquo;self diagnosis&amp;rdquo;. They saw a cash cow and I suppose so did she on a lesser scale. She was physically, mentally and verbally abusive to my brothers and me. Every time she would abuse us it was always because she had a &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo;. We were just supposed to forgive her and move on. I hate her, I hated her then and I hate her now. She stole my childhood and my brothers childhood away from us. I knew there wasn&amp;rsquo;t anything wrong with her other than the fact she was an angry person who wanted constant sympathy from others and saw my brothers and me as weapons of mass destruction for our father. I wondered why she had children in the first place if she didn&amp;rsquo;t like children. However, I digress. The main reason I agree with your article is that she not only wanted mental illness for herself she had my brothers and me diagnosed with mental disorders. Her diagnosis for me was ADHD. Honestly, I never felt that there was anything wrong with me. So she took me from one doctor to another until she found one that would diagnose me with ADHD and prescribe me Ritalin. I hated it. I felt no emotions at all when I took it. No anger but also no joy, No sadness but also no happiness. I felt like a zombie on the inside. It also caused me to have serious sleep disturbances and horrific nightmares. It was supposed to be given to me twice a day during the school year only. However she had me on it three times a day all year long for 7 years and the only thing I got out of it was a physical addiction. I have four children of my own now and withdrawing from that addiction was more physically painful than giving birth to four 10 pound babies combined. I refuse to go to doctors unless very ill or injured and don&amp;rsquo;t take any prescriptions other than Synthroid for low thyroid hormones. I think another issue with all these &amp;ldquo;mental Illness&amp;rdquo; classifications is being used to abuse children through the use of physicians. It is deplorable!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PTSD and depression???</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-and-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 05:30:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-and-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I have a story to tell, I don&amp;rsquo;t care if you like it I only need to tell it&amp;hellip; First let me tell you a little bit about me, I am 13, my real name is not Kykie, I am a girl of course, and I am mentally messed up, or so I&amp;rsquo;ve been told. I guess the first bad thing that happened, happened when I was only four, a guy my family loved and trusted, a guy I loved and trusted started sexually assaulting me (I think that&amp;rsquo;s what they ended up charging him for), this continued up until I was about 11. Nobody noticed&amp;hellip; Probably because nobody wanted it to be true. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one that got touched by him so did my two cousins but he did the most with me, he even kissed me and told me he loved me&amp;hellip; Honestly I thought I loved him too, I liked everything he did even when I knew it was wrong I still liked it, I actually wanted more. One night when he kissed me, I was he one that kissed him again and again. Even though my cousins told me multiple times he was bad news I didn&amp;rsquo;t listen. When the police came around because someone finally noticed I didn&amp;rsquo;t tell them everything he did&amp;hellip; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want too, I still wanted more from him I thought he was still a good guy. I still remember what he did, setting me on his lap and touching me, even though I knew it was wrong I never refused I never even wanted him to stop&amp;hellip; Two weeks after his arrest there was a death in the family we all knew it was coming, stage 4 brain cancer. Then nothing everything was quiet everyone treated me like a porcelain doll, fragile. Honestly, my past didn&amp;rsquo;t and doesn&amp;rsquo;t affect me but everyone else thinks it does, probably because to everyone that knows about this I act like an actual victim, like he scared me, and hurt me, like I thought everything was bad but really he never once frightened me. Then after everything settled my brother started acting out. He stared out with just smoking a little but of pot and drinking every once in a while but then everything turned around. My brother started getting aggressive getting into bad fights with my dad and attacking my mom, even hurting my siblings and me I was his first target. He stole my whole life savings from me, almost 900 dollars, that&amp;rsquo;s when I didn&amp;rsquo;t trust him anymore he did that and then I knew he doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about his family anymore, he was 15 and only cared about himself and his friends. Somewhere in that time I started cutting, and messing around with guy after guy. I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually sleep with anyone until I was about to turn 13 this year, but before I started sleeping around a bit I was doing other sexual stuff. I know it&amp;rsquo;s gross because I am so young but I felt like that was all I could do it was like it was wired into my brain, plus I have always felt older than I actually am. And to guys I was an easy target I cut, I was depressed, still am just not as bad. When I cut though I actually feel better and some people understand that and some don&amp;rsquo;t. My current boyfriend has been my longest relationship, we&amp;rsquo;ve been together for 2 months and I haven&amp;rsquo;t really done anything with him, especially since we are in different states, which is hard but we can make it. I think the reason I messed around with guys so much was I wanted to feel wanted even if it was bad, and I felt like that is what I need to do. So I told guys I was 15 or 16 and then it took off from there. My depression sky rocketed, I have attempted suicide 25 times and got caught once on an OD. I was sent to inpatient and stayed for 2 weeks, almost got sent to residential, but instead I stayed the maximum amount at inpatient and then they released me. I was put into therapy and I had to see a psychiatrist, who gave me depression meds, strong ones too. I decided to quit going and quit taking my medications cold turkey which had horrible side affects but I got over it. I&amp;rsquo;ve felt better recently I have been put into high-school AP classes after testing out for it,my brother is in drug and alcohol rehab (court ordered after not doing his probation), my boyfriend has helped A LOT (He also used to cut so kinda had an idea on how I felt), yet sometimes at least once or twice a day I still think just one cut won&amp;rsquo;t hurt, or if I was dead who would really care but in the end everyone dies might as well attempt to live miserable moments and make up for all of the stupid stuff I have done. So I guess that&amp;rsquo;s pretty much the parts of my life everyone actually finds somewhat interesting and I guess that&amp;rsquo;s what everyone sees me as&amp;hellip; I mean they can only judge me for what they know which isn&amp;rsquo;t a lot so&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>They Call This “Help”: One Man’s Tears and the Horrors of Canadian Institutional Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/they-call-this-help-one-man-s-tears-and-the-horrors-of-canadian-institutional-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 04:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/they-call-this-help-one-man-s-tears-and-the-horrors-of-canadian-institutional-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I am an inmate of St. Joseph’s Psychiatric Hospital, Hamilton, Ontario. Although I am still trapped in the intricate web of the forensic “mental health” system, I consider myself a psychiatric survivor. After all, I’ve made it this far, but I realize that more time is needed before I’m finally able to extricate myself from the forces of psychiatric oppression. Before entering the system, I knew virtually nothing about the philosophy and practice of psychiatry. After about a year and a half of being subjected to an endless, humiliating barrage of psychological and physical abuse, I have come to loathe and despise this pernicious and evil form of pseudoscience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Ex Mental health betterment</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/on-ex-mental-health-betterment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/on-ex-mental-health-betterment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;Despite a long debated idea about the abolishment of psychiatry and the futuristic dream for the once known mentally ill and ex mental health population of America and elsewhere, has left me dazed and confused about a lot of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Ex mental health patient culture to me wasn&amp;rsquo;t very helpful, I was expecting more of a professional environment, ready to help you start your career, open up flexible opportunities to make money by business networking, etc, and become a happy, successful individual and not a slave to the sadistic culture known as psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Fixed Delusion</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-fixed-delusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 04:29:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-fixed-delusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I’ve spent my adult life working in mental health services.  I worked for 15 years in residential treatment with adolescents, and another 15 years in large outpatient programs with adults.  I’ve been in clinical roles and leadership roles, primarily as a group therapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a strident cognitive behaviorist. I’ve been a passionate and sincere student of human behavior for as long as I can remember. I respect the scientific method, and try to maintain critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bipolar disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 05:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
It saddens me that there appears to be 6 distinct camps on mental illness&#39;s validity. I am convinced that Camp 1, the APA and their DSM, allow or add so many disorders, and constantly rewrite diagnosis criteria to pump up business. Camp 2: The &#34;worried well&#34; that feed this machine by seeking help for normal human behaviors that disturb them and they request or demand to be &#34;cured.&#34; Camp 3: Big Pharma, encouraging the above 2. (Advertising symptoms to advertise &#34;cures.&#34;) Camp 4: The dissenters , often those who have been misdiagnosed and fed the &#34;cure&#34; only to find out later (or hopefully sooner) that they never needed drugs to alleviate their &#34;symptoms&#34; of their &#34;abnormality. This camp also includes those affected by a loved one&#39;s misdiagnosis and altogether unnecessary &#34;treatment&#34; with drugs.  Sometimes these include those who have opinions, but no experience.  Camp 5: Those who have experienced the horrors of living with EXTREME and valid symptoms of some abnormality that cannot be verified with any medical tests. Most of these do not seek help, usually because they don&#39;t believe they are abnormal or hope against hope that these &#34;problems with living&#34; will pass and their own form of normal will return and stay. (Normal can and does indeed fall on a spectrum, which often falls far to either pole.)
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s not forget Camp 6. The dead due to suicide. They cannot defend or even explain their &amp;ldquo;stance&amp;rdquo; on it. The almost MISSING Camp is the balanced view. They (I) take ALL of the above into consideration.  I know nothing of any of the many many disorders in the DSM. (DSM 5 is frighteningly LITTERED with old and new.) I do know quite a bit about Bipolar 1, Manic Depression, WHATEVER you wish to label it.. I have 30 years of experience in and out of each camp.   Your take on the various symptoms as simply being a result of adults never outgrowing childish behaviors is probably 99% accurate. The other 1% are the only ones that are rarely mentioned, described, or outspoken about the growing controversy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klonopin and prozac withdrawal</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/klonopin-and-prozac-withdrawal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 05:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/klonopin-and-prozac-withdrawal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been almost 3 months since I have ingested any antidepressants or benzos. Almost died after drinking a large amount of vodka with the daily does of pills. Went to a rehab for a month and have been clean since. This is after over 27 years of benzos and prozac. I am 60 years old and am finally coming a awake. The Withdrawals, notably the restless leg and horrible cramping have been horrid at night, but I am totally committed to staying off the evil pills! Thanks for listening!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Write for Health</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/write-for-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/write-for-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
I am a college student who has experienced several various mentally challenging roadblocks. My mental and health issues stemmed from a previous eating disorder. I have experienced stages of anxiety, depression and eating disorder relapses. My own self harm also resulted in medical conditions that I will live with and need to be treated for for the rest of my life. On days when I am feeling low, I like to write. I never usually share my writings but today, I feel that submitting the following passage will give me a sense of relief. I encourage others experiencing road blocks in their path towards recovery to write. Write whether you want to keep it for yourself or share it like I am.
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have you ever felt so ashamed and disappointed in yourself that you can not even face a mirror? Have you ever felt so engulfed in your own thoughts that you want to scream so loud that no one, except God, can hear you? Have you ever felt so alone that you contemplated contacting someone for hours, just hovering your finger over call or send.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Sentence: Life behind bars of the Mental Healthcare system</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-sentence-life-behind-bars-of-the-mental-healthcare-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 05:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-sentence-life-behind-bars-of-the-mental-healthcare-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
I received my &#39;life sentence&#39; from a Montana psychiatrist at the tender age of 22. I was diagnosed with Bipolar because I had what he called a &#39;chemical imbalance&#39; in my brain and would need to take medicine to treat it for the rest of my life. At the time I was struggling to deal with the aftermath of two very violent rapes. One at the age of 13, the other at 19. I trusted this psychiatrist, never questioned him, or his authority. He was educated. I was not. Due to severe side effects, adverse reactions, and constant withdrawal symptoms from ALL the psychiatric drugs  approximately 75 over time) I became &#39;stuck&#39; in the revolving door of psychiatric hospitals, emergency rooms, ICU&#39;s, and jails for the next 35 years from psychiatric drug- induced: mania&#39;s, crippling depressions to the point of at least 15 suicide attempts - 2 resulting in coma, Klonopin induced anxiety developing into chronic panic attacks and finally full-blown agoraphobia when I&#39;ve never experienced this before, excruciating migraines, self-hatred, social isolation, increased alcohol use to combat the akathesia, the loss of self, anger, rage, and violence. And then my Mental Healthcare workers told me it was &#39;just fine&#39; to cold turkey from my Klonopin after 10+ years of use never mentioning one single withdrawal symptom I may experience. I was left to endure the mental torture of this withdrawal at my home, alone. I developed all the classic symptoms: light, sound sensitivity, hallucinations, sweating, anxiety/panic so extreme I didn&#39;t know the human mind could tolerate it or survive, heart palpitations, no sleep for 5 continuous days, psychosis so severe that I had no contact with Reality (at all) as I once knew it and seizures. I also became catatonic. I prayed for death every second of every minute of every hour of everyday for 6 weeks. I was denied access to my psychiatrist. Protocol was through our therapist who I tried twice only to be told &#34;No, you have to wait until your next scheduled appointment&#34;. I told her I wasn&#39;t going to last that long, and I didn&#39;t. Due to the extreme psychosis I ended up in the psyche hospital and then the ER after being in this anxiety/pure panic/psychotic state of mind with no sleep for five continuous days my body began shaking uncontrollably and I didn&#39;t know how to get it to stop. I later filed a &#39;Recipients&#39; Rights&#39; case against them for &#39;neglect of care&#39; which was DENIED because I signed a simple one-page Klonopin consent form the year before that didn&#39;t list any withdrawal symptoms. Because my Mental Healthcare wouldn&#39;t help me determine &#39;what the hell I just went through for 6 long horrific, torturous weeks&#39; (my K-pin withdrawal - 50 symptoms) if it was Benzodiazepine withdrawal or Serotonin Syndrome I decided to get off my Effexor, Trazodone, &amp;amp; Lithium because I knew I would never, ever survive another &#39;what ever that was&#39; again,and I believed it could be nowhere near as traumatic as my K-pin withdrawal. I was very wrong. Still no mention of withdrawal symptoms from workers I saw every week. Once again, the classic symptoms introduced
themselves: brain zaps, severe flu like symptoms, every muscle in my being ached, chronic insomnia (2 hrs of sleep a night for 5 months. When I was able to sleep it was only terrifying nightmares.) the ungodly uncontrollable mental anguish of the &#39;crying spells&#39; that pharmaceutical companies downplay for 5 long months, suicidality, mania, depression, compulsive-obsessive thinking, anger, rage, violence along with a host of other symptoms, but this is the most horrifying symptom I developed - homicidality. I sat at my kitchen table for months planning out this mass shooting that I knew I was going to die in. In fact, in my psychotic mind, it was not only OK, it was expected. I was a 57 year old grandmother of 9 grandchildren at the time. I should not have to know what it feels like to become a killer, let alone a mass killer. My brain became so impaired, disabled, and ragefully psychotic from these withdrawals that it&#39;s a miracle I didn&#39;t find a gun. I did put myself in a psychiatric hospital because of this where I begged them to treat me without using psychiatric drugs, only they didn&#39;t see it that way. I was &#39;Court Ordered&#39; to take Risperdal, Cogentin, Neurontin &amp;amp; Ambien and in this drug induced mental state my house burns to the ground and I&#39;m left homeless. It&#39;s been 2 1/2 years since my Klonopin withdrawal. 1 1/2 years since my Effexor, Trazodone &amp;amp; Lithium withdrawal so I&#39;m off ALL psychiatric drugs although I do have extensive cognitive impairment, but I have my own feelings, thoughts and behaviors back. I literally started my life over at the age of 57. I am now 59. And isn&#39;t it amazing that since I stopped taking my medicine the revolving door into the psych hospitals, ER, the Intensive Care Units and jails has miraculously stopped - completely. Our psychiatrists have no idea how we suffer at their hands. They refuse to acknowledge us, listen to us, or even believe what we tell them because, after all, according to them, &#34;What do we know? We&#39;re mentally ill.&#34;
&lt;p&gt;Sandra&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipolar 2 research</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-2-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 09:21:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-2-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I am a 58 year old male.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was born into a dysfunctional family with issues of shame and guilt.  I believe that this affected my psychological state. I had severe Asthma and I was unintentionally put in front of an open fire and out in a cold street in my pram where I was exposed to leaded petrol car fumes.This was very traumatic possible PTSD. we also had a long haired dog. All these things were my triggers for asthma for years to come.  We were a poor family in those days and would eat a lot of bread.Flour etc. I had skin prick testing for my Asthma allergies and was sensitive to most things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Life Story</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-life-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 05:30:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-life-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As third born of four children, I was pretty much invisible. My brother, 3 years older than me, would come home from school and we would play school and he would teach me everything he learned that day. I was five, he was eight. I idolized my big brother. I followed him everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in the first grade, my brother died, my parents got a divorce, a new man moved into the family, and we all moved to another city. For a six year old, it was just too much for me. I became a total introvert. I seldom spoke at home….only when asked a direct question. My sisters…one four years older, one four years younger …. totally ignored me. Both my sisters were pretty and popular, but not very bright. (I was the exact opposite.) They both flunked a grade….older sister flunked 7th grade, younger sister flunked 3rd grade…..how does someone flunk 3rd grade? They went to 9 different schools, just like I did….but I had a hard time always being the new kid in class.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Need Advice for my Troubling Life</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/need-advice-for-my-troubling-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 06:00:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/need-advice-for-my-troubling-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I have been struggling with bullying since middle school and I find it hard.  I will start from the beginning. I started getting bullied in middle school because i looked different. I decided to create coping skills, like watching anime and playing video games.  Indeed these skills helped me get through hard times when i was young. Middle school was bad. I experienced friendship lose, but it was out of my own stupidity. I was left alone and struggling in school.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Story</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 05:30:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I too have been digonisoed with bi- polar 11. and hve been taken lithium for the last twney four years, since 1991 nd I find that iam bter off and can fuction better without them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Reader&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depleted to Undefeated: PTSD and Me</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depleted-to-undefeated-ptsd-and-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 05:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depleted-to-undefeated-ptsd-and-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basis of my story is rooted in my own, unique experience with medical and psychiatric treatment for Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). This writing is not intended to convince or influence the necessity or use of mental health professionals. Rather, it is my perspective of what did, is, or will contribute to my personal journey towards a permanently healthier mental state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The way we were brought up and now</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-way-we-were-brought-up-and-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 06:55:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-way-we-were-brought-up-and-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written before in this. I am hoping to make something all known for you who have worked hard for freedoms we may not always get. Also i have seen some anger from the members who rightfully get angry and want to get through to the people who are not getting what the drugs can do to many. it is not just about the meds with mental health. It is a big part, but see we need to have autonomy within mental health or it will be warring forever over the things that we were duped about in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You Are Stronger Than What You Think</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/you-are-stronger-than-what-you-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 05:30:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/you-are-stronger-than-what-you-think/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I&amp;rsquo;ve never used the services of psychologists, never took a
&amp;ldquo;pill.&amp;rdquo;
But I have felt under sudden Depression and Anxiety, like any of you.
Self awareness is necessary. To know when you are not acting
&amp;ldquo;normal.&amp;rdquo;
If we keep hoping for something to happen in an unrealistic way, on
denial, and at the end of the journey we cannot achieve that goal,
DEPRESSION hits&amp;hellip;
How do I beat it?
Redirecting my mind to most realistic goals.
Recharging my mind with optimism, remembering the beautiful things we
have achieved already.
Admiring Nature, the smile of a kid: LOVING.
Exercises help. Art too.
The most important thing?
Think you have come to this world with a purpose.
Think you can help others.
Feel like a champion who can accomplish everything.
And stay away from medication:
The cure is inside you, in your mind, in your soul&amp;hellip;
Be strong!
YOU ARE STRONGER THAN WHAT YOU THINK!!!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Disease or a Decision? My Journey From Pain to Peace.</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-disease-or-a-decision-my-journey-from-pain-to-peace/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 06:00:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-disease-or-a-decision-my-journey-from-pain-to-peace/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I’m impressed with your site Phil. You are highly intelligent and an excellent writer. Some others here also state their thoughts in a clear eloquent fashion. This place is like a breath of fresh air. It&amp;rsquo;s not often I see critical thinking and logic employed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve dealt with depression, anxiety, and addiction most of my life.  I’m at peace today, after a long journey. Like millions, I was “diagnosed” with depression after a brief conversation with a “doctor” AKA “specialist”. As a kid, I had dysfunctional parents. Dad was detached and drank. Mom died when I was a baby, and as a teenager, I had a 2 year sexual relationship (my first) with my demanding narcissistic stepmother. My anger and shame was not addressed by the “specialist”, and I was given Prozac, which made me feel lifeless. For 20 years I used meth, cocaine, pills, and pot. I told people meth saved my life, because I believed I couldn’t tolerate my negative thoughts and feelings without it. I thanked God for meth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurring Depression</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recurring-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recurring-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I am 46 years old and have taken antidepressants (Lexapro, Paxil, now Zoloft) for 10 years.  But the reason I began taking them wasn&amp;rsquo;t due to my own need for relief from depression or anxiety.  It was actually an effort to improve my relationship with my husband at the time.  He suffered from depression and took medication, but said that I was overly critical, driven, intense, etc. and I think he was right.  But I was also young and immature, and am an engineer by profession.  I do have a critical thought process, no doubt.  We were mismatched from the start and separated not long after I started the medication, but have a 11 year old son together.  The divorce process, and going back to work full time as a single mom was difficult and stressful.  But after taking the Lexapro for over 4 years, I actaully began feeling lethargic and depressed and decided to stop taking it cold turkey.  Big mistake, I learned the hard way, and ended up on Paxil after a few months. Now I am having the same problem with the Paxil, and I really just want to get off the medication all together because I feel that it is causing the depression.  I was never depressed to begin with, but now I am!  After a couple of bad experiences with withdrawal symptoms from coming off the meds, I am really apprehensive about trying to taper off of them, but I want myself back, not this medicated, lethargic, irritable, unproductive person.  I was far from perfect, as my ex-husband made painfully clear, but I always had hope for a better future and energy to work for it.  I can&amp;rsquo;t help but feel that the meds have done more harm than good in my particular situation.  I just wonder if others have had similar experiences?  Thank you and best wishes in whatever you are searching for&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 years of depression</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/25-years-of-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/25-years-of-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I am 44 years old now and it took me over 25 years to conclude that I have depression caused by a physiological issue. I think it started when I was 15, I cannot be absolutely sure as it crept up very slowly – just like failing eyesight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many teenagers I would come home from school very frequently and fall asleep due to exhaustion.  This daytime sleep probably fed into an issue with insomnia that I am still learning to control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>potential lawsuit</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/potential-lawsuit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 09:46:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/potential-lawsuit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sue or not to sue. I welcome any thoughts . . . lay and/or psych opinions about the following matter. Most of the following was taken from a statement written by the patient&amp;rsquo;s daughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . . my mother and I took my father to the emergency room at Hospital due to concerns regarding his diabetes. He had not taken his insulin for several days and was having uncharacteristic confusion along with large thirst for water . . . when the woman who checked us in learned that he was diabetic, he was checked in and taken immediately to one of the rooms. My mother and I accompanied him. . . . a nurse took his blood sugar and measured it to be 485, which she said &amp;ldquo;wasn&amp;rsquo;t bad.&amp;rdquo; While in the emergency room, he continued to behave strangely, but seemed to be in good spirits. He was in good spirits and conversed with several members of staff and told them that someday he would be on TV.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>why</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 05:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/why/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I have had a severe depression since I was in high school. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had a bad life. I have had heart break and not very many good friends.  I lost my virginity to a guy after three dates at 21. and i don&amp;rsquo;t love him or anyone else right now. I dont&amp;rsquo; want to talk to him. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to see him again. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have sex again. I&amp;rsquo;ve been raped in another country, in that i was so freakin drunk that i was about to have sex on a bench, but ,managed to get up and wlak away and he let me. Now, I drink and i feel the need to cut myself. I feel so alone, so scared of this feeling inside me and so embarrassed. I thought i had overcome this in my depression \but my leg is cut up and my hands and i don&amp;rsquo;t know where else to turn. I don&amp;rsquo;t want help from &amp;lsquo;professionals&amp;rsquo;. I got drunk one time and threatened to kill myself.  I got beaten by the police and taken to the hospital. The next day i feel fine, and i know i should stop drinking, but I&amp;rsquo;m 21 and I JUST WANT TO BE NORMAL. It hurts me to know this is inside me and i hate it. The blood fades but the scars never do, and they&amp;rsquo;re on show for everyone who looks. What then? How do i explain this to other people?  My shame, my skin, my depression? I do love my life and i always think that i make this great big progressions in my depression, yet here i am, cutting myself. Is it my subconscious telling me no i&amp;rsquo;m not okay or is it my depression acting out against my own happiness. Every time that i try to go out with friends, soomething happens to make them cancel, or not be able too. And here i am, cutting myself because i dont&amp;rsquo; think that no one loves me because i&amp;rsquo;m worthless, fat, ugly, not fun, depressing, needy, scary, boring. Whatever. I&amp;rsquo;m alone, and they don&amp;rsquo;t see it. If they did, they probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even want to be around me or associated. I hate myself, because no one else seems to like me. I miss having fun and being surrounded by people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walk in mile in my shoes</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/walk-in-mile-in-my-shoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 08:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/walk-in-mile-in-my-shoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;My name is vishalatchi arunagiri, I am a 22 year old girl diagnosed with a learning disability and schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now recovering very well and have written many articles and published a book online. I am now forming my own meetup group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the illness i was sleeping and studying makeup which helped me and i started making progress in focusing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression/ ADHD</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-adhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 06:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-adhd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I was searching Google for effects of propaganda on the human psych, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;and stumbled upon this site. After reading a few stories, I felt I had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to share my own. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I was in high school I was depressed. To the point where I was a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;walking text book definition. Failing grades, poor hygiene, isolation. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;All the signs were obvious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I had to go to rehab for drinking too much cough syrup.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I went to the doctor he diagnosed me with ADHD. I have never been &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;a hyper person. always rather slow and calm.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Than he tells me that he is going to just experiment with multiple &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;drugs to see what works, and than diagnose me with whatever that drug &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;treats.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;First drug was Vyvanse (lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Its a new &amp;ldquo;abuse-free&amp;rdquo; amphetamine. Due to a coating of protein, the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;chemical can only dissolve in your stomach acid. Injecting, Smoking, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;or Snorting would not activate it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;However the prescribed dose taken once a day was enough to make me a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;full effect of amphetamines, and I began losing alot of sleep. After &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;having multiple panic attacks on this medication, I demanded the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;doctor take me off of it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;He than gave me Focalin (Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Another new &amp;ldquo;abuse-free&amp;rdquo; drug. During my younger years I experimented &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;with MDMA, and I would compare the feeling of Focalin with that of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Extacy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I got into college my doctor pulled me off of it saying that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;college kids are more likely to sell it, and that he must change my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;prescription.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Next drug was Strattera (atomoxetine). I threw up every time I took &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;it. It gave me intense piriods of happiness followed by extreme bursts &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;of anger for no reason at all.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I stopped going to the doctor, I stopped taking medications. I no &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;longer trust the medical system, the pharm companies, or even the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;government. I&amp;rsquo;d rather suffer the depression untreated than go through &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;what I went through in high school.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;On a side note, The experience made me drop out of school, and get my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;GED. That year, my school experienced a higher drop out rate than ever &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;before.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labelled</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/labelled/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2014 05:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/labelled/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I’d been seeing an NHS clinical psychologist for thirteen years.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Let’s call her Marie and me Sarah (all names are changed in my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;story). We talked about what had happened to me and how it had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;affected me, we looked at what I found difficult. We considered &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;strategies to manage my distress that sometimes manifested as profound &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;anxiety and dissociation, and at others as depression. We used &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;relaxation techniques, grounding techniques. She offered phone support &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;between appointments if she had space, set up a good plan with the GP &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;for their support and for me to use three days of low dose diazepam if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I was become overwhelmed and exhausted, just enough to get me back on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;track. I had some art therapy. We thought about all aspects of my life &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;and how I could best look after myself within my friendship/family &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;groups.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;But I began to struggle more as we wrestled the most traumatic &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;episodes of my childhood. I started to feel increasingly suicidal for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;more of the time and the self-harm increased. I needed more help. I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;lived alone. We’d often thought that were there a safe place to go, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;a restful, peaceful, caring place, that would have been so good. Marie &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;and the GP (rightly) suggested hospital would not be that and reviewed &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;what could be done. With some persuading, the Crisis Team began to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;offer me some support from 2005. They were mixed. One CPN, Matt, was &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;fantastic; most saw me as ‘hysterical’ or a bottomless pit. But &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;they didn’t know me.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt; &lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Then the Trust axed Marie’s post at a crucial point in my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;psychodynamic therapy. I was in turmoil. A new clin psych was found, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Simon. It took me a time to trust a man, but eventually work became &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;possible and we got back to exploring the part of my past that so &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;often caused me to feel I was a nothing and a no-one with no right to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;life. I felt I was fighting this beast called suicide who was sucking &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;me in such that only my toes were sticking out of its clamped jaw, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;jaws my arms could not prize open. I just had to hang on, to not be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;swallowed, for 2 days until the appointment with Simon, and then there &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;would be help.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What If You Should Be Depressed?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-if-you-should-be-depressed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 05:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-if-you-should-be-depressed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;i have been very depressed three or four times. always it was the same &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;cause. i&amp;rsquo;ve never had the experience of being depressed for no reason. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i&amp;rsquo;ve never gone to bed feeling fine and woke up feeling depressed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i think i&amp;rsquo;ve acquired enough sophistication to say:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i can&amp;rsquo;t imagine anyone under the same circumstances not becoming very &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;depressed, crying constantly, hating himself, thinking of killing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;himself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i also think the circumstances are new to human experience. that is, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;in the past my guess is such circumstances were very uncommon.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;what were they every single time: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;a beautiful girl or woman who was unavailable. but not because i was &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;ugly or boring or whatever.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;because of my family background.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i live in the us. despite college entrance exams above the mean for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;admits to all of america&amp;rsquo;s best universities. despite the same for its &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;graduate school entrance exams, i never had a chance of getting in. my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;parents divorced. my dad hit me, fornicated, was a loser.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;and so am i. social reproduction is reason enough to top yourself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the pills didn&amp;rsquo;t work. the psychiatrists and therapists were idiots.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;my solution has been alcohol.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;i&amp;rsquo;m in the following study believe it or not &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style=&#34;color: #1155cc;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.cog-genomics.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cog-genomics.org/&#34;&gt;https://www.cog-genomics.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;but i have no prospects and never will.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;anyway, blah, blah, blah&amp;hellip;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;it is a fundamental tenet of the american ideology, so to say, that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the locus of pathology is the individual, never his society and never &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the two together.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants: A Reader&#39;s Story</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-a-reader-s-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 05:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-a-reader-s-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live in São Paulo, Brazil, I&amp;rsquo;m 35 years old, single, and always said I had depression. Was considered slow, sad, spoke little, called donkey and cold, and all this time I thought it was true and should see a psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched, the psychiatrist asked a few questions, and used antidepressants, Pristiq and others. At first I was very excited, since it was a more cheerful and talkative person, but two months later went and had the effect of increasing the dose and use lamictal,the remedy worked a little, changed my personality and was a person different, but felt did not want this all my life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Service and Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-service-and-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2014 06:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-service-and-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I and my daughter are both victims of false sexual abuse allegations.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;During , the now, five year long ordeal I have witness abysmal and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;unethical behavior by the psychologists and psychiatrists involved in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;my case.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;The behavior witnessed includes the withholding of retractions by the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Social Services hand-picked psychologist The professionals act without &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;regard to the child.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;The psychologists/psychiatrists that are used by Child Protective &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Services are essentially a tool used by Social Services to win their &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;case. The professionals do not care for the children or the parents.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;They want to ensure that they testify to exactly what Social Services &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;expects of them.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Unfortunately, most attorneys do not know how to critically and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;effectively question a mental health professional.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I have no doubt that some professionals are sincere but in my specific &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;case I have observed very troubling behavior.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I would be very skeptical of any diagnosis or testimony of any &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;professional who testifies on behalf of social services. One must &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;remember to distinguish between science and pseudoscience.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Hell to Hope</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/from-hell-to-hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2014 05:58:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/from-hell-to-hope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;   &lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Can.you tell I have a cat just by looking at me?  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Can you tell I have a mental illness just by looking at me?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I began to change in my early teens, be it hormones and my shifting &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;brain chemistry, or the stress of my parents seperating. Something &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;stressor from the outside flipped on the switch to a new life filled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;with major mood swings out of my control.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Low self extreme kept me from meeting or caring about being social. I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;only went to school because I had to. Luckily one day two high school &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;girls came to my 8th grade health class and talked to us about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;everything from Stress to Smoking to Sex even Suicide. They asked us &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to write thrm a question about these topics and others. I wrote &amp;ldquo;I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;want to die&amp;quot;It was the first time I admitted to myself or anyone else &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that I had these thouhts constantly. When class was over the girls &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;kindly asked if I would like to talk to the counselor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;That day was just the beginning of my journey towards understanding &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;mental illness, and ultimately accepting mental Wellness. Over the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;next few years I spent time in psychiatric hospitals, tried medication &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that would hopefully be the missing puzzle piece of chemistry my brain &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;needed. Most of the medications tried their best but caused the worst. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I never once stopped taking the medication I was prescribed, for I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;never wanted to feel so completely out of control again. I realized I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;was accepting my chemical imbalance and each day I began to understand &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;myself and my issues in a much lighter, hopeful way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;The support I recieved on my journey towards wholness helped me &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;acknowledge I was a person not a problem. My mother was my life &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;support at times. She learned all she could about mood disorders and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;educated our family so as not to judge me, but be very proud. I also &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;met some peers within the mental health community that I still keep in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;touch with regularly. It was a blessing to know I was not alone in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;issues I faced. And that I would be accepted by my peers, for they had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experienced similar challenges.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I knew I had a message and a story to tell. I wanted to share my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experience From Hell to Hope with students. That is where my journey &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;began. So , with a father whose son has schizophrenia, and I, with my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;rapid cycling moods we have spoken to over 4,000 high school students &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;since 2006.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;My hope is to stop stigma, treating people badly because they seem &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;different. I want to promote education of mental illness so people &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;suffering and their loved ones will believe recovery is real.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s no warmer on the inside</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/it-s-no-warmer-on-the-inside/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 05:58:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/it-s-no-warmer-on-the-inside/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a 29-year-old man with a story I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to share for a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;while now.  It&amp;rsquo;s not a story of misery or desperation, for which I am &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;every day grateful.  More a story of dissatisfaction, occasional &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;crisis, and a desire to understand this whole affair of mental health.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;My upbringing was all a person could ask for, a loving and stable &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;family and a fair degree of academic success.  If anything was missing, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;it was simply the acknowledgement that sometimes people get depressed, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;anxious, or otherwise mad, and that madness in itself is a natural &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;part of life, for some of us more than others.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Survivor&#39;s Tale</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-survivor-s-tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 09:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-survivor-s-tale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;My Story&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I tried to commit suicide for the first time when I was 15. I spent my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;16th birthday locked up in Dammasch State Mental Hospital, I freaked &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;out when I was told I was going to have to stay so my clothes were &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;ripped off me, by male aids and I was thrown naked in a real padded &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;room&amp;hellip; hint they are NOT padded. The light was on all the time and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;nothing was provided for cover to keep warm. I remember seeing men &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;looking at me and I remember pictures being taken thru the peek hole &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;window. I was in that room, with meals shoved thru a slit in the door &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;for 3 days. The toilet was a hole in the floor and no, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;any toilet paper. . While at the &amp;ldquo;hospital&amp;rdquo;, I remember being put in a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;strait jacket and tied into a chair and my &amp;ldquo;meds&amp;rdquo; forced down my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;throat. When I realized I could vomit them back up I was sedated and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;given drugs via an IV. I woke up to being raped. I made friends with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;one gal, she was 14. She had ( I know know as ) anorexia. I watched &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;her try and try and try to eat. She died. Another person I made &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;friends with hung himself and died. The psy dr said I was on the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;schedule for shock treatments since I refused to co-operate with the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;rules and the staff. That scared the shit outta me. I started doing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;all the things I was supposed to do and 3 months later I was &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;released.. cured. Nothing was different for me, except I learned how &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to manipulate people to get what I wanted. I HATED that feeling so I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;never took &amp;ldquo;advantage&amp;rdquo; of that &amp;ldquo;skill&amp;rdquo;.. Remember I had just turned &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;16.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;In my early 20&amp;rsquo;s I tried to commit suicide again and committed to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;another hosp in Vancouver WA with a DX of Manic Depression. I was on a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;cocktail of lithium, stelazine, tofranil chloral hydrate and a few &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;others I can&amp;rsquo;t remember the names of .. for more than 7 years I saw a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;psychiatrist until my divorce and my insurance ran out. Dumped to fare &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the best I could into the mental health system for the poor I quit all &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;my drugs cold turkey.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;It was while under the Dr&amp;rsquo;s care I read a book he recommended called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Self-Talk. I believed I was sick with metal illness(es?) until I read &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that book. For the first time I heard no one can make me feel anyway &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;at all unless I choose to let them. That my responses to life were &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;totally under my control and direction ALL of them. I was 32. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve attempted suicide or came very very close to it 6 times in my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;life. Finally I asked myself, self, I&amp;rsquo;m smart enough to have gotten &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the job done so whats REALLY going on? I figured out WHY I kept diving &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;into the back hole. I really do walk a different, road now thanks to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;getting the message my subconscious kept sending me. Thats been my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experience with the Mental Health system. I am continually agast and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;appalled at the amount of drugs being forced onto people, particularly &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;children, We adults have been fed a line of BS for so long about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;depression that it&amp;rsquo;s destroying us as a nation and no one can see it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring a Label of ODD</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/acquiring-a-label-of-odd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 10:26:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/acquiring-a-label-of-odd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Oppositional Defiant Disorder has to be the cruellest label, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;stigmatization of all. Allegedly caused by &amp;ldquo;inconsistent Parenting&amp;rdquo; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;routinely misinterpreted to mean &amp;ldquo;different parenting styles&amp;rdquo; children &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;who are bored in school, whose coping mechanisms, eg. zoning out, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;messing in class, who are unable and or unwilling to learn &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;unchallenging material, who question, who are more advanced than their &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;peer age group are routinely labelled as O.D.D. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Is Bipolar</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-is-bipolar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 06:01:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-is-bipolar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I am a 30 year man who finally realized a few months ago (after finding this website) that he is not mentally ill but just an adult who often acts like a child. I dabbled with some &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; drugs (meaning prescribed) in the last few years when I was first diagnosed  with depression (was put on anti deps + anti anxiety pills) and then bipolar a year later (this time it was mood stabilizers and sleeping pills).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovery Model: A Reader&#39;s Story</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recovery-model-a-reader-s-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 10:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/recovery-model-a-reader-s-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very interested to read some of your very clearly reasoned, explained and referenced posts. I am familiarising myself with the status of the Recovery Model of mental health for my new job and have repeatedly come across critiques of modern psychiatry and the DSM diagnosis. I am encouraged by this line of questioning because I have 7 years experience with the Grow peer support program for recovery and personal development. Like many recovery programs, it largely ignores diagnosis, seeks to recognise and draw out the strength and human potential in all of us and has helped many people to dispense with meds altogether and live a productive, peaceful and happy life. In contrast I have found it heartbreaking to see the dehumanising &amp;ldquo;flattening&amp;rdquo; of friends when they have been heavily medicated or zapped. Learning how to constructively experience, integrate and grow from the disappointments and challenges of life has been preventative for me and taken me off the slippery path of unhealthy thoughts and attitudes. Professional therapists need to see psych patients as humans first with intrinsic value and untold potential. They need to see the purpose of medication as the end of medication. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Story: Schizoid Personality</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-story-schizoid-personality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 05:45:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-story-schizoid-personality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my teenage years I met the World Health Organization&amp;rsquo;s criteria for &amp;ldquo;schizoid personality disorder&amp;rdquo;.  At the time, I did not consider the possibility that there might be anything wrong with me. Instead, I believed that my isolation was a result of a lack of social understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at age eighteen, when I left my harmful family environment to go to college, I set out to remedy this lack of social skills. I broke off communication with every one of my high school associates and set out to meet lots of new people and involve myself in many social activities. Meanwhile, I learned everything I could about human behavior. I researched history, economics and art; biology, anthropology and evolution. I learned the principles of marketing and tried them out in real life. I visited websites and combed one-by-one through what amounts to perhaps a thousand individual psychological research summaries. Then I examined the mathematics of information theory and machine learning to put this all together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHOOSING A DIRECTION:  PSYCHIATRY VS RECOVERY</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/choosing-a-direction-psychiatry-vs-recovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 05:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/choosing-a-direction-psychiatry-vs-recovery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;navbar&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;Navbar1&#34;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;navbar-iframe-container&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Norwegian psychiatrist has written a book for children with the title «&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.na24.no/article3668539.ece&#34;&gt;Pappa’n min er syk i tankene sine»,&lt;/a&gt; which translates into «My daddy is ill in his thoughts».&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applaud her wish to help children understand what is going on when a parent is having mental problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also disagree with the belief system she writes within, the idea that depression and anxiety and psychosis are illnesses of the thoughts or brain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Galvanizing of a POOR HISTORIAN</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-galvanizing-of-a-poor-historian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 13:28:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-galvanizing-of-a-poor-historian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In hospital ED records from 2007, there is a mention made by a doctor who was dictating his activities, observations of and involvement with me during 5 hours, that I am a&amp;quot;poor historian.&amp;quot; Ironically, I have to this day never met with or even seen this doctor, and vice versa. The conclusion was followed by a little post-script stating that he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know me from Adam if he saw me, despite having written the entire account of me from the first person perspective. Really, I provided very little history, because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really asked, (something I figured was attributable to the hospital records department having in its own filed the most substantial majority of records and historical accounting from me, having been in an adult intensive outpatient program for two years, following a month long inpatient procedure, and after the two years of intensive, was still an outpatient scheduling check-in and progress check-up on a more casual schedule over six months &amp;hellip; right up to the day that all information pertaining to me became non-existent, and new diagnoses, and history of the new diagnoses were filled in. I was not, however, even examined under any terms that might pass for making an effort to actually determine a diagnostic impression, no evaluation nor anything close was performed, but my previously [assumed] diagnosis for which I had been seeing a private doctor regularly, being monitored on medications and therapy for Bi-Polar II (actually it was never diagnosed, I was being treated for &amp;ldquo;target symptoms,&amp;rdquo; which were actually the result of a tardive syndrome induced by olonzapine -cycling between moderate to mild akathisia and fatigue resulting from it) , but records would have shown enough target symptom treatment to inform that I was Bi-Polar II. Bi-Polar [any] was R/O in the newly made that day diagnoses: Psychosis NOS R/O BI-POLAR, and Schizophrenia with history of Schizophrenia (that was the info written in by the phantom Doctor who divined these from no disclosed resource (perhaps Spiritual PhytoEssencing that randomly penetrates his 5th and 6th Chakra in the form of Sound-Thought Ethereal Essence guiding his knowledge, or maybe he was told to write up something for em stat purposes only w/o any responsibility for or contact with the patient, as he noted at the end). It&amp;rsquo;s curious that in my medical history and records, it was first recognized that I am a &amp;ldquo;Poor Historian.&amp;rdquo; What makes me a poor historian in effect today (my records and history are so toxic and viral, far beyond errors, that to allow for them to be transmitted to any new health provider w/o undergoing a major audit and revision into something that seems like it can pass meaningful use muster, would probably direct a well-intentioned but lethal course of treatment, in addition to being a DANGER TO SHIPPING).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dead from Meds</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dead-from-meds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 14:12:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dead-from-meds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;My sister was diagnosed at that difficult time when she had to get a job after college. She was shy and fearful too, about life but not growing up in the cocoon of a large family, the youngest of 6 children. I was the oldest girl and required to work at the family business every summer starting at 9 years old. Sis, I will call her di not have to do anything. 6 years younger than me she was bought expensive clothes because my parents had more money. I was bought cheap things and when I hit 16 was told that I had to buy all my clothes from then on. I left and now am so glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why dont you tell the truth about being a Scientologist?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/why-dont-you-tell-the-truth-about-being-a-scientologist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 15:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/why-dont-you-tell-the-truth-about-being-a-scientologist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The following post is a part of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/category/tell-your-story/&#34;&gt;“Tell Your Story” category&lt;/a&gt;, where our readers submit their stories about their contact with the mental health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was originally a submission in our forum by &lt;em&gt;Jaymax&lt;/em&gt;, before we changed to the new submission format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-27&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;Jaymax
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why dont you tell the truth about being a Scientologist?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;February 15, 2013, 04:50&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Dear Phil.Why don&#39;t you tell the truth about being a Scientologist from the Church of Scientology? And that&#39;s why you campaign against psychiatry with misinformation and lies?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-28&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;Phil
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re: Why dont you tell the truth about being a Scientologist?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;February 15, 2013, 10:34&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Jaymax,I am not a member of the Church of Scientology, or indeed of any church. As to why I criticize psychiatry, it is because it is based on spurious and invalid premises and does an enormous amount of harm.If you believe that I disseminate &#34;misinformation and lies,&#34; then please come back and specify.Best wishes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-29&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;Jaymax
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re: Why dont you tell the truth about being a Scientologist?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;February 20, 2013, 01:46&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Really? You sound EXACTLY like a Scientologist ranting about the evils of psychiatry.My main issue is actually that your knowledge of the field mental health is so outdated and lacking. Do you not believe in ongoing education and Professional Development?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-30&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;Phil
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re: Why dont you tell the truth about being a Scientologist?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;February 21, 2013, 10:19&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Jaymax,Thanks for coming in.Firstly, the only common ground between Scientologists and me is the fact that we criticize modern psychiatry. Our reasons are very different.Secondly, I don&#39;t rant.
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, perhaps my knowledge of the field is outdated and lacking. I certainly don&amp;rsquo;t claim to know everything. The critical question, however, is this – &lt;i&gt;specifically&lt;/i&gt; what errors am I making? What am I missing? What am I getting wrong? Attacking me because I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;outdated&amp;rdquo; serves no purpose. Snidely questioning my commitment to education gets us nowhere. Instead, provide me &lt;i&gt;one piece&lt;/i&gt; of hard evidence that contradicts my position. One fact is better than a thousand ad hominem attacks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello Phil</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/hello-phil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 15:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/hello-phil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The following post is a part of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/category/tell-your-story/&#34;&gt;“Tell Your Story” category&lt;/a&gt;, where our readers submit their stories about their contact with the mental health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was originally a submission in our forum by &lt;em&gt;normac&lt;/em&gt;, before we changed to the new submission format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-18&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;normac
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello Phil&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;September 11, 2012, 16:31&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;I happened upon your blog a few days ago, and have a few questions about bipolar.Hope you are doing better, as I observed you were off due to surgery.
&lt;p&gt;My story is long, as most people with a mental illness can attest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia is a broken spirit</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-a-broken-spirit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 15:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-a-broken-spirit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The following post is a part of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/category/tell-your-story/&#34;&gt;“Tell Your Story” category&lt;/a&gt;, where our readers submit their stories about their contact with the mental health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was originally a submission in our forum by &lt;em&gt;lonewolf&lt;/em&gt;, before we changed to the new submission format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-9&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;lonewolf
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/forum/?mingleforumaction=viewtopic&amp;amp;t=4#postid-9&#34;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schizophrenia is a broken spirit&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;March 22, 2012, 12:24&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;My younger brother was diagnosed with schizophrenia about 8 years ago. Since then, my mother and father have been so immensely sad watching my brother not be able to hold down a job, talk to himself, laugh to himself, pace around the backyard of my parents home, and not have a an adult life with adult responsibilities.I never accepted that diagnosis for him. I refused to believe that he had a chemical imbalance without PROOF of a chemical imbalance. Human beings are capable of all kinds of behavior. Just because a behavior doesn’t fit in with this particular culture, at this particular point in time, doesn’t mean that the person is suffering from an illness. Furthermore, most people suffering from an illness WANT to get better. I never felt Joe wanted to get better. I could see it in his eyes that he discovered a loophole, a way out. A way to get disability checks, sympathy from my parents, etc. Everyone and the system was reinforcing his behavior.Since Joe is my brother, only 2.5 years younger than me, I feel I know him pretty well. I know that he’s sensitive and shy and would get embarrassed. I also know that some of his life skills aren’t the best (neither were mine when I was a young adult but I kept thrashing forward). Joe went to school after high school and graduated from DeVry with an electronics degree. At around the age of 23-24, he got a job at FedEx as an IT support person. After a few incidents at work where he didn’t have a solution to a problem right away, he got embarrassed and quit. Instead of telling the person with the computer issue, “hold on, let me go ask someone else”, or go and google an answer, or simply state that he is not sure but will spend a few hours or days figuring it out. He instead came home and started crying to my parents that he doesn’t feel “normal”. I knew that life was tough. People take for granted how tough life is. I knew what he was going through. He needed to be told that he has the skills to do good at that job. He needed to be encouraged to go back out there the next day. Instead my parents took that too mean that perhaps he had some weakness, or problem. Perhaps he was depressed? They weren&#39;t sure so from that moment on, he was set off on a journey of phsychologists, psychiatrists, therapists, rehab, detox, mental hospitals, prison, currently Joe roaming the streets asking people for money.It was great for Joe. For the most part he could sit at home, smoke cigarettes all day, which my parents would by for him. I was told to speak gently to Joe since he was &#34;under a lot of stress&#34;. Joe knew he had my parents fooled and that they would now allow him to sit at home and do nothing. But his little plan has backfired on him. He has stopped evolving and has therefore lost his friends, is not capable of talking to women, has no money, etc. And is now much unhappier than he ever would have been if he simply plowed through life&#39;s challenges on his own.
&lt;p&gt;It’s sad watching him deteriorate like this. But I firmly believe that what he is suffering from is a broken spirit, not a chemical imbalance. He needs to be in a place where he is not allowed to smoke, drink alcohol, or smoke grass. He needs discipline and routine. He needs an environment where he is rewarded for good behavior and punished for bad behavior. He needs to be exercising regularly, eating nutritious foods, going to sleep and waking up at regular hours, and someone needs to work with him to slowly build up life skills and confidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One guys story.</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/one-guys-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:56:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/one-guys-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The following post is a part of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/category/tell-your-story/&#34;&gt;“Tell Your Story” category&lt;/a&gt;, where our readers submit their stories about their contact with the mental health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was originally a submission in our forum by &lt;em&gt;jonnyworthington&lt;/em&gt;, before we changed to the new submission format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-2&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;jonnyworth-
ington
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One guys story.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;August 8, 2011, 02:59&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;What can I say, I finally found some rational thinking out here.
I guess I will start about 15 years ago, I was an angry teenager. I wanted less restrictions, more time with my girlfriend, so on and so on. Typical teenager stuff.
Then I decided to ditch school, and home, and maybe get my parents attention. It most certainly did and it launched me into the modern world of psychiatry. It is indeed an odd world.
I left home and school, so my parents were convinced something must be wrong with me.
I didn&#39;t think there was, but they thought I had ADD, put me on some medicine. I also found it hard to connect the dots, but they put me on something, so my parents thought it was an answer.
Fast forward about nine years, and once again, pressure from the &#39;rents, and I was being put on adderall, which I will say was a &#39;productive&#39; drug. I could have built bridges in hours, lots of energy. I guess thats what speed will do with you. Stopped taking that after a few months because it just didn&#39;t seem normal. It was just making me more productive doing something I didn&#39;t want to be doing.
Moving along the next few years, I took up drinking, heavily at times. Got into a hole and got a sort-of intervention staged on me. Went to rehab, shrinks, and they decided I had bipolar. I took med&#39;s and did the rehab. I found that lamictal, and depakote are great ways to put a tarp over creativity, insight, and general joy of living. Struggled with rehab a bit, and was on and off the bottle. I was looking for an answer, and a rational answer.
I found the modern behavioral health system to be flawed in its dealings with substance abuse, mainly the fact that they all subscribe to something similar to AA&#39;s 12 steps. Powerless? Not in control of my life and circumstace? Seemed awfully unlikely to me, so I treated myself. I read, looked for answers and stumbled upon Rational Recovery. It made a lot of sense to me, as it treated an addiction as one. Something that can be beaten by out thinking the problem itself. It works, its just knowing yourself enough, and taking the time to get to know yourself. I have been clean for a couple of months, and its the easiest time I have had with it in years. Problem solved, and all I needed was to understand my own brain.
So I searched some more online, and found this site, and I guess its nice to see some &#39;alternate&#39; thinking. I just find it difficult that western society has quickly gotten on board with the &#39;science&#39; of psychology.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-3&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34; width=&#34;100&#34;&gt;Phil
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re: One guys story.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on: &lt;/strong&gt;August 12, 2011, 18:03&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap=&#34;nowrap&#34; width=&#34;10%&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Jonny,Thanks for coming in and telling your story. My major criticism of substance abuse “treatment” ( at least in the US) is the over-reliance on AA. Some treatment units, in fact, do little more than induct the client into AA and teach the so-called twelve steps. The problem with this approach is that AA is a religion and doesn’t sit well with people who are not religiously inclined. The traditionalists, however, usually insist that there is only one way to get sober, i.e. through AA, and they imply that the individuals who don’t or won’t embrace AA have some defect or character flaw that inevitably prevents their attaining sobriety. But you probably know more about all this than I do.I’m glad you found Rational Recovery, and I hope that you continue to do well. Once again, thanks for coming in, and best wishes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force someone to change his Religion</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/force-someone-to-change-his-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/force-someone-to-change-his-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The following post is a part of our &lt;a title=&#34;Tell Your Story&#34; href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/category/tell-your-story/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tell Your Story&amp;rdquo; category&lt;/a&gt;, where our readers submit their stories about their contact with the mental health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was originally a submission in our forum by &lt;em&gt;AlmuntherAlmaktoum&lt;/em&gt;, before we changed to the new submission format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;postid-4&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
&lt;table width=&#34;100%&#34; cellspacing=&#34;0&#34; cellpadding=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&#34;2&#34; valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Hi,
I am sharing a series of forum posts written by a friend of mine. This is a man who suffered from Schizophrenia, has had a criminal history and had 7 relapses.I am posting this because recently, he was able to challenge his delusions and through a tolerant religious belief system was able to remain off the medication and function normally in society.Unfortunately due the flaws with modern psychological treatment that most readers of this website are familiar with, he has been forced to take drugs and consequently he has lost the belief that helped him challenge his delusion.I am also sharing an audio recording that he did of a recent meeting with his carers.&lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytreatmentcase.com/?q=node/1#attachments&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://involuntarytreatmentcase.com/?q=node/1#attachments&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has given me permission to share all this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
