<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Dealing With Problems of Daily Living on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/dealing-with-problems-of-daily-living/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dealing With Problems of Daily Living on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 05:30:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/dealing-with-problems-of-daily-living/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  The Hoax Unravels</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of stating the obvious, ADHD is not an illness.  Rather, it is an unreliable and disempowering label for a loose collection of arbitrarily chosen and vaguely defined behaviors.  ADHD has been avidly promoted as an illness by pharma-psychiatry for the purpose of selling stimulant drugs.  In which endeavor, they have been phenomenally successful, but, as in other areas of psychiatry, the hoax is unraveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression:  A Different Perspective</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-a-different-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 05:30:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-a-different-perspective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently come across an interesting paper:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://egg.bu.edu/~youssef/SNAP_CLUB/depression.pdf&#34;&gt;How to Understand and then Escape from Depression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Saul Youssef, a professor of &lt;em&gt;physics&lt;/em&gt; at Boston University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central theme of the paper is that persistent or chronic depression is caused by &amp;ldquo;…an unconscious withdrawal of participation in a person’s own internal decision making processes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have been depressed for most of my life, and, at various times, I have tried most of the recommended treatments for depression. I have tried Saint John’s Wort, exercise, Yoga, talk therapy, SSRIs, thyroid supplements and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy. In my case, I would say that thyroid supplements, exercise and Yoga helped the most and all of them helped at least a little bit.  Unfortunately, none of these treatments helped dramatically. Then, however, in late 2013 and early 2014, I finally figured it out. I came to understand what was happening in my own head and why it was causing my own depression and I was able to figure out a way to escape. I don’t mean that I am now successfully managing my depression. I mean it’s gone. I am writing up what I think is going on and what I did to escape because I don’t think that my case is unusual. I think that exactly the same thing will work for many people.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants:  Drugs, Not Medication</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 05:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 7, John Read, PhD, a psychologist at Swinburne University of Technology in Melbourne, published a short article on Mad in America.  The title is:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/04/largest-survey-date-finds-high-rates-emotional-interpersonal-adverse-effects-antidepressants/&#34;&gt;Largest Survey of Antidepressants Finds High Rates of Adverse Emotional and Interpersonal Effects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article presents the results of a survey conducted in New Zealand and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy-journal.com/article/S0165-1781%2814%2900083-3/abstract&#34;&gt;published online&lt;/a&gt; in February, 2014 in Psychiatry Research.  The survey involved 1,827 individuals who were taking antidepressants.  Dr. Read is widely published. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peter Kinderman in Scientific American.  An Important Milestone!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/peter-kinderman-in-scientific-american-an-important-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 05:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/peter-kinderman-in-scientific-american-an-important-milestone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 17, Scientific American published on its MIND blog website &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/mind-guest-blog/2014/11/17/why-we-need-to-abandon-the-disease-model-of-mental-health-care/&#34;&gt;Why We Need to Abandon the Disease-Model of Mental Health Care&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;by Peter Kinderman, PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The idea that our more distressing emotions such as grief and anger can best be understood as symptoms of physical illnesses is pervasive and seductive. But in my view it is also a myth, and a harmful one. Our present approach to helping vulnerable people in acute emotional distress is severely hampered by old-fashioned, inhumane and fundamentally unscientific ideas about the nature and origins of mental health problems. We need wholesale and radical change, not only in how we understand mental health problems, but also in how we design and commission mental health services.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Or Revolution?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/evolution-or-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 05:30:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/evolution-or-revolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 22, Just Another Word Press.com site ran an article called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mtaspsychologyblog.wordpress.com/2014/07/22/evolution-not-revolution-my-thoughts-on-the-dcps-call-for-a-paradigm-shift/&#34;&gt;Evolution not revolution: My thoughts on the DCP’s call for a paradigm shift&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;The website is owned and operated by MTAS Psychology, an agency providing psychological therapy and expert witness services in Manchester, UK.  The article is unsigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary focus of the article is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;paradigm shift paper&lt;/a&gt; issued on May 13, 2013 by the British Psychological Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Clinical Psychology.  That paper, as readers may remember, drew attention to &amp;ldquo;conceptual and empirical limitations&amp;rdquo; inherent in psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s so-called diagnostic system, and called for a paradigm shift – &amp;ldquo;towards a conceptual system not based on a &amp;lsquo;disease&amp;rsquo; model.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blame the Clients?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/blame-the-clients/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 05:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/blame-the-clients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 6, I wrote a post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/06/06/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry DID Promote the Chemical Imbalance Theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/06/psychiatry-promote-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;published on Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;, and generated a number of comments on that site, five of which were from TherapyFirst, who in his first comment identified himself as Joel Hassman, MD, a practicing psychiatrist.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hassman did not argue with the general notion that psychiatric practice today consists almost exclusively of the prescription of drugs.  Indeed, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantmedicatelife.com/2013/06/16/an-open-letter-to-graduating-psychiatry-residents/&#34;&gt;one of his own blog posts&lt;/a&gt; on June 16, 2013, he wrote in an open letter to newly qualified psychiatrists:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Toddlers for Inattention, Impulsivity, and Hyperactivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-toddlers-for-inattention-impulsivity-and-hyperactivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 05:58:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-toddlers-for-inattention-impulsivity-and-hyperactivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, the New York Times ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/17/us/among-experts-scrutiny-of-attention-disorder-diagnoses-in-2-and-3-year-olds.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thousands of Toddlers Are Medicated for A.D.H.D., Report Finds, Raising Worries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;by Alan Schwarz.  Here is the opening sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;More than 10,000 American toddlers 2 or 3 years old are being medicated for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder outside established pediatric guidelines, according to data presented on Friday by an official at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The CDC official is Susanna Visser, MS, DrPh, Acting Associate Director of Science for the Division of Human Development and Disability, and she was speaking at the annual Rosalyn Carter Georgia Mental Health Forum.  I have not been able to find the text of Ms. Visser&#39;s speech.  (It will probably be published later.)  Meanwhile, there is a good deal of information in Alan Schwarz&#39;s article.  Here are some more quotes:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The report, which found that toddlers covered by Medicaid are particularly prone to be put on medication such as Ritalin and Adderall, is among the first efforts to gauge the diagnosis of A.D.H.D. in children below age 4. Doctors at the Georgia Mental Health Forum at the Carter Center in Atlanta, where the data was presented, as well as several outside experts strongly criticized the use of medication in so many children that young.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critique of the Schizophrenia Diagnosis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-critique-of-the-schizophrenia-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 05:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-critique-of-the-schizophrenia-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In January 2014, the journal Research on Social Work Practice ran a special issue called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rsw.sagepub.com/content/24/1.toc&#34;&gt;A Critical Appraisal of the DSM-5: Social Work Perspectives&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt; There are fifteen articles on this general theme, and together they present a wide range of arguments against the DSM system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social workers represent the numerically biggest group of mental health practitioners in the US, and it is particularly gratifying to see a major social work journal addressing this topic so forthrightly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;ADHD&#39; and Dangerous Driving</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 05:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Laurence Jerome, a Canadian psychiatrist, and two colleagues wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/ADHD-and-Driving-Jerome-et-al-ccap15_3p105.pdf&#34;&gt;What We Know About ADHD and Driving Risk: A Literature Review, Meta-Analysis and Critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It was published in the Journal of the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry in August, 2006. The primary result of the meta-analysis was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Current data support the utility of stimulant medication in improving driving performance in younger ADHD drivers.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The study is lengthy and well-referenced, but in keeping with standard psychiatric practice, it conceptualizes and presents ADHD as a &#34;…common psychiatric disorder…&#34; with symptoms of &#34;…inattention, impulsiveness and hyperactivity…&#34;  In other words, they present ADHD as something that a person &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; rather than as something that a person &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; The problem with this approach is that it creates the impression that meaningful or significant correlations/effects have been found, where in fact all that has happened is an elucidation of the terms used.
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the authors refer to a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Fried%2C+R.%2C+Petty%2C+C.R.%2C+Surman%2C+C.B.%2C+Reimer%2C+B.%2C+Aleardi%2C+M.%2C+Martin%2C+J.M.+2006&#34;&gt;Fried et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2006) and state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Fights Back – With More PR</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-fights-back-with-more-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 05:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-fights-back-with-more-pr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;About six months ago, I wrote a post called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/10/14/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Health Care Reform and Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.  In that article, I gave a brief account of the APA&amp;rsquo;s Council on Communications, and I expressed the belief that the council seemed more concerned with PR (in the most tawdry sense of the term) than with any serious examination or reform of psychiatric practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Lately, I was browsing the APA blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://apahealthyminds.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Healthy Minds, Healthy Lives&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, and it seemed that a good deal of what I was reading seemed to have a fairly heavy PR component.  So I opened the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatry.org/advocacy--newsroom/council-on-communications&#34;&gt;Council on Communications&lt;/a&gt; tab and found that their lead page is pretty much as it was six months ago.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perfect Psychiatrist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 05:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On March 19, a new article was posted on Aeon Magazine.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/magazine/being-human/have-psychiatrists-lost-perspective-on-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;A Mad World&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and was written by Joseph Pierre, MD, who works in Log Angeles as a psychiatric practitioner and professor.  Dr. Pierre has authored more than fifty papers, and has received several awards.  He has lectured nationally and internationally, and would, I think, be considered an eminent psychiatrist.  I am grateful to several readers for the link to the article.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benzodiazepines: Disempowering and Dangerous</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/benzodiazepines-disempowering-and-dangerous/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 05:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/benzodiazepines-disempowering-and-dangerous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I recently read an article by Fredric Neuman, MD, Director of the Anxiety and Phobia Center at White Plains Hospital, NY.  The article is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/fighting-fear/201206/the-use-the-minor-tranquilizers-xanax-ativan-klonopin-and-valium&#34;&gt;The Use of the Minor Tranquilizers: Xanax, Ativan, Klonopin, and Valium&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and was published in June 2012 by Psychology Today.  Thanks to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/medskep&#34;&gt;Medicalskeptic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; for the link.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Neuman opens by telling us that benzodiazepines are &amp;ldquo;…very commonly prescribed for any sort of discomfort.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Involuntary Mental Health Commitments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-mental-health-commitments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 05:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-mental-health-commitments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The recent publicity surrounding the Justina Pelletier case has focused attention, not only on the spurious and arbitrary nature of psychiatric diagnoses, but also on the legitimacy and appropriateness of mental health commitments.  It is being widely asserted that these archaic statutes are fundamentally incompatible with current civil rights standards, and the question &amp;ldquo;should mental health commitments be abolished?&amp;rdquo; is being raised in a variety of contexts.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;CRITERIA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Our Children:  A Book Review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-our-children-a-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 05:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-our-children-a-book-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Drugging-Our-Children-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4320&#34; alt=&#34;Drugging Our Children &#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Drugging-Our-Children-2-233x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;163&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The 2012 book &lt;em&gt;Drugging Our Children: How Profiteers Are Pushing Antipsychotics on Our Youngest, and What We Can Do to Stop It&lt;/em&gt;, is edited by Sharna Olfman PhD, and Brent Dean Robbins, PhD.  It is a collection of ten articles, plus an Introduction and an Afterword by Sharna Olfman.  Here are the chapter titles, with a quote from each:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Introduction&lt;/i&gt;, by Sharna Olfman, PhD&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Is Bipolar</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/life-is-bipolar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 06:01:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/life-is-bipolar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I am a 30 year man who finally realized a few months ago (after finding this website) that he is not mentally ill but just an adult who often acts like a child. I dabbled with some &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; drugs (meaning prescribed) in the last few years when I was first diagnosed  with depression (was put on anti deps + anti anxiety pills) and then bipolar a year later (this time it was mood stabilizers and sleeping pills).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  Are We Helping Or Harming?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 06:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In November 2013, the British Medical Journal published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://charlesmarsan.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Overdiagnosis-ADHD.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: are we helping or harming?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Rae Thomas, PhD, Psychologist, Australia; Geoffrey K. Mitchell, MB BS, FRACGP, PhD, Professor of General Practice, Australia; and Laura Batstra, PhD, Psychologist, Netherlands.  The article is part of a series on the dangers of overdiagnosis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Prevalence and prescribing rates for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) have risen steeply over the past decade, partly in response to concerns about underdiagnosis and undertreatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovery Model: A Reader&#39;s Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/recovery-model-a-reader-s-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 10:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/recovery-model-a-reader-s-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very interested to read some of your very clearly reasoned, explained and referenced posts. I am familiarising myself with the status of the Recovery Model of mental health for my new job and have repeatedly come across critiques of modern psychiatry and the DSM diagnosis. I am encouraged by this line of questioning because I have 7 years experience with the Grow peer support program for recovery and personal development. Like many recovery programs, it largely ignores diagnosis, seeks to recognise and draw out the strength and human potential in all of us and has helped many people to dispense with meds altogether and live a productive, peaceful and happy life. In contrast I have found it heartbreaking to see the dehumanising &amp;ldquo;flattening&amp;rdquo; of friends when they have been heavily medicated or zapped. Learning how to constructively experience, integrate and grow from the disappointments and challenges of life has been preventative for me and taken me off the slippery path of unhealthy thoughts and attitudes. Professional therapists need to see psych patients as humans first with intrinsic value and untold potential. They need to see the purpose of medication as the end of medication. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Psychology Going the Way of Psychiatry?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/is-psychology-going-the-way-of-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 05:45:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/is-psychology-going-the-way-of-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 7, Maria Bradshaw, co-founder of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.casper.org.nz/&#34;&gt;CASPER&lt;/a&gt;, published an interesting article on Mad in America.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/01/prescribing-rights-psychologists/&#34;&gt;Prescribing Rights for Psychologists&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and it suggests that psychology as a profession may be falling into some of the same errors that enmire psychiatry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria makes some very compelling points, and focuses particularly on the fact that psychologists have won prescribing rights in a number of jurisdictions, and are engaged in an ongoing effort to expand this aspect of their work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Human Behavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 05:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A couple of months ago I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/11/21/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/&#34;&gt;article concerning ECT&lt;/a&gt; which generated some controversy.  One of the issues that came up was the relationship between &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;biological &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;explanations of human activity and more global explanations, which, for want of a better term, I&amp;rsquo;ll call person-centered explanations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any human activity can be viewed from different levels of abstraction.  Suppose, for instance, that I am sitting in my living room reading a book.  Then I put the book down, stand up, and go outside.  If the question were to be asked:  why did he put the book down and go outside? A wide range of perspectives and answers are possible.  One could, for instance, focus on the fact that I am a biological organism, and one could develop a detailed and comprehensive flow sheet of every muscle movement, every heartbeat, every sensory input, neural impulse etc., that had occurred from the moment that I put the book down until I was standing outside.  Such an account might be more or less detailed.  There would, of course, be physical limitations on the amount of information of this sort that is attainable, but from a theoretical point of view, one could compile a detailed, complete, and accurate biological account of the actions in question.  And such an account would be a valid response to the question:  why did he put the book down and go outside.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizoid Personality Disorder</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/schizoid-personality-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 05:51:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/schizoid-personality-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/16/my-story-schizoid-personality/&#34;&gt;new entry&lt;/a&gt; on the Tell Your Story section of my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, who wishes to remain anonymous, tells how during his teenage years, his social skills were poor, and he met the criteria for schizoid personality disorder, the essential features of which are social isolation and emotional detachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;By the end of this project I had developed solid social skills, created an interesting circle of friends and no longer met the criteria for &#39;schizoid personality disorder&#39;. This is without any psychiatry, medication, or even the knowledge that I was &#39;suffering&#39; from something that many consider a &#39;disorder&#39;.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness: A Man-made Monster</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 05:45:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3758&#34; alt=&#34;Nelson Mandela quote&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote-300x210.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the above image online yesterday, at the site &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thethingswesay.com/&#34;&gt;The Things We Say&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental illness is also man-made.  It is the invention of psychiatry - their spurious medicalization of all significant problems of thinking, feeling, and/or behaving.  Its purpose is to legitimize the prescription of dangerous psychotropic drugs to as many people as possible.   &lt;strong&gt;It benefits psychiatrists and drug companies, but damages, stigmatizes, and disempowers its victims.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Disease-Centered Model Vs. The Drug-Centered Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-disease-centered-model-vs-the-drug-centered-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 05:55:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-disease-centered-model-vs-the-drug-centered-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Joanna Moncrieff is an eminent British psychiatrist, a founding member of the Critical Psychiatry Network, and the author of several papers and books, including &lt;i&gt;The Myth of the Chemical Cure&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Bitterest Pills&lt;/i&gt;.  I have discussed both of these books on this website, and I recommend them highly.  Dr. Moncrieff speaks out clearly and fearlessly about the concepts and practices that drive modern psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both of the books mentioned above, Dr. Moncrieff advocates a shift from a disease-centered model of drug action to a drug-centered model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/protecting-the-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/protecting-the-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/1636&#34;&gt;Safeguarding a Generation of Children from Over-diagnosis and Prescription of Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Dave Traxson, who works as an Educational Psychologist in the UK, and is posted on the  DxSummit website, an online platform for rethinking mental health, a forum in which the concepts underlying pharma-psychiatry are questioned and challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I view the trend towards mass medication of children with mind altering and potentially toxic drugs and ‘drug cocktails’ as a form of psycho-economic imperialism. By that I mean that young peoples’ developing minds are being colonized, using biochemicals, for huge commercial profit and in effect, increased social control. This has resulted from carefully constructed ‘business plans’ in boardrooms which some years ago saw the population of children in the western world as a great market expansion opportunity. The pharmaceutical companies have reaped the huge financial rewards of this rich and very bitter harvest ever since.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Allen Frances – Lucy Johnstone Debate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 05:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Allen Frances, MD, Chairperson of the DSM-IV task force, published an article on Psychology Today.  It is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201310/does-it-make-sense-scrap-psychiatric-diagnosis-0&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Does It Make Sense To Scrap Psychiatric Diagnosis?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and is essentially a response to the British Psychological Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Clinical Psychology&amp;rsquo;s (DCP) call to abandon the medical model in situations where it is not appropriate, and to embrace a psychosocial approach.  You can see a copy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;DCP&amp;rsquo;s May 13, 2013, statement here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Psychiatric Case Study.  A Sad Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-psychiatric-case-study-a-sad-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 06:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-psychiatric-case-study-a-sad-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the criticisms that I routinely make of psychiatry is that its primary agenda during initial evaluations is the assignment of a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis,&amp;rdquo; and that ongoing &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; consists of 15-minute &amp;ldquo;med checks,&amp;rdquo; during which drug regimens are changed and adjusted.  The essence of my criticism is that this kind of approach&lt;strong&gt; inevitably oversimplifies human problems, and in practice does more harm than good&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My contentions in this regard have from time to time been challenged.  It has been said that my portrayal of psychiatry is a kind of misleading caricature, and that in reality, psychiatrists do, in fact, concern themselves with human issues over and above &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and drugs.  This debate will, of course, continue, but I recently read an article on Psychiatric Times that has some bearing on the matter.  [Thanks to Nick Stuart for the link.]  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/ptsd/conduct-disorder-adhd%E2%80%94or-something-else-altogether?GUID=4FCB4641-7FC8-4BA6-B25E-F52C8AD7E802&amp;amp;rememberme=1&amp;amp;ts=17102013&#34;&gt;Conduct Disorder, ADHD – or Something Else Altogether?&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;The author is Steven Dilsaver, MD, and the piece is dated October 11, 2013.  The article is a case study of the psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of an eight-year-old boy (John).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critique of Psychiatry&#39;s Medical Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 06:15:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read &lt;i&gt;De-Medicalizing Misery&lt;/i&gt; [palgrave macmillan, 2011].  It&amp;rsquo;s a comprehensive collection of articles, edited by Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon.  The table of contents provides a sense of the book&amp;rsquo;s scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Carving Nature at its Joints?  DSM and the Medicalization of Everyday Life&lt;/i&gt;, Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dualisms and the Myth of Mental Illness&lt;/i&gt;, Philip Thomas and Patrick Bracken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Making the World Go Away, and How Psychology and Psychiatry Benefit&lt;/i&gt;, Mary Boyle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cultural Diversity and Racism: An Historical Perspective&lt;/i&gt;, Suman Fernando&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Social Context of Paranoia&lt;/i&gt;, David J. Harper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;From Bad Character to BPD: The Medicalization of &#39;Personality Disorder&#39;&lt;/i&gt;, James Bourne&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Medicalizing Masculinity&lt;/i&gt;, Sami Timimi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Can Traumatic Events Traumatize People?  Trauma, Madness, and Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Lucy Johnstone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children Who Witness Violence at Home&lt;/i&gt;, Arlene Vetere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Discourses of Acceptance and Resistance:  Speaking Out about Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, Ewen Speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Personal &lt;/i&gt;is&lt;i&gt; The Political&lt;/i&gt;, Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&#39;I&#39;m Just, You Know, Joe Bloggs&#39;:  The Management of Parental Responsibility for First-episode Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Carlton Coulter and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Myth of the Antidepressant:  An Historical Analysis&lt;/i&gt;, Joanna Moncrieff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Antidepressants and the Placebo Response&lt;/i&gt;, Irving Kirsch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Why Were Doctors So Slow to Recognize Antidepressant Discontinuation Problems?&lt;/i&gt; Duncan Double&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Toxic Psychology&lt;/i&gt;, Craig Newnes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychotherapy:  Illusion with No Future?&lt;/i&gt; David Smail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Psychologization of Torture&lt;/i&gt;, Nimisha Patel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;What Is to Be Done? &lt;/i&gt;Joanna Moncrieff, Jacqui Dillon, and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Each author brings to the general topic his or her unique perspectives, and the result is persuasive and inspiring.
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from the final chapter:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Concept of Mental Illness:  Spurious or Valid?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 05:35:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 17, 2013, Peter Kinderman, PhD, Professor of Clinical Psychology at the University of Liverpool, wrote an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-20986796&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Grief and Anxiety are not mental illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 4, 2013, Steven Novella, MD, wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/dsm-v-mental-illness-vs-normal-behavior/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 20, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Novella&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, on September 17, Dr. Novella wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/more-on-mental-illness-denial-and-how-not-to-argue/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;More On Mental Illness Denial and How Not to Argue&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a critique of my critique.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Suicide Prevention:  A 30-year Failed Experiment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-suicide-prevention-a-30-year-failed-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2013 06:38:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-suicide-prevention-a-30-year-failed-experiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Mad in America dated September 17, 2013.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/09/nz-psychiatrist-psychiatrys-medical-model-suicide-prevention-30-year-failed-experiment/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry &amp;amp; Suicide Prevention: A 30-year Failed Experiment&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Maria Bradshaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria Bradshaw is the founder of CASPER, an organization that rejects the medical model of suicide prevention in favor of a sociological model.  Ms. Bradshaw founded CASPER after her son&amp;rsquo;s antidepressant-induced suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the gist of Ms. Bradshaw article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Mulder, MD, is head of psychiatry at Otago University in New Zealand.  For at least the last 15 years, he has supported the notion of psychiatric intervention as a suicide-prevention measure.  For instance, here&amp;rsquo;s something he wrote in 2008 in an article published in &lt;a href=&#34;http://lefnet.hu/resources/userfiles/file/Rihmer/Mulder%20APS%2008,%20suic%20during%20AD.pdf&#34;&gt;Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overall Efficacy of Mental Health Treatment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/overall-efficacy-of-mental-health-treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2013 08:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/overall-efficacy-of-mental-health-treatment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article by J. Sareen et al on Cambridge Journals Online, September 2013.  It&amp;rsquo;s call &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;amp;aid=8965169&amp;amp;fulltextType=RA&amp;amp;fileId=S003329171200284X&#34;&gt;Common mental disorder diagnosis and need for treatment are not the same: findings from a population-based survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  Five of the six authors are working at universities in Canada, the sixth at a university in California.  [Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/08/diagnosis-and-the-need-for-treatment-are-not-linked/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; for the link to the abstract.  The full article is, unfortunately, behind a paywall.]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Latest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 07:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 12, Jeffry Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, posted an article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1738168&#34;&gt;IPS to Feature Patrick Kennedy, Celebrate Community Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a preview of an APA conference scheduled for October 10-13 in Philadelphia: &amp;ldquo;Transforming Psychiatric Practice, Reforming Health Care Delivery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman tells us that he is very excited about the conference, and that the theme is particularly relevant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…given the changes we are experiencing in the profession and some of the exciting program events that I hope will support APA’s goal of being in the forefront of changes in the profession under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Burden of Mental &#39;Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 09:51:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GrahamCLDavey&#34;&gt;Graham Davey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/socratext&#34;&gt;Richard Pemberton&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link to an interesting article in the August 29, 2013 issue of the Lancet.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/GBD-Mental-2010-from-Lancet.pdf&#34;&gt;Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Harvey A. Whiteford, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Burden of Disease survey is a systematic, scientific attempt to quantify the comparative magnitude of disease, injuries, and risk factors by age, sex, and geography over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time for a Paradigm Change: Crucial Points</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-for-a-paradigm-change-crucial-points/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 08:23:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/time-for-a-paradigm-change-crucial-points/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new post on Peter Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s blog.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://peterkinderman.blogspot.com/2013/09/time-for-paradigm-change.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Time for a paradigm change&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s dated September 2.  The article is based on a speech that Dr. Kinderman gave to North Wales Clinical Psychology Programme, Annual Stakeholders&amp;rsquo; Meeting on the same date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;But mental well-being is fundamentally a psychological and social phenomenon, with medical aspects. It is not, fundamentally, a medical phenomenon with additional psychological and social elements.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Living-With-Parents Blues</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-living-with-parents-blues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 05:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-living-with-parents-blues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the general rise in economic indicators over the past year or two, there are still many young adults who, for economic reasons, have had to move back in with their parents.  A proportion of these people become depressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depression is the normal human reaction to loss, disappointment, or a general sense of unfulfillment.  Viewed in this light, it is not surprising that young people who have to move back in with their parents might be depressed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Madness Contested: An Outstanding Book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 06:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested &lt;/i&gt;has recently been published by PCCS Books.  It&amp;rsquo;s a collection of articles, edited by Steven Coles, Sarah Keenan, and Bob Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a remarkable piece of work.  It covers just about every contentious concept in the present &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; debate, and brings to bear an abundance of new insights and up-to-date research findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 21 articles plus an introduction by the editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the name of each article with a brief quotation from each:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Medical Model vs. Psychosocial/Behavioral Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/medical-model-vs-psychosocial-behavioral-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 05:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/medical-model-vs-psychosocial-behavioral-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously there are many points of contention between mainstream biological psychiatrists on the one hand, and those of us who condemn this system as spurious and destructive.  Much of what I&amp;rsquo;ve written on this website over the past four years has been an elucidation of these differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I would like to focus on just one of these differences:  &lt;i&gt;disempowerment&lt;/i&gt; of clients in the psychiatric system, and &lt;i&gt;empowerment&lt;/i&gt; within frameworks that are more psychosocial/behavioral in nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agitation and Neuroleptics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/agitation-and-neuroleptics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 06:12:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/agitation-and-neuroleptics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sandra Steingard, MD, is a practicing psychiatrist who from time to time posts articles on Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s Mad in America website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Steingard apparently prescribes psychotropic drugs in her practice, but she is by no means a pill-for-every-problem practitioner, and her articles are always interesting and thought-provoking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Steingard posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/07/a-paradox-revealed-again/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;A Paradox Revealed – Again&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Mad in America on July 7, 2013.  In this article she mentions the recent study by Lex Wunderink et al, which found that people being treated for first episode psychosis were doing a great deal better functionally after seven years if their neuroleptic drugs had been discontinued or reduced relatively early in the process, as compared to individuals who were retained on the drugs for two years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Intrinsically Flawed and Rotten</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter yesterday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobStamatakis&#34;&gt;Robert Stamatakis&lt;/a&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have to ask, I don&#39;t understand.  Do you work in the UK?  Your descriptions of psychiatry are nothing I recognize.  These descriptions of psychiatry are nothing like the practice I see on a daily basis.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
I am certainly a very outspoken critic of psychiatry, and in that regard Robert&#39;s question/challenge is a fair one, to which I will try to respond.
&lt;p&gt;My primary criticism of modern psychiatry – and indeed the criticism that underpins all the others – is that its fundamental concepts are spurious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personal Goals and Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/personal-goals-and-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2013 06:06:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/personal-goals-and-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read a noteworthy article on PLOS One.  It&amp;rsquo;s by Joanne M. Dickson and Nicholas J. Moberly, and it&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064512&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reduced Specificity of Personal Goals and Explanations for Goal Attainment in Major Depression&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s a very interesting and detailed paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors, who work at the University of Liverpool and the University of Exeter respectively, asked a group of depressed people and another group of people who were not depressed to list their goals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PTSD:  The Spurious Medicalization of Painful Memories</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 04:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read &lt;i&gt;Crazy Like Us: The Globalization of the American Psyche,&lt;/i&gt; by Ethan Watters (Free Press, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, the theme of which is that western countries, especially America, are &lt;strong&gt;exporting the medicalization of human problems to less developed regions of the world&lt;/strong&gt;.  The new &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; are being avidly promoted as if they had the same kind of reality as pneumonia or cancer, and are being foisted on vulnerable populations, with little regard for their impact on the cultures, ideas, sensitivities, and health of the recipients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative to DSM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 05:58:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month (May 31), National Public Radio (NPR) ran an interview on Science Friday with Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, and Gary Greenberg, PhD, practicing psychotherapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t hear the interview, but I have read the &lt;a href=&#34;http://m.npr.org/news/Health/187534467&#34;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt;.  Doctors Insel and Lieberman were spinning the barrage of criticism directed at psychiatry in recent months, while at the same time clinging desperately to the notion that the problems that psychiatrists &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; are real illnesses.  It&amp;rsquo;s become a familiar theme, and there was nothing new.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What &lt;em&gt;Is&lt;/em&gt; Mental Illness?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 08:50:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently received the following question from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ambtax1&#34;&gt;Disparity&lt;/a&gt;, on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I&#39;m interested in all your posts, but they&#39;re always telling us what mental illness &#39;isn&#39;t.&#39;  Do you have many on what it &#39;is&#39;?&lt;/p&gt;
I referred him/her to the post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2012/06/01/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;There are No Mental Illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and received the following reply:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have read it a few times.  I largely agree with it.  But &#39;something&#39; happens to people.  Whatever the label.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
Questions of this sort arise fairly frequently, and I thought it might be helpful to write a post.
&lt;p&gt;WHAT HAPPENS TO PEOPLE?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going Against the Stream</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/going-against-the-stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 09:11:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/going-against-the-stream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AN INTERESTING STORY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I came across the following on Twitter from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Sectioned_&#34;&gt;Mental Health @Sectioned_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I just met someone who told me their remarkable story about falling down the rabbit hole into psychiatric sectioning and forced medication.  I listened with fascination to their intricate story in all its twists and turns, looping backwards and forwards with incredible details.  The longer we spoke the more was revealed, the crazier and more believable it sounded.  I was listening, probing for clarification, trying to grasp what happened and why.  First the overview, then the highlights, then more details, expanding out, backing round, drawing me in.  There were many parallels in our stories, and many contrasts.  It reminded me why I don&#39;t really talk in detail about what happened to me: because, if you&#39;ve not experienced it, it sounds unbelievable.  Unless you&#39;ve experienced the scorching reality of forced drugging, seclusion, assault by nurses and patients, it sounds like a mad fantasy.  It&#39;s too far outside most people&#39;s realities for them to contemplate it being true, and so quietly assume you&#39;re deluded.  So it smooths life&#39;s path to make light, to skirt over the details, to change the topic.  And sometimes, sometimes, when I meet someone who&#39;s been through something similar, I listen to their story and realize I&#39;m not the only one.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kinderman-Pies Debate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 08:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 15, Peter Kinderman, PhD, of the University of Liverpool, posted an article on DxSummit.org.  It was called &lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/197&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;So…What Happens Next?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article was that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are conceptually spurious, unhelpful, and even hindersome in practice, and discourage practitioners from pursuing genuine explanations for the problems clients bring to their attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an excellent piece, and I did a short post in which I recommended it strongly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Abuse in Childhood Make You Crazy?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2013 09:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A NEW PARADIGM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an interesting article by Jacqui Dillon, Lucy Johnstone and Eleanor Longden.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp; Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&#34; href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Trauma-Dissociation-Attachment-and-Neuroscience-Dillo-Johnstone-Longden.pdf&#34;&gt;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp;Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article was published in the Journal of Critical Psychology, Counselling and Psychotherapy (Vol 12, No 3, September 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;A new and profoundly important paradigm for understanding overwhelming emotional pain has emerged over the last few years, with the potential to change the way we conceptualise human suffering across the whole spectrum of mental health difficulties. It is a strongly evidence-based synthesis of findings from trauma studies, attachment theory and neuroscience, which offers new hope for recovery. It also presents a powerful challenge to biomedical model psychiatry in that it is based on scientific evidence that substantiates and attests to what many individuals with first-hand experience of mental health problems have always known –– that the bad things that happen to you can drive you mad.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Wellbeing Foundation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-wellbeing-foundation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 05:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-wellbeing-foundation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tommymorrela&#34;&gt;Tommy Morrela&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, I&amp;rsquo;ve become aware of &lt;a href=&#34;http://wellbeingfoundation.com/&#34;&gt;The Wellbeing Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.  They are located in Ireland.  Here are some quotes from their &lt;a href=&#34;http://wellbeingfoundation.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;About Us&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;To call human suffering a disease, something pathological, is deluded. The biological model of psychological distress has no basis in science; it takes away from the equation between &#39;healer&#39;, sufferer and society the need for understanding, compassion, healing, prevention and social and political change. The medicalisation of problems of living has to stop. We have a collective duty of care to bring about the destruction of psychiatry in its present form.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Caretaker Personality Disorder: Another Fiction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-caretaker-personality-disorder-another-fiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 05:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-caretaker-personality-disorder-another-fiction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article in the current (May/June) issue of The National Psychologist called &lt;i&gt;Compulsive pleasing is deceptive and dangerous&lt;/i&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Les Barbanell, EdD.  (The National Psychologist is a newspaper-type publication for psychologists.  It&amp;rsquo;s published in Ohio, in the US.  Some of their material is posted online, but this article is not.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is about &amp;ldquo;the Caretaker Personality Disorder (CPD),&amp;rdquo; which apparently Dr. Barbanell invented in 2006 and has been promoting since.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Attempt to Defend DSM-5</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 06:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 April, The Conversation ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/mental-disorders-debunking-some-myths-of-the-dsm-5-12047&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental disorders: debunking some myths of the DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Perminder Sachdev, MD.  Dr. Sachdev is a psychiatrist, and was a member of the DSM-5&amp;rsquo;s Neurocognitive Disorders Work Group.  He works at the School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Australia.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davetraxson&#34;&gt;Dave Traxson&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANALYSIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the title.  &amp;ldquo;…debunking some myths of the DSM-5.&amp;rdquo;  This sounds good.  You might get the impression that he&amp;rsquo;s going to address the myth of mental illness – the myth that all human problems are illnesses and are best treated by drugs.  But – alas – you would be mistaken.  Dr. Sachdev lists four myths that he plans to debunk.  He refers to these as the &amp;ldquo;…four key criticisms about DSM-5…&amp;rdquo;  Let&amp;rsquo;s examine what he says about these one by one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood &#39;Mental Disorders&#39; According to the CDC</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 05:23:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 17, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a report titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/pdf/other/su6202.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental Health Surveillance Among Children – United States, 2005-2011&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The CDC is based in Atlanta, Georgia and is a part of the US Department of Health and Human Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CDC&amp;rsquo;s report runs to 40 pages, including tables and references.  It received a fair amount of media coverage, and will likely inform legislation and other government action for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM: The Big Lie</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-the-big-lie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2013 12:14:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-the-big-lie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very interesting article by Kyle Arnold on DxSummit.org.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/456&#34;&gt;DSM: Letting Go of the Big Lie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The lie is that we have succeeded in domesticating emotional suffering, that we have placed it in a grid with clear and familiar boundaries. The lie is that we know the line between mad and normal, and can tell you on which side of the fence you belong. The lie is that it is science, rather than ethics or social norms, that can tell us what kind of behavior is acceptable and what is not. The lie is that psychiatric treatment is objective medical treatment, as clear and direct as your medical doctor treating a broken wrist.  The lie is that by accepting a psychiatric label, you embark on the road to being cured. The lie is the provision of false hope at the price of a stigmatized identity.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talk Therapy for Schizophrenia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 21:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Vermont&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Seven Days&lt;/i&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Burlington&amp;rsquo;s HowardCenter Tries a New Approach to Treating Mental Illness: More Talk, Fewer Meds.&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.7dvt.com/2013burlingtons-howardcenter-tries-new-approach-treating-mental-illness-more-talking-fewer-meds&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Steven_Coles_&#34;&gt;Steven Coles&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently Vermont&amp;rsquo;s Department of Mental Health is promoting a &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; kind of treatment for psychosis:  talk therapy.  The project leader is Dr. Sandra Steingard, who for most of her career accepted the orthodox view of schizophrenia and the need for neuroleptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s a Great Day for Humanity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/it-s-a-great-day-for-humanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 22:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/it-s-a-great-day-for-humanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, after two years of deliberation, the Division of Clinical Psychology (which is part of the British Psychological Society)  issued a &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;Position Statement on the Classification of Behavior and Experience in Relation to Functional Psychiatric Diagnosis.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt; It is subtitled &amp;ldquo;Time for a Paradigm Shift.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DCP summarizes its paper as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The DCP is of the view that it is timely and appropriate to affirm publicly that the current classification system as outlined in DSM and ICD, in respect of the functional psychiatric diagnoses, has significant conceptual and empirical limitations. Consequently, there is a need for a paradigm shift in relation to the experiences that these diagnoses refer to, towards a conceptual system not based on a ‘disease’ model.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Article by Brett Jason Deacon</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-article-by-brett-jason-deacon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2013 08:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-article-by-brett-jason-deacon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the current issue of Clinical Psychology Review (April 8, 2013), you will find a very interesting article by Brett Jason Deacon, PhD, who is an Associate Professor of Psychology at the University of Wyoming.  The article is called &lt;i&gt;The Biomedical Model of Mental Disorder: A Critical Analysis of its Tenets, Consequences, and Effects on Psychotherapy Research&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/Deacon-biomedical-model-and-stigma-2013.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a critique of the biomedical model from a theoretical and a practical perspective.  The author has managed to elucidate a comprehensive range of criticisms of the biomedical model, and has blended them together into a coherent and compelling account.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – Embracing a Social Paradigm?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 07:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the May 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;The future of academic psychiatry may be social&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt;by Stefan Priebe, Tom Burns, and Tom K. J. Craig.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NSVo2eU9meHQtOUU/edit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The past 30 years have produced no discoveries leading to major changes in psychiatric practice. The rules regulating research and a dominant neurobiological paradigm may both have stifled creativity. Embracing a social paradigm could generate real progress and, simultaneously, make the profession more attractive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Distress Is Not An Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 06:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uilleannair&#34;&gt;Sam Thompson&lt;/a&gt; (University of Liverpool) posted the following tweet on April 27:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Can anyone point me to a good, succinct summary of the case for equating mental distress with illness?  (serious, non-sarcastic question)&lt;/p&gt;
On the face of it, this looks like a straightforward question, and one might think that a straightforward answer could be found.  But this is not the case, because ultimately it boils down to a matter of definition.  And psychiatry is a field where &lt;strong&gt;definitions are notoriously fuzzy&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;MENTAL DISORDER&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Mental Illness&#34; Under Fire</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-under-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-under-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very interesting article by Paris Williams on Mad in America, &lt;i&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Mental Illness&amp;rdquo; Paradigm: An &amp;ldquo;Illness&amp;rdquo; That is out of Control.&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/05/the-mental-illness-paradigm-itself-an-illness-that-is-out-of-control/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author gives us a compelling critique of the &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; model, and also presents us with an &lt;strong&gt;alternative paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;… to see those conditions we generally refer to as &#39;mental illnesses&#39; as instead the natural manifestations of an individual’s struggles with the fundamental dilemmas inherent in simply being alive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Need More Mental Health Services?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-need-more-mental-health-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 12:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-need-more-mental-health-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Sandy Hook massacre, there were a great many calls for &amp;ldquo;more mental health services&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;better access to mental health services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us on this side of the fence groaned, because we knew that any official or private response to this call would be on the lines of more of the same.  The same &lt;strong&gt;spurious concepts&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;pseudo-illnesses&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;destructive drugging&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;destructive electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;involuntary confinement&lt;/strong&gt;; and the same &lt;strong&gt;stigmatization and loss of empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Antidepressant Risks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-antidepressant-risks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 15:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-antidepressant-risks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article in Science Daily (April 29, 2013) titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;i&gt;Antidepressants Linked with Increased Risks After Surgery&lt;/i&gt;,&amp;rdquo; which I found courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/04/130429164638.htm#.UX-m2v4zuaI.twitter&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  The article is a report of a study published in JAMA Internal Medicine.  You can see an abstract of the study &lt;a href=&#34;http://archinte.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1682366&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted by Andrew Auerbach MD et al, and involved examining the records of 530,416 patients who had undergone major surgery between January 2006 and December 2008 at 375 US hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and the Other Professions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 09:33:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t have precise figures, but I would guess that psychiatrists constitute less than 5% of the professional staff in the mental health system  The other 95% are psychologists, counselors, social workers, case managers, behavior analysts, case aides, art therapists, occupational therapists, job coaches, etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these other professions have specialized training, both theoretical and practical, and it is reasonable to suppose that they bring to their jobs a &lt;strong&gt;wide range of conceptual orientations&lt;/strong&gt;, and an equally &lt;strong&gt;wide range of practical skills.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Website:  by Mick Bramham</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 09:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across &lt;i&gt;Thinking About Mental Health: Myths, treatment risks &amp;amp; alternatives.&lt;/i&gt;  You can find it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s written by Mick Bramham, from Dorset, England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/chemical-imbalances.html&#34;&gt;Depression: Serotonin Imbalance?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The whole idea of antidepressants supposedly correcting chemical imbalances has more to do with drug company marketing than evidence-based science.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Unfortunately, drug companies are known to exaggerate the benefits of their products and to play down the risks;&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Postpartum Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-postpartum-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 09:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-postpartum-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/04/24/postpartum-depression/&#34;&gt;post on postpartum depression&lt;/a&gt; which has generated a certain amount of negative comment.  For this reason, I thought it might be helpful to clarify some points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEFINITION AND EXPLANATIONS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DSM makes no mention of postpartum depression as such.  The closest it comes is major depressive disorder with postpartum onset.  In other words, the APA conceptualizes postpartum depression as ordinary major depression (which can incidentally range in severity from mild to severe) which happens to occur in the postpartum period.  This is in marked contrast to the popular notion that postpartum depression is somehow a function of the postpartum woman&amp;rsquo;s hormones, and is fundamentally different from other forms of depression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internet Addiction: A Bad Habit, Not An Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 17:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSM-5 drafting committee considered including Internet addiction in the upcoming revision, but eventually backed off, at least for now.  Apparently they decided to put it in the category &amp;ldquo;requiring further study.&amp;rdquo;  So it&amp;rsquo;ll be in DSM-6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, people are being given the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; anyway – and of course, the &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AN ILLUSTRATIVE CASE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt; for sending me a link to a recent article in the UK&amp;rsquo;s MailOnline.  It was written by Rebecca Seales and Eleanor Harding.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2312429/Four-year-old-girl-Britains-youngest-iPad-ADDICT-Shocking-rise-children-hooked-using-smartphones-tablets.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Anxiety Disorder: Now Also for Adults</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of separation anxiety disorder has been around since DSM-III.  In DSM-IV it is defined as &amp;ldquo;…excessive anxiety concerning separation from the home or from those to whom the person is attached.&amp;rdquo;  (DSM-IV-TR p 121).  The APA&amp;rsquo;s prevalence estimate is 4%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is listed under the heading: &amp;ldquo;Other Disorders of Infancy, Childhood, or Adolescence.&amp;rdquo;  One of the criteria is that the problem must begin before age 18, and in practice the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; was generally confined to children under the age of 10 or so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Blood Test for Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 07:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of Talla Trialogue on Twitter, I have read an article by Shari Roan called &lt;i&gt;Blood Test for Depression Proves It&amp;rsquo;s Not All In Your Head&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.takepart.com/article/2013/01/25/major-depression-can-be-diagnosed-blood-test&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article appears to be an interview with Lonna Williams, the CEO of Ridge Diagnostics.  This company is reportedly introducing a blood test for depression.  The test is called MDDScore and is expected to cost $745.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article tells us that:  &amp;ldquo;You get a numerical score that suggests how likely it is that you have depression. Studies show that MDD Score is about as accurate at making a diagnosis as the most rigorous evaluations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative to the Medical Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-the-medical-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 13:41:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-the-medical-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Lucy Johnstone on twitter, I came across a chapter from Steven Coles&amp;rsquo; book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested&lt;/i&gt;.  The book was published in the UK in February 2013, but won&amp;rsquo;t be available in the US until September of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapter is called&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychminded.co.uk/news/news2013/april2013/proven-alternative-to-the-medical-model-in-mental-health-care.htm&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;A proven alternative to the medical model in mental health care?&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  and describes the Leeds Survivor Led Crisis Service, which for twelve years has provided a &lt;strong&gt;genuine alternative to mainstream mental health services. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People Helping People</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/people-helping-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 21:51:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/people-helping-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things are changing in the mental health business.  People of various persuasions are attacking the medicalization of human problems on the grounds of spuriousness and destructiveness.  Others are drawing attention to the ineffectiveness of the drugs, the dangerous side-effects, and the corrupting links between psychiatrists and big pharma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the change that ultimately is going to have the greatest effect is the fact that more and more service users are shucking off the archaic legacy of silence and shame, and are telling their stories.  They are telling us that the &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; in many cases hurt them rather than helped, but more importantly, that they are now finding their way not through psychiatry, but through something much more powerful and effective:  &lt;i&gt;people &lt;/i&gt;helping &lt;i&gt;people!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Psychotropic Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 10:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytransformation.blogspot.com/2011/04/fishing-lessons-from-my-son.html#.UWBNjZOG0eU&#34;&gt;nice article at Involuntary Transformation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Nathan, poses a very interesting question:  since drugs cause damage to children and there are many better alternatives, &lt;strong&gt;why do so many parents choose the drug option&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan goes on to suggest that the reason lies in the effort that the pharmaceutical industry invests in marketing, and he calls for &amp;ldquo;…complete and total transparency in all Mental Health Services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Children Gives Them the Wrong Message</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 10:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The routine drugging of children for the ordinary problems of childhood is destructive for two reasons:  firstly because of the toxic effects of the pharmaceutical products, and secondly because it &lt;strong&gt;conveys to the child the message that drugs are an acceptable way to deal with life&amp;rsquo;s problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This latter kind of damage is graphically illustrated in a tragic NY Times article by Ted Gup.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/03/opinion/diagnosis-human.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Ted is a fellow of the Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freudian Psychoanalysis is Better than Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 10:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I received a short comment from Ruth Elliot on my post&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/26/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/#.UVt4fZOG0eU&#34;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psychiatric &amp;ldquo;Diagnoses&amp;rdquo; for Children&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Ruth linked to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://claudiamgoldmd.blogspot.com/2013/01/towards-new-or-return-to-old-paradigm.html#comment-form&#34;&gt;article by Claudia Gold, MD&lt;/a&gt;.  Claudia is a Freudian psychoanalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ideological orientation is behavioral, and if you were to ask people in this business:  what is the opposite of a behaviorist? you would probably get the answer:  a Freudian psychoanalyst.  And vice versa.  They are two very different ways of conceptualizing human activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petition on Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting new article by Paula Caplan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/comedy-history-and-the-future-mental-disorder-labels&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It discusses the harmful effects of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the fact that because of these labels, people have lost their &amp;ldquo;… jobs, custody of children, health insurance, and the right to make decisions about their medical and legal affairs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paula also mentions a petition she created in December 2011 calling for &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Congressional Hearings about Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  The petition is still up. You can find it&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.change.org/petitions/everyone-who-cares-about-the-harm-done-by-psychiatric-diagnosis-endorse-the-call-for-congressional-hearings-about-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal from Benzodiazepines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Important updates on this subject can be found at the posts listed at the bottom of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I&#39;ve recently come across an article by Matt Samet called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/social-vacuum/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Social Vacuum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&#39;s dated March 2013, and was published on Robert Whitaker&#39;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Matt had been taking a benzodiazepine for some time, and while on a tapering withdrawal, he experienced some distressing symptoms, including some acute social discomfort.  (For a full account of benzo withdrawal –&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benzodiazepine_withdrawal_syndrome&#34;&gt; click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and the Law</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 14:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this website is that there are no mental illnesses, and that the widespread medicalization of ordinary human problems is spurious and destructive.  These concepts have been around for decades, but in the last four or five years have &amp;ldquo;taken off,&amp;rdquo; and are finding a good deal of acceptance among practitioners, academics, clients, and the general public.  Change is in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A matter that is sometimes overlooked, however, is that the &lt;strong&gt;concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and its &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; by psychiatrists and other professionals is deeply embedded in the legal system of most states and countries&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Involuntary Commitment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 11:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent times a good deal of criticism has been directed towards the practice of involuntarily committing individuals to state and private mental hospitals.  Most of this criticism focuses on the lack of effective due process; conflicts of interest in the case of private facilities; and failure to adequately explore alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my view, all of these criticisms are valid, and warrant attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is another side to the story that is seldom aired outside the mental health centers.  A great many clients &lt;i&gt;like&lt;/i&gt; going to the mental hospital; they plan their trips in advance and &amp;ldquo;freak out&amp;rdquo; at the appointed time, knowing that the knee-jerk response of the mental health center will be a court-ordered admission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Call Yourself That:  The Harmful Effects of Negative Self-labeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/don-t-call-yourself-that-the-harmful-effects-of-negative-self-labeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 11:25:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/don-t-call-yourself-that-the-harmful-effects-of-negative-self-labeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we were young, most of us devoted a good deal of time and energy to squabbling with other children.  To the dismay of our parents, we because adept in the use of impolite language, and kept our stock of insulting words and phrases up-to-date.  As adults we are more socially sophisticated.  We no longer call one another rude names – at least not openly.  Tragically, however, many people go through their entire adult lives calling &lt;i&gt;themselves&lt;/i&gt; names, which although not as vulgar as the insults of childhood, are considerably more destructive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
