<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>DSM on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/dsm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DSM on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 14:09:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/dsm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Bereavement Exclusion and DSM-5</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 14:09:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of major depressive &lt;i&gt;disorder&lt;/i&gt; is based on the presence of a major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;, in turn, is defined by the presence of five or more items from the following list during a two-week period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) depressed mood most of the day, nearly every day, as indicated by either subjective report (e.g., feels sad or empty) or observation made by others (e.g., appears tearful). Note&lt;b&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; In children and adolescents, can be irritable mood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining Mental Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/defining-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 12:54:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/defining-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a take-no-prisoners article by Paula Caplan on Psychology Today.  You can see Paula&amp;rsquo;s article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/how-the-ny-times-portrays-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks to @yobluemama2 on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…the now well-established facts that psychiatric diagnosis is unscientific, does not reduce human suffering, and causes many kinds of serious harm.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…the chances even that two therapists simultaneously meeting with the same person will assign that person the same label are poor, which of course means that diagnosis is not helpful in choosing treatment or improving outcome.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freudian Psychoanalysis is Better than Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 10:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I received a short comment from Ruth Elliot on my post&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/26/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/#.UVt4fZOG0eU&#34;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psychiatric &amp;ldquo;Diagnoses&amp;rdquo; for Children&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Ruth linked to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://claudiamgoldmd.blogspot.com/2013/01/towards-new-or-return-to-old-paradigm.html#comment-form&#34;&gt;article by Claudia Gold, MD&lt;/a&gt;.  Claudia is a Freudian psychoanalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ideological orientation is behavioral, and if you were to ask people in this business:  what is the opposite of a behaviorist? you would probably get the answer:  a Freudian psychoanalyst.  And vice versa.  They are two very different ways of conceptualizing human activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Inter-Rater Reliability is Low</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/the-dsm-5-field-trials-inter-rater-reliability-ratings-take-a-nose-dive/&#34;&gt;article by Jack Carney&lt;/a&gt;, DSW, on this topic on Mad in America.  Jack refers to the DSM-5 field trials published earlier this year in the American Journal of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inter-rater reliability is measured by a statistic called a kappa score.  A score of 1 means perfect inter-rater agreement; a score of 0 indicates zero agreement.  In psychosocial research a kappa score of 0.7 or above is generally considered good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petition on Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting new article by Paula Caplan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/comedy-history-and-the-future-mental-disorder-labels&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It discusses the harmful effects of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the fact that because of these labels, people have lost their &amp;ldquo;… jobs, custody of children, health insurance, and the right to make decisions about their medical and legal affairs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paula also mentions a petition she created in December 2011 calling for &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Congressional Hearings about Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  The petition is still up. You can find it&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.change.org/petitions/everyone-who-cares-about-the-harm-done-by-psychiatric-diagnosis-endorse-the-call-for-congressional-hearings-about-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muddled Thinking and Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until just a few years ago, the spurious nature of mental illness received little or no attention either in professional circles or in the general media. There were a few of us &amp;ldquo;cranks&amp;rdquo; who poked away at the issue, but peer condemnation was usually swift and outspoken.  On one occasion I was called an &amp;ldquo;anti-science Nazi&amp;rdquo; for daring to suggest that the condition known as ADHD might have more to do with ineffective parental discipline than with brain chemistry.  We were voices in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Thoughts on Dr. Novella&#39;s Articles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 09:55:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/#.USd7W6WG0eU&#34;&gt;Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;Mental Illness Denial Part I&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Novella makes the point that various parts of the brain enable us to do certain things, and that if we are doing these things dysfunctionally, or not well, or perhaps not at all, then clearly there is something wrong with that part of the brain.  The example he gives is the activity of paying attention – but I think this is provided as an example, and that Dr. Novella intended his comments to apply to the full range of problems embraced by the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric “Diagnoses” vs Real Diagnoses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-vs-real-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2012 16:25:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-vs-real-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robert Whitaker’s website, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;, is abuzz lately with articles challenging the medical model that underlies DSM and psychiatric “treatment” in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently there was an article by Alice Keys, MD, called “&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/12/do-diagnoses-injure-people/&#34;&gt;Do Diagnoses Injure People&lt;/a&gt;?”&lt;/em&gt;  Of course I believe emphatically that they do, and I read the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the content is valuable, and I encourage readers to take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one aspect of the piece, however, that I found troubling.  Dr. Keys made the point that psychiatric diagnoses can be dangerous, but then mitigated this considerably by making the same assertion about medical diagnoses in general. Whilst there may be a measure of truth to this assertion, it is misleading, in that it creates the impression that psychiatric “diagnoses” are just as valid as real medical diagnoses, which is simply not the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Cracks in the Sandcastle: Anti-DSM Sentiment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle-anti-dsm-sentiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 14:29:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle-anti-dsm-sentiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane recently wrote an article called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201209/anti-dsm-sentiment-rises-in-france&#34;&gt;Anti-DSM Sentiment Rises in France&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; “Anger and concern about the growing influence of the &lt;em&gt;DSM&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in France, as well as over a number of related, prominent pharmaceutical scandals here, has culminated in the creation of &lt;em&gt;Stop&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;DSM,&lt;/em&gt; a professional and political group that is strongly opposed to the manual’s diagnostic power and what it sees as its negative social consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Article by Bruce Thyer PhD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/article-by-bruce-thyer-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 08:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/article-by-bruce-thyer-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article the other day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It Is Time to Rename the DSM, &lt;/em&gt;by Bruce A. Thyer, PhD, Florida State University, Ethical Human Psychology and Psychiatry, Vol 8, No. 1, Spring 2006&lt;/p&gt;
Dr. Thyer points out that although the DSM claims to be atheoretical, its contention that the various “mental illnesses” reside &lt;em&gt;within the individual&lt;/em&gt;, as opposed, for instance, to being understandable reactions to adverse life events, is in itself a theoretical stance.
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Thyer also points out that in the manual’s description of conduct disorder there is a little known (and in my experience even less used) caveat to the effect that this so-called diagnosis should not be assigned if the misbehavior is “…simply a reaction to the immediate social context.”  This is laudable, of course, on the part of the APA, but Dr. Thyer goes on to pose the obvious question:  Why is this exclusion not applied to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the conditions listed? He then answers his own question:  Because “…if this practice was followed, the very concept of &lt;em&gt;mental disorders&lt;/em&gt; threatens to evaporate, in favor of viewing these as environmentally driven phenomena.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s New?  APA Threats, Xanax, Etc.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/what-s-new-apa-threats-xanax-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 11:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/what-s-new-apa-threats-xanax-etc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Daniel Carlat’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://carlatpsychiatry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; carries an &lt;a href=&#34;http://carlatpsychiatry.blogspot.com/2012/01/apa-threatens-to-sue-dsm5watch-website.html&#34;&gt;interesting item&lt;/a&gt;.  It seems that a lady named Suzy Chapman started a site called dsm5watch, in which she expressed criticism of the DSM.  Well, the APA didn’t like this and sent her a cease and desist letter, claiming that the string “DSM-5” is trademarked, and that she was infringing their rights.  She complied, changing the name of her site to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dxrevisionwatch.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;dxrevisionwatch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find interesting here is that the APA claim to be interested in public comment.  I guess as long as it doesn’t get too critical.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sexual Disorders Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sexual-disorders-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2010 12:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sexual-disorders-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that almost all the so-called mental illnesses listed in the APA’s Diagnostic and Statistical Manual are nothing more than the ordinary everyday challenges of human existence.  The psychiatric profession has “elevated” these problems to the status of disorders and illnesses to justify and legitimize their involvement in these areas, and in particular to justify the use of drugs to alter people’s moods and actions.  Psychiatry – once a respectable helping profession – has degenerated into something little better than drug pushing.  The real winners, of course, are the pharmaceutical companies, who use the psychiatrists and other mental health professionals to promote the widespread drugging of the population.  The DSM’s so-called sexual disorders represent a particularly blatant example of psychiatric invention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personality Disorders Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/personality-disorders-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 15:42:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/personality-disorders-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that there are no mental illnesses.  The concept of mental illness is a spurious invention of psychiatrists and other mental health professionals for the purpose of medicalizing normal human problems and selling drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central tenet of the mental health system is that unusual, bizarre, and disturbing behaviors are caused by mental disorders (or illnesses).  But their definition of a mental disorder is: a serious behavioral problem.  So problem behavior is caused by problem behavior.  This is the facile logic behind the widespread peddling of drugs in which psychiatry and the mental health system engage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The So-Called Mental Illnesses Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 19:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that mental illness is a spurious and invalid concept, which is promoted and developed by the American Psychiatric Association to legitimize the use of mood-altering drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that people display various problems in their daily lives and particularly in their interpersonal relationships.  The American Psychiatric Association claims that all such problems are caused by mental illness and their list of these so-called illnesses is so long that virtually anybody can be embraced within their coils.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conduct Disorder and Oppositional Defiant Disorder</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/conduct-disorder-and-oppositional-defiant-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2009 14:12:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/conduct-disorder-and-oppositional-defiant-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONDUCT DISORDER
&lt;/strong&gt;
The essential feature of Conduct Disorder, according to the APA, is a “repetitive and persistent pattern” of rule breaking or activity which violates other people’s basic rights.  The manual identifies four broad categories of behavior under this heading:  aggression; destruction of property; theft or deceitfulness; and serious violation of rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSM goes on to state that individuals with this disorder display little concern for the feelings or welfare of others, are frequently callous and indifferent to other people’s pain and loss, and show little in the way of feelings of guilt or remorse.  Poor frustration tolerance, irritability, temper tantrums, and recklessness are cited as frequently associated features.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can They Just Invent Illnesses?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-they-just-invent-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2009 12:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-they-just-invent-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The notion of a professional group such as the APA sitting in their councils and committees inventing illnesses for themselves to treat seems so preposterous that a measure of disbelief on the part of the reader is understandable.  In its historical context, however, the development is not so surprising.  The original 1952 DSM was very simple and unpretentious, and whilst part of the APA’s motivation in drafting the document was undoubtedly to draw some credibility and respectability to their profession, there is at the same time nothing to suggest any great drive at that time towards aggrandizement or service expansion.  However, having agreed in 1952 that neurosis was a form of mental disorder, it was inevitable that subsequent revisions of the manual would attempt to define this feature further and look for subdivisions of the general category.  This, of course, is exactly what has happened, and the current version of DSM lists literally dozens of disorders of this sort, although the general term neurosis is no longer used.  (For an interesting discussion of this matter, see Karen Franklin’s post at &lt;a href=&#34;http://forensicpsychologist.blogspot.com/2008/10/dsm-makeover-what-will-they-come-up.html&#34;&gt;In The News&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
