<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Disability on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/disability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Disability on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 11:15:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/disability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>More On Disability</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 11:15:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In his book &lt;em&gt;Anatomy of an Epidemic&lt;/em&gt;, Robert Whitaker drew attention to the increasing numbers on the Social Security disability rolls due to so-called mental illness.  Robert raises the possibility that the drugs routinely used to “treat” depression may be contributing to the problem.  In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/mad-in-america/201102/disability-in-the-age-prozac&#34;&gt;recent post&lt;/a&gt;, he discusses this matter further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the reasons for the increase in the disability rolls are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who seek psychiatric help are being told routinely that they have brain abnormalities and that they need to take drugs for the rest of their lives –“just like diabetics.”  This promotes a disability mindset which often translates into a disability application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.  Applicants for disability based on the so-called mental illnesses are screened by either a psychiatrist or a psychologist.  Both of these professional groups are immersed and heavily invested in the conceptualization of ordinary living problems as illnesses, and tend to accept uncritically the applicants’ claims that they “just can’t do anything.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
