<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Bipolar on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/bipolar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bipolar on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 05:30:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/bipolar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>More on the Biological Evidence for &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 10, 2017, I put up a post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/http:/behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;The Biological Evidence for &amp;ldquo;Mental Illness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  It was published simultaneously on Mad in America.  The post was a response to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.madinamerica.com/comment-history/?user_id=11436&#34;&gt;earlier comment&lt;/a&gt; from Carolina Partners in Mental Healthcare PLLC, which included the assertion &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses have a long history of biological evidence.&amp;rdquo;  In my January 10 article, I challenged this assertion and pointed out that no such evidence existed.  The article generated some comments, most of which were favorable.  There was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/#comment-3097355796&#34;&gt;one comment&lt;/a&gt;, however, from Michael, who asserted:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Response To Dr. Pies</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-response-to-dr-pies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 05:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-response-to-dr-pies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Behavioar-Therapist-Oct-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;October 2015 issue of the Behavior Therapist&lt;/a&gt; (pages 206-213), Jeffrey Lacasse, PhD, and Jonathan Leo, PhD, published an article titled &lt;em&gt;Antidepressants and the Chemical Imbalance Theory of Depression: A Reflection and Update on the Discourse&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the article had particular merit, and I drew attention to it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/11/02/more-on-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;a post dated November 2&lt;/a&gt;.  The post, &lt;em&gt;More on the Chemical Imbalance Theory, &lt;/em&gt;was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/11/more-on-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;published on Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that post, I quoted a number of passages from the Behavior Therapist article, including:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressant-induced Mania</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressant-induced-mania/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressant-induced-mania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is generally recognized in antipsychiatry circles that antidepressant drugs induce manic or hypomanic episodes in some of the individuals who take them.  Psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s usual response to this is to assert that the individual must have had an underlying latent bipolar disorder that has &amp;ldquo;emerged&amp;rdquo; in response to the improvement in mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with such a notion is that it is fundamentally unverifiable.  Psychiatry defines &amp;ldquo;bipolar disorder&amp;rdquo; by the presence of certain behaviors and feelings.  If a person meets these criteria, he/she is said to &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; bipolar disorder.  What immediately needs to be noted is that bipolar disorder, in common with psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s other &amp;ldquo;disorders&amp;rdquo; has no explanatory value.  To illustrate this, consider the following hypothetical conversation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Is Bipolar</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-is-bipolar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 06:01:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/life-is-bipolar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I am a 30 year man who finally realized a few months ago (after finding this website) that he is not mentally ill but just an adult who often acts like a child. I dabbled with some &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; drugs (meaning prescribed) in the last few years when I was first diagnosed  with depression (was put on anti deps + anti anxiety pills) and then bipolar a year later (this time it was mood stabilizers and sleeping pills).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 00:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing this post as a response to a comment posted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://drpullen.com/&#34;&gt;medical blog&lt;/a&gt; in my previous post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2011/02/24/more-on-so-called-bipolar-disorder/#comments&#34;&gt;More on So-called Bipolar Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2001 I became very ill.  The symptoms were exhaustion and mild nosebleeds. I went to three different practitioners, but they all were dismissive of my concerns, assured me that I was in good health, and sent me on my way.   On August 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of that year I was admitted to the hospital in Greeley, Colorado with complete kidney failure.  The nephrologist at the hospital gave me the &lt;em&gt;diagnosis&lt;/em&gt; that had eluded the earlier doctors:  Wegener’s Granulomatosis - a rare autoimmune disease that attacks lungs, kidneys, and airways. I have been on dialysis every since.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on So-called Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-so-called-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2011 14:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-so-called-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I received the following email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Hi Phil,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;I would like to hear from you how we can survive the bipolar disorder, as I understand bipolar is a very serious disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;[Name]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The question seems important enough to warrant a more public response, though I have omitted the writer’s name to safeguard confidentiality.
&lt;p&gt;So here’s my reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the condition known as “bipolar disorder” is emphatically NOT a disease.  Rather, it is a loose cluster of behaviors which psychiatrists – in concert with the pharmaceutical companies – have &lt;em&gt;called&lt;/em&gt; an illness with the purpose of selling drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipolar Disorder Is Not An Illness</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-disorder-is-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2009 11:42:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bipolar-disorder-is-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post was edited and updated on June 24, 2013,  to address comments received from readers.  I thank them for their input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSM-IV’s criteria for a manic episode are given below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. A distinct period of abnormally and persistently elevated, expansive, or irritable mood, lasting at least 1 week (or any duration if hospitalization is necessary).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2009 17:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/posttraumatic-stress-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post was edited and updated on July 7, 2013 in the light of comments from readers.  I am grateful for their input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anxiety disorders listed in DSM-IV is posttraumatic stress disorder. The criteria for this condition are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. The person has been exposed to a traumatic event in which both of the following were present:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) the person experienced, witnessed, or was confronted with an event or events that involved actual or threatened death or serious injury, or a threat to the physical integrity of self or others
(2) the person&#39;s response involved intense fear, helplessness, or horror. Note: in children, this may be expressed instead by disorganized or agitated behavior&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
