<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Survivors of Psychiatry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/survivors-of-psychiatry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Survivors of Psychiatry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 09:30:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/survivors-of-psychiatry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Another Survivor&#39;s Tale</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-survivor-s-tale/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 09:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-survivor-s-tale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;My Story&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I tried to commit suicide for the first time when I was 15. I spent my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;16th birthday locked up in Dammasch State Mental Hospital, I freaked &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;out when I was told I was going to have to stay so my clothes were &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;ripped off me, by male aids and I was thrown naked in a real padded &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;room&amp;hellip; hint they are NOT padded. The light was on all the time and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;nothing was provided for cover to keep warm. I remember seeing men &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;looking at me and I remember pictures being taken thru the peek hole &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;window. I was in that room, with meals shoved thru a slit in the door &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;for 3 days. The toilet was a hole in the floor and no, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;any toilet paper. . While at the &amp;ldquo;hospital&amp;rdquo;, I remember being put in a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;strait jacket and tied into a chair and my &amp;ldquo;meds&amp;rdquo; forced down my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;throat. When I realized I could vomit them back up I was sedated and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;given drugs via an IV. I woke up to being raped. I made friends with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;one gal, she was 14. She had ( I know know as ) anorexia. I watched &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;her try and try and try to eat. She died. Another person I made &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;friends with hung himself and died. The psy dr said I was on the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;schedule for shock treatments since I refused to co-operate with the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;rules and the staff. That scared the shit outta me. I started doing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;all the things I was supposed to do and 3 months later I was &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;released.. cured. Nothing was different for me, except I learned how &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to manipulate people to get what I wanted. I HATED that feeling so I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;never took &amp;ldquo;advantage&amp;rdquo; of that &amp;ldquo;skill&amp;rdquo;.. Remember I had just turned &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;16.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;In my early 20&amp;rsquo;s I tried to commit suicide again and committed to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;another hosp in Vancouver WA with a DX of Manic Depression. I was on a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;cocktail of lithium, stelazine, tofranil chloral hydrate and a few &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;others I can&amp;rsquo;t remember the names of .. for more than 7 years I saw a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;psychiatrist until my divorce and my insurance ran out. Dumped to fare &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the best I could into the mental health system for the poor I quit all &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;my drugs cold turkey.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;It was while under the Dr&amp;rsquo;s care I read a book he recommended called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Self-Talk. I believed I was sick with metal illness(es?) until I read &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that book. For the first time I heard no one can make me feel anyway &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;at all unless I choose to let them. That my responses to life were &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;totally under my control and direction ALL of them. I was 32. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve attempted suicide or came very very close to it 6 times in my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;life. Finally I asked myself, self, I&amp;rsquo;m smart enough to have gotten &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;the job done so whats REALLY going on? I figured out WHY I kept diving &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;into the back hole. I really do walk a different, road now thanks to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;getting the message my subconscious kept sending me. Thats been my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experience with the Mental Health system. I am continually agast and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;appalled at the amount of drugs being forced onto people, particularly &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;children, We adults have been fed a line of BS for so long about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;depression that it&amp;rsquo;s destroying us as a nation and no one can see it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Involuntary Mental Health Commitments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-mental-health-commitments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 05:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-mental-health-commitments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The recent publicity surrounding the Justina Pelletier case has focused attention, not only on the spurious and arbitrary nature of psychiatric diagnoses, but also on the legitimacy and appropriateness of mental health commitments.  It is being widely asserted that these archaic statutes are fundamentally incompatible with current civil rights standards, and the question &amp;ldquo;should mental health commitments be abolished?&amp;rdquo; is being raised in a variety of contexts.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;CRITERIA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clubfoot – A Story of Hope</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/clubfoot-a-story-of-hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 05:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/clubfoot-a-story-of-hope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 27, NPR ran a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2014/01/27/265254533/how-parents-and-the-internet-transformed-clubfoot-treatment&#34;&gt;short piece&lt;/a&gt; on a new treatment for clubfoot.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from the transcript:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Just a decade ago, up to 90 percent of babies…were treated with surgery that usually had to be repeated several times. That created a buildup of scar tissue that often left patients with a lifetime of chronic pain, stiffness, arthritis and medical bills. But with the help of a simple, noninvasive solution and an Internet campaign led by parents, the course of treatment and likely outcomes have changed completely.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murphy&#39;s Mental Health Bill:  An Update</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 10:01:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill-an-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, December 26, at 8:25 p.m., the following comment was posted on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/16/murphys-mental-health-bill/#comment-1177912457&#34;&gt;December 16 post&lt;/a&gt; on the Murphy Mental Health Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Read the article in today&#39;s Wall Street Journal (12/26/13), &#39;A Mental-Health Overhaul&#39;, and you cannot help but be in favor of the Murphy Bill. It is a huge misrepresentation to say it is about &#39;coercive tactics&#39;. Take the bill piece by piece and debate it. If you have experienced the mental healthcare system you would recognize that this legislation is badly needed and long over due.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murphy&#39;s Mental Health Bill</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 17:42:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that pharma-psychiatry has come under considerable criticism in recent years.  In general, they do not respond to these criticisms, but instead they continue to beat the same old drum:  mental illness is becoming increasingly prevalent; we need more mental health screenings; we need more funding for &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;; and we need wider coercive powers to ensure that these sick people take their drugs.  They are also using the school shootings to generate alarm about &amp;ldquo;untreated&amp;rdquo; mental illness, and are calling in support from various quarters, including politicians.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness: A Man-made Monster</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 05:45:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3758&#34; alt=&#34;Nelson Mandela quote&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote-300x210.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the above image online yesterday, at the site &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thethingswesay.com/&#34;&gt;The Things We Say&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental illness is also man-made.  It is the invention of psychiatry - their spurious medicalization of all significant problems of thinking, feeling, and/or behaving.  Its purpose is to legitimize the prescription of dangerous psychotropic drugs to as many people as possible.   &lt;strong&gt;It benefits psychiatrists and drug companies, but damages, stigmatizes, and disempowers its victims.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Galvanizing of a POOR HISTORIAN</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-galvanizing-of-a-poor-historian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 13:28:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-galvanizing-of-a-poor-historian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In hospital ED records from 2007, there is a mention made by a doctor who was dictating his activities, observations of and involvement with me during 5 hours, that I am a&amp;quot;poor historian.&amp;quot; Ironically, I have to this day never met with or even seen this doctor, and vice versa. The conclusion was followed by a little post-script stating that he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know me from Adam if he saw me, despite having written the entire account of me from the first person perspective. Really, I provided very little history, because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really asked, (something I figured was attributable to the hospital records department having in its own filed the most substantial majority of records and historical accounting from me, having been in an adult intensive outpatient program for two years, following a month long inpatient procedure, and after the two years of intensive, was still an outpatient scheduling check-in and progress check-up on a more casual schedule over six months &amp;hellip; right up to the day that all information pertaining to me became non-existent, and new diagnoses, and history of the new diagnoses were filled in. I was not, however, even examined under any terms that might pass for making an effort to actually determine a diagnostic impression, no evaluation nor anything close was performed, but my previously [assumed] diagnosis for which I had been seeing a private doctor regularly, being monitored on medications and therapy for Bi-Polar II (actually it was never diagnosed, I was being treated for &amp;ldquo;target symptoms,&amp;rdquo; which were actually the result of a tardive syndrome induced by olonzapine -cycling between moderate to mild akathisia and fatigue resulting from it) , but records would have shown enough target symptom treatment to inform that I was Bi-Polar II. Bi-Polar [any] was R/O in the newly made that day diagnoses: Psychosis NOS R/O BI-POLAR, and Schizophrenia with history of Schizophrenia (that was the info written in by the phantom Doctor who divined these from no disclosed resource (perhaps Spiritual PhytoEssencing that randomly penetrates his 5th and 6th Chakra in the form of Sound-Thought Ethereal Essence guiding his knowledge, or maybe he was told to write up something for em stat purposes only w/o any responsibility for or contact with the patient, as he noted at the end). It&amp;rsquo;s curious that in my medical history and records, it was first recognized that I am a &amp;ldquo;Poor Historian.&amp;rdquo; What makes me a poor historian in effect today (my records and history are so toxic and viral, far beyond errors, that to allow for them to be transmitted to any new health provider w/o undergoing a major audit and revision into something that seems like it can pass meaningful use muster, would probably direct a well-intentioned but lethal course of treatment, in addition to being a DANGER TO SHIPPING).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugs Out: Brain Stimulators In:  Psychiatry&#39;s Next Assault On Our Humanity?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugs-out-brain-stimulators-in-psychiatry-s-next-assault-on-our-humanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 05:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugs-out-brain-stimulators-in-psychiatry-s-next-assault-on-our-humanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 21, the Guardian/Observer (UK) ran an online article by Vaughan Bell titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/science/2013/sep/22/brains-neuroscience-prozac-psychiatric-drugs&#34;&gt;Changing brains: why neuroscience is ending the Prozac era&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pmace&#34;&gt;Paul Mace on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that although the use of psycho-pharmaceutical products is at an all-time high and is still rising in most parts of the world, the psychiatric promise of &lt;i&gt;drug&lt;/i&gt;-induced happiness may be at, or close to, its peak.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Latest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 07:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 12, Jeffry Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, posted an article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1738168&#34;&gt;IPS to Feature Patrick Kennedy, Celebrate Community Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a preview of an APA conference scheduled for October 10-13 in Philadelphia: &amp;ldquo;Transforming Psychiatric Practice, Reforming Health Care Delivery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman tells us that he is very excited about the conference, and that the theme is particularly relevant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…given the changes we are experiencing in the profession and some of the exciting program events that I hope will support APA’s goal of being in the forefront of changes in the profession under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Madness Contested: An Outstanding Book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 06:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested &lt;/i&gt;has recently been published by PCCS Books.  It&amp;rsquo;s a collection of articles, edited by Steven Coles, Sarah Keenan, and Bob Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a remarkable piece of work.  It covers just about every contentious concept in the present &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; debate, and brings to bear an abundance of new insights and up-to-date research findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 21 articles plus an introduction by the editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the name of each article with a brief quotation from each:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Restraints</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/physical-restraints/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 15:52:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/physical-restraints/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://sectioneduk.wordpress.com/2013/06/19/restraint/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Restraint – 10 ways it harms psychiatric patients&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Sectioned&amp;rsquo;s blog today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It describes Sectioned&amp;rsquo;s own experience in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sectioned lists ten ways he/she was harmed by this practice, and the article is well worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going Against the Stream</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/going-against-the-stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 09:11:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/going-against-the-stream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AN INTERESTING STORY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I came across the following on Twitter from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Sectioned_&#34;&gt;Mental Health @Sectioned_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I just met someone who told me their remarkable story about falling down the rabbit hole into psychiatric sectioning and forced medication.  I listened with fascination to their intricate story in all its twists and turns, looping backwards and forwards with incredible details.  The longer we spoke the more was revealed, the crazier and more believable it sounded.  I was listening, probing for clarification, trying to grasp what happened and why.  First the overview, then the highlights, then more details, expanding out, backing round, drawing me in.  There were many parallels in our stories, and many contrasts.  It reminded me why I don&#39;t really talk in detail about what happened to me: because, if you&#39;ve not experienced it, it sounds unbelievable.  Unless you&#39;ve experienced the scorching reality of forced drugging, seclusion, assault by nurses and patients, it sounds like a mad fantasy.  It&#39;s too far outside most people&#39;s realities for them to contemplate it being true, and so quietly assume you&#39;re deluded.  So it smooths life&#39;s path to make light, to skirt over the details, to change the topic.  And sometimes, sometimes, when I meet someone who&#39;s been through something similar, I listen to their story and realize I&#39;m not the only one.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Abuse in Childhood Make You Crazy?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2013 09:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A NEW PARADIGM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an interesting article by Jacqui Dillon, Lucy Johnstone and Eleanor Longden.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp; Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&#34; href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Trauma-Dissociation-Attachment-and-Neuroscience-Dillo-Johnstone-Longden.pdf&#34;&gt;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp;Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article was published in the Journal of Critical Psychology, Counselling and Psychotherapy (Vol 12, No 3, September 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;A new and profoundly important paradigm for understanding overwhelming emotional pain has emerged over the last few years, with the potential to change the way we conceptualise human suffering across the whole spectrum of mental health difficulties. It is a strongly evidence-based synthesis of findings from trauma studies, attachment theory and neuroscience, which offers new hope for recovery. It also presents a powerful challenge to biomedical model psychiatry in that it is based on scientific evidence that substantiates and attests to what many individuals with first-hand experience of mental health problems have always known –– that the bad things that happen to you can drive you mad.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Victim of Psychiatry Speaks Out</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-victim-of-psychiatry-speaks-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 14:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-victim-of-psychiatry-speaks-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an October 2012 article by Ted Chabasinski.  It&amp;rsquo;s on Mad in America and it&amp;rsquo;s called:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/10/our-task-is-to-take-away-the-power-of-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Our Task Is to Take Away the Power of Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ted tells us that &lt;strong&gt;he was was subjected to electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; when he was six years old&lt;/strong&gt;.  You can see a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/author/tchabasinski/&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the October 2012 article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Those who benefit from the way things are now won’t give up their money and power without a huge fight.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survivor&#39;s Story:  The Dark Threads</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 09:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just read &lt;em&gt;The Dark Threads,&lt;/em&gt; by Jean Davison (Accent Press Ltd, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s autobiographical, and describes with great detail and insight how a young woman of 18 years, whose only problem was acute shyness coupled with a yearning for some meaning in life, made the mistake of visiting a psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jean describes how she was &lt;strong&gt;bullied into accepting psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; She was &lt;strong&gt;drugged into a zombie-like stupor and given electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;  &lt;/strong&gt;She describes graphically the disempowering and humiliating aspects of &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; and the endless patronizing condescension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock &#34;Treatment&#34; Is Not Safe and Provides Little If Any Benefit</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DELICATE THINGS REQUIRE DELICATE HANDLING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, one of my hobbies was making small transistor radios.  It sounds complicated, but is well within the reach of an average 15-year-old.  You get some magazine articles, learn how to read a circuit, and learn how to use a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transistor is a small device – about half the size of a pencil eraser – with three wires coming out of it.  In building a radio receiver, the transistors have to be soldered to other devices which are in turn soldered to other devices, etc…  The soldering iron is plugged into a wall outlet, but no mains electricity reaches the tip of the iron.  However, tiny eddy currents can circulate in the tip, and although they are only of the order of &lt;i&gt;milliamps&lt;/i&gt;, they can burn a transistor in seconds.  What you have to do is unplug the iron from the socket, make the joint with the tip&amp;rsquo;s retained heat, and then replug the iron to have it ready for the next joint.  The point being that &lt;i&gt;delicate things require delicate handling&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;strong&gt;electricity can be very destructive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
