<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Pharmaceutical Industry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/pharmaceutical-industry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pharmaceutical Industry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 05:30:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/pharmaceutical-industry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Mental Health Reform Act of 2016 (SB 2680) Would Be a Huge Step Backwards</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 6, HB 2646 (the Tim Murphy Bill) passed the US House and was sent to the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the present time, a related bill is working its way through the Senate.  This is SB 2680, The Mental Health Reform Act 2016.  It is sponsored by Lamar Alexander (R-TN), Patty Murray (D-WA), Bill Cassidy (R-LA), Chris Murphy (D-CT), David Vitter (R-LA), and Al Franken (D-MN).  The wording of the bill was finalized in March of this year, and it passed out of committee on March 16.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances &#39;Replies&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-replies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 05:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-replies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 19, 2015, I published a post titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/06/19/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-and-johnson/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allen Frances&amp;rsquo; Ties to Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that post, I set out some very serious allegations against Dr. Frances.  I drew these allegations from a document titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Rothman.pdf&#34;&gt;Special Witness Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; dated October 15, 2010.  The report was written by David Rothman, PhD, Professor of Social Medicine at Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rothman&amp;rsquo;s report was produced in the context of a lawsuit filed by the State of Texas against Janssen Pharmaceutica, a subsidiary of Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances&#39; Ties to Johnson &amp; Johnson</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 05:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uottawa.scholarsportal.info/ottawa/index.php/aporia/article/view/3486/3195&#34;&gt;Diagnosisgate: Conflict of Interest at the Top of the Psychiatric Apparatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Paula Caplan, PhD.  The article was published in Aporia, the University of Ottawa nursing journal, in January 2015.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oa.uottawa.ca/journals/aporia/about_aporia.jsp?lang=&#34;&gt;Aporia&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;a peer-reviewed, bilingual, and open access journal dedicated to scholarly debates in nursing and the health sciences.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr, Caplan is a clinical and research psychologist, and an Associate at Harvard&amp;rsquo;s DuBois Institute.  She worked as a consultant to the DSM-IV task force in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s, but resigned from this position after two years.    Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from her February 2014 post on Mad in America &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/02/great-crazy-cover-harm-results-rewriting-history-dsm/&#34;&gt;The Great “Crazy” Cover-up: Harm Results from Rewriting the History of DSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma-funded Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-funded-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-funded-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On August 20, 2014, P&lt;em&gt;sychiatry Advisor&lt;/em&gt; published an article on its website.  The article was written by Leslie Citrome, MD, a professor of psychiatry at New York Medical College in Valhalla, NY, and a member of the Board of Directors of the American Society of Clinical Psychopharmacology.  The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatryadvisor.com/is-bias-against-pharma-funded-research-fair/article/367248/&#34;&gt;Is Bias Against Pharma-Funded Research Fair?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  This is an interesting title, because bias, by its very definition, is unfair.  So the very wording of the question begs the question – which strikes me as unfair.  But let&amp;rsquo;s put that aside.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FDA:  The Fox Guards the Hen House</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 05:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In their Fall 2013 issue, the Journal of Law, Medicine, and Ethics published a symposium of papers by members of the Harvard&amp;rsquo;s Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics.  The symposium was called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ethics.harvard.edu/lab/featured/325-jlme-symposium&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption and Pharmaceutical Policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The symposium focuses on pharmaceutical products generally, but all the material is relevant and important in the context of psychiatric drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will highlight one of these papers:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Light-et-al-document-from-Safra-Institue-on-corruption-1.pdf&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption of Pharmaceuticals and the Myth of Safe and Effective Drugs&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by Donald W. Light, Joel Lexchin, and Jonathan J. Darrow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 05:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In January of this year, Steven Hyman MD, former Director of NIMH and currently a leading psychiatric researcher at MIT and Harvard, published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/npp/journal/v39/n1/full/npp2013181a.html&#34;&gt;Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; in Neuropsychopharmacology.  The article is in the journal&amp;rsquo;s commentary section and is essentially an opinion piece.  Here&amp;rsquo;s Dr. Hyman&amp;rsquo;s summary:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite high prevalence and enormous unmet medical need, the pharmaceutical industry has recently de-emphasized neuropsychiatric disorders as &#39;too difficult&#39; a challenge to warrant major investment.  Here I describe major obstacles to drug discovery and development including a lack of new molecular targets, shortcomings of current animal models, and the lack of biomarkers for clinical trials.  My major focus, however, is on new technologies and scientific approaches to neuropsychiatric disorders that give promise for revitalizing therapeutics and may thus answer industry&#39;s concerns.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sandy Hook Massacre:  The Unanswered Question</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sandy-hook-massacre-the-unanswered-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 05:50:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sandy-hook-massacre-the-unanswered-question/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On December 27, 2013, Connecticut State Police issued a 7,000-page, heavily redacted, report on the massacre that occurred at Sandy Hook Elementary School just over a year earlier (December 14, 2012).  For the record, I have &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;not&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; read the 7,000-page report, but I have read the Wikipedia article &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook_Elementary_School_shooting&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Sandy Hook Elementary School shooting&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, last updated January 4, 2013, and several media reports on the matter, including reports from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/28/nyregion/with-release-of-final-sandy-hook-shooting-report-investigation-is-said-to-be-over.html?hpw&amp;amp;rref=nyregion&amp;amp;_r=0&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.courant.com/2013-12-28/news/hc-lanza-sandy-hook-report1228-20131227_1_peter-lanza-adam-lanza-nancy-lanza&#34;&gt;Hartford Courant&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/police-file-to-be-released-on-newtown-shooting/2013/12/27/36612944-6ec5-11e3-a5d0-6f31cd74f760_story.html&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Over Reliance On Pharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-over-reliance-on-pharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 05:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-over-reliance-on-pharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I recently read &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/data/Journals/AJP/4236/appi.ajp.2011.11010039.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The NIMH-CATIE Schizophrenia Study: What Did We Learn?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, and T. Scott Stroup, MD, MPH.  The article was published in the American Journal of Psychiatry 168:8, August 2011.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;When the CATIE study was designed in 1999-2000, the prevailing opinion of researchers and clinicians alike was that the newer (second-generation) antipsychotic drugs were vastly superior to the older (first-generation) antipsychotic drugs in efficacy and safety. This largely reflected the results of studies sponsored by the manufacturers of the new drugs…, marketing messages of pharmaceutical companies and the hopes of many who wanted better treatments.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children: Harvard&#39;s Shame</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 05:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2012, Mark Olfson, MD, et al, published an article in the Archives of General Psychiatry.  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22868273&#34;&gt;National Trends in the Office-Based Treatment of Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The authors collected data from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Surveys for the period 1993-2009, and looked for trends in antipsychotic prescribing for children, adolescents, and adults in outpatient visits.  Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;&lt;!--
table { 	border: 1px solid gray;     	border-collapse: collapse;      	width: 500px;   	cellspacing: 0; } th {     	background-color: #eee;          border: 1px solid black; }  th#blank {     	background- color: #FFF;  }  th.colOne {         width: 100px; } td {     	text-align: center;  	border: 1px solid black; } table#diagnosis th.data {         width: 120px; }
--&gt;&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;antipsychoticRX&#34; cellspacing=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;colOne&#34;&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Increase in no. of antipsychotic prescriptions per 100 population (1993-2009)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0-13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.24-1.83 (almost 8-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;14-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.78-3.76 (almost 5-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;21+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25-6.18 (almost 2-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;The authors provide a breakdown of the diagnoses assigned to the children and adolescents during the antipsychotic visits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Care For Your Mind (CFYM): A New Advocacy Group</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 06:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 27, Psychiatric Services, a journal of the APA, published an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1745505&#34;&gt;Blog Brings Doctors, Patients Together to Address MH Issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It was written by Vabren Watts, a Psychiatric News Journalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a booster piece for the recently-formed CFYM (Care For Your Mind):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…an online forum for people with mood disorders—along with their families and psychiatrists—to discuss the mental health care system and changes that may affect them under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dangers of SSRI&#39;s</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 06:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SSRI&amp;rsquo;S AND SUICIDE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Fiddaman has a post up today called &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.com/2013/11/mhra-consultant-calls-for.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;MHRA Consultant Calls for Antidepressant Use in Young&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The article highlights some of the dangers associated with SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, and also describes some of the attempts to suppress or discount the significance of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2010, Swedish psychiatrist Göran Isacsson, MD, PhD, published a paper in Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica.  The piece was titled &lt;i&gt;Antidepressant medication prevents suicide in depression,&lt;/i&gt; and reported that of a group of 1,077 depressed people who had committed suicide, only 15.2% had measurable amounts of antidepressants in the blood stream at the time of the suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/protecting-the-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/protecting-the-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/1636&#34;&gt;Safeguarding a Generation of Children from Over-diagnosis and Prescription of Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Dave Traxson, who works as an Educational Psychologist in the UK, and is posted on the  DxSummit website, an online platform for rethinking mental health, a forum in which the concepts underlying pharma-psychiatry are questioned and challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I view the trend towards mass medication of children with mind altering and potentially toxic drugs and ‘drug cocktails’ as a form of psycho-economic imperialism. By that I mean that young peoples’ developing minds are being colonized, using biochemicals, for huge commercial profit and in effect, increased social control. This has resulted from carefully constructed ‘business plans’ in boardrooms which some years ago saw the population of children in the western world as a great market expansion opportunity. The pharmaceutical companies have reaped the huge financial rewards of this rich and very bitter harvest ever since.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The New Holy Grail: Dysfunctional Neural Circuits</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 06:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org//newsArticle.aspx?articleid=1758579&#34;&gt;Change, Challenge, and Opportunity: Psychiatry Through the Looking Glass of Research&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s dated October 17, and was authored  by Steven Hyman, MD, and Jeffrey Lieberman, MD.  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;Mental Health Law on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is President of the APA.  Dr. Hyman was Director of NIMH from 1996 to 2001, and is now the Director of the Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research at the Broad Institute.  The Broad Institute is affiliated with Harvard University, and Dr. Hyman is a Harvard Distinguished Service Professor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jon Rappoport&#39;s Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 05:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Jon Rappoport&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, please take a look.  Here are two quotes from his September 22 post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/2013/09/22/psychiatry-targets-college-students-for-destruction/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry targets college students for destruction&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The concept called &#39;mental disorder&#39; is a sales pitch backed up by extraordinary PR, money, academic gibberish, and government-granted official status.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;People need to wake up to the fact that the whole panoply of human suffering has been co-opted, taken over, redefined, re-translated into a lexicon of pseudoscience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Mass Shooting: Link to SSRIs?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-mass-shooting-link-to-ssris/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 09:45:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-mass-shooting-link-to-ssris/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A mass murder occurred yesterday, September 16, at the U.S. Navy Yard in Washington D.C.  There are reports of at least 12 dead, and several wounded.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.yahoo.com/contract-worker-behind-navy-yard-shooting-rampage-111847531.html&#34;&gt;Early news stories&lt;/a&gt; describe the perpetrator as having &amp;ldquo;mental issues,&amp;rdquo; and it is reported that he &amp;ldquo;…had been &lt;strong&gt;treated since August by the Veterans Administration for his mental problems&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  It is likely that this &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; involved the prescription of psychiatric drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And still no government inquiry into the &lt;strong&gt;link between psycho-pharmaceutical products, especially SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, and acts of violence/suicide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Burden of Mental &#39;Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 09:51:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GrahamCLDavey&#34;&gt;Graham Davey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/socratext&#34;&gt;Richard Pemberton&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link to an interesting article in the August 29, 2013 issue of the Lancet.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/GBD-Mental-2010-from-Lancet.pdf&#34;&gt;Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Harvey A. Whiteford, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Burden of Disease survey is a systematic, scientific attempt to quantify the comparative magnitude of disease, injuries, and risk factors by age, sex, and geography over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Never Mind The Facts; Just Sell More Pills</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 05:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article, recently published in Journal of Contemporary Psychotherapy, on Springer Link.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10879-013-9244-x/fulltext.html&#34;&gt;Shooting the Messenger: The Case of ADHD&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and it was written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently some of the authors had noted in 1995 a marked increase in the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of the condition known as ADHD in southeastern Virginia.  This is a large urban conglomeration of six different cities, including Norfolk, Portsmouth, and Virginia Beach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman is Back</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 05:45:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FearLoathingBTX&#34;&gt;Carl Elliott via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s latest post on Psychiatric News. It&amp;rsquo;s called – believe it or not – &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1723795&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Time to Re-Engage With Pharma? &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;dated August 1, 2013.  And it&amp;rsquo;s classic Dr. Lieberman sleight of hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His opening statement, for instance, reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drug companies aren’t held in high esteem by the public these days.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This may or may not be true.  But note what he&#39;s done.  The issue here is the long-standing and corrupt relationship &lt;i&gt;between psychiatry and the manufacturers of drugs&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;But from his first sentence, Dr. Lieberman has taken psychiatry out of the equation.  He has also lumped the makers of legitimate medicines in with the makers of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Mobilizing Consumer Groups Over Drug Trials Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-mobilizing-consumer-groups-over-drug-trials-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 09:02:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-mobilizing-consumer-groups-over-drug-trials-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2013/jul/21/big-pharma-secret-drugs-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Big pharma mobilising patients in battle over drugs trials data&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt;in last Sunday&amp;rsquo;s Guardian, a UK newspaper.  It was written by Ian Sample, the Guardian&amp;rsquo;s science correspondent.  Here are the two opening sentences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The pharmaceutical industry has &#39;mobilised&#39; an army of patient groups to lobby against plans to force companies to publish secret documents on drugs trials.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs companies publish only a fraction of their results and keep much of the information to themselves, but regulators want to ban the practice. If companies published all of their clinical trials data, independent scientists could reanalyse their results and check companies&#39; claims about the safety and efficacy of drugs.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Has the Moral High Ground (According to Jeffrey Lieberman)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 05:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I suppose everyone knows by now, psychiatry has been on the receiving end of some very serious criticism in recent years.  The criticism has come from many sources, including: survivors of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; non-psychiatric mental health practitioners, journalists, the general public, and even from some psychiatrists themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the criticisms has been equally varied, and includes:  that the concept of mental illness is fundamentally spurious and devoid of explanatory significance; that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; (i.e. drugging people) is ineffective, physically damaging and disempowering; that psychiatry has forged and continues to maintain corrupt and corrupting relationships with the pharmaceutical industry with regards to the peddling of drugs and the hijacking of research for commercial ends; etc…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics in Nursing Homes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-in-nursing-homes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-in-nursing-homes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, The American Society of Consultant Pharmacists published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ascp.com/articles/antipsychotic-medication-use-nursing-facility-residents&#34;&gt;report on the use of neuroleptic drugs in nursing homes&lt;/a&gt;.  According to this report, 25% of nursing home residents receive neuroleptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) consider these prescriptions appropriate only if the recipient is psychotic.  (Obviously we could discuss this at length, but let&amp;rsquo;s set that issue aside for now.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What CMS considers entirely &lt;i&gt;inappropriate&lt;/i&gt;, however, is prescribing these products to residents with dementia as a way of controlling &amp;ldquo;difficult&amp;rdquo; behaviors such as wandering, being abusive, or resisting care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Really Want to Expand Mental Health Services?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 08:02:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT&amp;rsquo;S SPEECH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 3, President Obama delivered a &lt;a href=&#34;http://m.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2013/06/03/remarks-president-national-conference-mental-health&#34;&gt;speech on the expansion of mental health services&lt;/a&gt;.  The occasion was the National Conference on Mental Health, which was held at the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The truth is,&#34; the President told us, &#34;in any given year, one in five adults experience a mental illness — one in five.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
In most human endeavors something is true only if it can be shown to be so.  In psychiatry and politics, however, a statement becomes true if it&#39;s repeated often enough.  For the past 60 years, the APA has been systematically expanding their diagnostic net until – surprise, surprise – it now envelops 20% of the population.  With the lowering of thresholds in DSM-5, we can be sure that this number will continue to rise, and whoever is President then will be able to tell us that one in &lt;i&gt;four&lt;/i&gt; of the population has a mental illness.  Gosh!
&lt;p&gt;Note also that the President uses the term &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;mental disorder.&amp;rdquo;  The APA use the latter term in their manual to make the concept somehow more acceptable.  But these &amp;ldquo;disorders&amp;rdquo; always morph into illnesses in application.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>George Albee, PhD (1921-2006)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/george-albee-phd-1921-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2013 07:08:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/george-albee-phd-1921-2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The late George Albee, psychologist, never accepted the medical model of behavioral/emotional problems.  He fought tirelessly for years to insulate psychology from the encroaching medicalization of its subject matter, and he died in 2006 believing that his efforts had failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He authored more than 200 articles.  As early as the 50&amp;rsquo;s and 60&amp;rsquo;s, he argued that &lt;strong&gt;social factors such as racism, poverty, and child abuse were largely responsible for the conditions known as mental illness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Payments to Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2013 05:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 12 of this year, the Los Angeles Daily News ran an article by Susan Abram titled:  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailynews.com/ci_22751458/california-doctors-report-prescription-drug-company-payments-speaking-engagements&#34;&gt;Doctors report big pharma payouts for drug endorsements&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It discusses the financial ties between physicians and drug companies in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;In fact, hundreds of physicians, psychiatrists, and medical school faculty members across California are on the payroll of major drug companies, earning tens of thousands of dollars for speaking to other medical professionals at events held by industry leaders that make drugs such as Advair, Cymbalta, Viagra and Zoloft.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Dollars Behind Mental Health Websites</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-dollars-behind-mental-health-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2013 05:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-dollars-behind-mental-health-websites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on MINNPOST, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.minnpost.com/second-opinion/2013/05/many-mental-illness-websites-show-drug-company-bias-study-finds&#34;&gt;Many mental-illness websites show drug-company bias, study finds&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;dated May 16.  The article is by Susan Perry, and presents the results of a Web survey of mental health websites conducted by John Read and A. Cain from the University of Auckland, New Zealand.  The original study was published in Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica.  You can see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acps.12146/abstract&#34;&gt;abstract here&lt;/a&gt;.  The full article is behind a paywall.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/leoniefen&#34;&gt;Leonie Fennell&lt;/a&gt; for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Still Fighting Back: Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 11:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, is president-elect of the APA, and is scheduled to take over the reins from Dr. Dilip Jeste this month.  Never in its history has the APA been subject to such scrutiny or criticism from such diverse sources, and one might reasonably have expected Dr. Lieberman to open on a conciliatory note, promising investigations, reforms, etc….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no!  He&amp;rsquo;s in the ring slugging furiously from the opening bell.  Two days ago (May 20) he published an article in Scientific American titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/mind-guest-blog/2013/05/20/dsm-5-caught-between-mental-illness-stigma-and-anti-psychiatry-prejudice/&#34;&gt;DSM-5: Caught between Mental Illness Stigma and Anti-Psychiatry Prejudice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – Embracing a Social Paradigm?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 07:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the May 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;The future of academic psychiatry may be social&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt;by Stefan Priebe, Tom Burns, and Tom K. J. Craig.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NSVo2eU9meHQtOUU/edit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The past 30 years have produced no discoveries leading to major changes in psychiatric practice. The rules regulating research and a dominant neurobiological paradigm may both have stifled creativity. Embracing a social paradigm could generate real progress and, simultaneously, make the profession more attractive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Effect of DSM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 12:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep two dictionaries on my desk.  The first is a 1964 Webster&amp;rsquo;s; the second is a 2009 Webster&amp;rsquo;s.  This morning I looked up the word &amp;ldquo;depression&amp;rdquo; in both books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1964:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;n. &lt;b&gt;1.&lt;/b&gt; a depressing or being depressed.  &lt;b&gt;2.&lt;/b&gt; a depressed part or place; hollow or low place.  &lt;b&gt;3.&lt;/b&gt; low spirits; dejection.  &lt;b&gt;4.&lt;/b&gt; a decrease in force, activity, amount, etc.  &lt;b&gt;5.&lt;/b&gt; a period marked by slackening of business activity, much unemployment, falling prices and wages, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bereavement:  An &#34;Opportunity&#34; for Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 10:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new post on Mick Bramham&amp;rsquo;s website called &amp;ldquo;A time to grieve, a time to console, and a time to profit?&amp;rdquo;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.mythsandrisks.info/2013/04/a-time-to-grieve-time-to-console-and.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have thought that, given the adverse publicity that pharma has been receiving in recent years, they would be easing up on their expansionist agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you would be wrong.  The &lt;strong&gt;APA has declared open season on bereavement&lt;/strong&gt;, and although DSM-5 won&amp;rsquo;t be released for a few more weeks, &lt;strong&gt;Eli Lilly is already grooming their SNRI Cymbalta as a &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for this pseudo illness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suicide Risk with Antidepressants</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-risk-with-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 15:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-risk-with-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There has been a great deal of discussion on this topic in recent years.  Families of suicide victims tend to blame the pills; the pharma companies blame the depression for which the pills were prescribed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;rsquo;ve read and heard a good many reports from people who have taken the pills and shortly afterwards experienced fairly strong suicidal urges pretty much out of the blue.  The frequency and similarity of these accounts is – at the very least – cause for concern.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Website:  by Mick Bramham</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 09:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across &lt;i&gt;Thinking About Mental Health: Myths, treatment risks &amp;amp; alternatives.&lt;/i&gt;  You can find it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s written by Mick Bramham, from Dorset, England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/chemical-imbalances.html&#34;&gt;Depression: Serotonin Imbalance?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The whole idea of antidepressants supposedly correcting chemical imbalances has more to do with drug company marketing than evidence-based science.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Unfortunately, drug companies are known to exaggerate the benefits of their products and to play down the risks;&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Words to Shape Attitudes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-power-of-words-to-shape-attitudes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2013 14:40:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-power-of-words-to-shape-attitudes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/04/19/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/&#34;&gt;Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?&lt;/a&gt;  The post was based on a study by Drs. Harrow and Jobe in which they speculated that the high relapse rate of &amp;ldquo;schizophrenics&amp;rdquo; who stop taking their drugs may have more to do with drug &lt;i&gt;withdrawal&lt;/i&gt; than the supposed drug efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, at BeyondMeds, pointed out that these drugs should not be called tranquilizers because some of their effects (e.g. akathisia, tardive dyskinesia, etc.) are anything but tranquil.  And this, of course, is a good point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPs Prescribe More Psychotropic Drugs than Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 10:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Psychiatrists, when challenged about the massive increase in psychotropic drug prescriptions, sometimes point out that the bulk of this prescribing is done – not by them – but by primary care doctors (GPs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; claim in this regards may be true, it is also somewhat misleading.  The &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; for which these drugs are being prescribed were &lt;i&gt;invented&lt;/i&gt; by psychiatrists, and &lt;strong&gt;it is these inventions that legitimize the prescribing activity&lt;/strong&gt;.  And, of course, as the psychiatrists invent more illnesses, the prescription rates increase proportionately.  Without the perceived legitimacy of the DSM, GPs simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t dish out antidepressants, anxiolytics, and stimulants on the scale seen today, if for no other reason than the fear of lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now – by Popular Demand – Ritalin for the Elderly!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 10:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the old days, which I well remember, misbehavior in school was considered a disciplinary problem.  This included not paying attention, fidgeting, not applying oneself to one&amp;rsquo;s work, talking, interrupting the teacher, etc., etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the APA decided that these various activities were really symptoms of a mental illness, and thereby created the ever-burgeoning market for Ritalin and other drugs which, we are falsely told, correct the &amp;ldquo;chemical imbalance&amp;rdquo; in these children&amp;rsquo;s brains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Psychotropic Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 10:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytransformation.blogspot.com/2011/04/fishing-lessons-from-my-son.html#.UWBNjZOG0eU&#34;&gt;nice article at Involuntary Transformation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Nathan, poses a very interesting question:  since drugs cause damage to children and there are many better alternatives, &lt;strong&gt;why do so many parents choose the drug option&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan goes on to suggest that the reason lies in the effort that the pharmaceutical industry invests in marketing, and he calls for &amp;ldquo;…complete and total transparency in all Mental Health Services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Conflicts of Interest in Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 11:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come across an article by Lisa Cosgrove et al entitled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jep.12016/abstract&#34;&gt;Conflicts of interest and the quality of recommendations in clinical guidelines.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;It was published in the Journal of &lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Evaluation in Clinical Practice in December of last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone knows, the APA publishes the DSM, but they also publish &amp;ldquo;Clinical Practice Guidelines&amp;rdquo; for various &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the condition known as major depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cosgrove and her colleagues examined the guidelines for major depression to see if the authors had financial or intellectual conflicts of interest.  An example of a financial conflict of interest would be recommending drug treatment when one is on the payroll of a drug company.  An example of an intellectual conflict of interest would be relying on and citing a poor quality study in support of a position in which one had a stake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma&#39;s Subtle but Pernicious Marketing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alice Keys, MD, has recently written a short article for Mad in America.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/he-who-pays-the-piper/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Keys points out that to maintain a medical license, one must accumulate continuing education credits, and that these credits have to be approved by state licensing boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that pharmaceutical companies have largely hijacked this process in recent decades, and that their &amp;ldquo;educational&amp;rdquo; presentations might be better described as infomercials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Marketing Ploy: Promoting Mental Health Evaluations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 05:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Hersteltalent on Twitter, I came across this newspaper article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/03/12/mental-health-checkups/1981495/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Doctors Urge Mental Health Screenings with Physicals&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It appeared in USA Today, and was written by Jessica Contrera of the Lafayette, Indiana Journal and Courier.  Dateline March 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article, which is written for the general public, is that when you go in to your doctor for a check-up, you should ask for a mental evaluation as well.  The article reminds us that &amp;ldquo;25% of American adults suffer from some form of mental illness each year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal from Benzodiazepines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Important updates on this subject can be found at the posts listed at the bottom of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I&#39;ve recently come across an article by Matt Samet called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/social-vacuum/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Social Vacuum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&#39;s dated March 2013, and was published on Robert Whitaker&#39;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Matt had been taking a benzodiazepine for some time, and while on a tapering withdrawal, he experienced some distressing symptoms, including some acute social discomfort.  (For a full account of benzo withdrawal –&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benzodiazepine_withdrawal_syndrome&#34;&gt; click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Pharma, by Ben Goldacre</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 23:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All the awful things you&amp;rsquo;ve heard and read about the pharmaceutical companies are documented on the pages of &lt;i&gt;Bad Pharma&lt;/i&gt; with compelling clarity and abundant references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Goldacre is a British physician.  His primary issue is the safety and efficacy of pharmaceutical products in general medicine, but he has a lot to say about psychiatric drugs also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs are tested by the people who manufacture them, in poorly designed trials, on hopelessly small numbers of weird, unrepresentative patients, and analysed using techniques which are flawed by design, in such a way that they exaggerate the benefits of treatments.&#34;(p. x)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma and Mental Health: Hand-in-Glove</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 19:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another interesting article:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/02/24/academic-integrity-in-ireland-and-the-uk-is-there-any-such-thing/&#34;&gt;Academic Integrity in Ireland and the UK: Is there any such thing?&lt;/a&gt; at Leonie fennells&amp;rsquo; Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about financial ties between pharmaceutical companies and psychiatrists.  Same old story; different location.  It&amp;rsquo;s worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Becky @yobluemama2 on Twitter for drawing my attention to this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fable for Our Times</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-fable-for-our-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 15:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-fable-for-our-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Several of my recent posts have been about fundamental issues. Here&#39;s something a little lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;On the coast of Maine near the Machias Estuary, the Atlantic Ocean pounds the cliffs and beaches.  The scenery is wild and beautiful, and there are lots of seagulls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One spring a seagull was born named Jimmy Brady.  He was a fine little seagull, but his brothers picked on him something terrible, and he grew up feeling nervous and very unsure of himself.  He thought he was ugly, and when it came time to jump off the cliff and fly, Jimmy just couldn’t do it.  He didn&amp;rsquo;t believe that a seagull, as horrible and klutzy as he believed himself to be, could ever soar over the waves as a seagull should.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Big Pharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 22:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have written frequently on this website about the hand-in-glove relationship between psychiatrists and the pharmaceutical companies.  It is my general position that the business-first orientation of the pharmaceutical companies, coupled with their willingness to pay large sums of money to co-operative psychiatrists, has been, and continues to be, a corrupting influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently come across two articles by Carl Elliot, MD, PhD. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/how-to-get-away-with-academic-misconduct-at-the-university-of-minnesota/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;How to Get Away with Academic Misconduct at the University of Minnesota,&amp;rdquo; &lt;/a&gt;and&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/and-thats-the-news-from-the-department-of-psychiatry-where-all-the-nurses-are-supportive-of-research-and-all-the-patients-are-reviewed-for-possible-research-candid/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;And That’s the News from the Department of Psychiatry.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mandatory Mental Health Screenings for Schoolchildren</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 19:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A regular commenter to this website has drawn my attention to a bill that has been proposed in the Connecticut state legislature.  The bill would require public school and homeschooled children to be assessed by mental health practitioners at grades 6, 8, 10, and 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bill, sponsored by Senator Toni Harp and Representative Toni Walker, is in response to the recent Sandy Hook murders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it starts.  Given the built-in vagueness of the DSM, and the inclusiveness bias of the mental health business, the outcome of these screenings (should the bill become law) is predictable: more and more parents disempowered with regards to their parenting responsibilities; more drugged children, and, tragically, more mass murders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold-blooded Killers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 14:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday our local newspaper ran an article called &amp;ldquo;Mental Health Needs Reform.&amp;rdquo;  It was written by a psychologist, and the main thrust of the piece was that if &amp;ldquo;serious mental health care reform&amp;rdquo; is not implemented, we will see more mass murders similar to those at Aurora and Newtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article contained several unwarranted assumptions, and recommended that mental hospitals &amp;ldquo;rebuild facilities for treating those patients.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position, of course, is that there are no mental illnesses, and that cold-blooded killers are not sick in any meaningful sense of the term, but are, rather, individuals who have not internalized an age-appropriate respect for the lives and welfare of other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dangerous People</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dangerous-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 18:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dangerous-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Connecticut mass murders of last month, a great deal of attention, official and otherwise, is being focused on the “mentally ill.”  Politicians of all persuasions are proclaiming that we need more funding for the so-called mental health services, and predictably, the various practitioners and centers are lining up with their hands outstretched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spurious logic, of course, is never identified, or if it is, it gets lost in the rhetoric.  Mental illness is presented (and accepted) as the proximate cause of the violence.  If one were to ask a mental health practitioner why an individual was so crazy and acted so brutally, the reply would be:  Because he has a mental illness.  But if one were to press the matter and ask:  How do you know he has a mental illness? the only possible response is: Because he is so crazy and acted so brutally.  The only evidence for the so-called illness is the very behavior it purports to explain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  More of the Same - Turf Expansion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 19:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until now, I’ve pretty much steered clear of DSM-5.  My reason for this is that the upcoming revision represents, to my mind, a distraction from the central issue, i.e., that the whole notion of mental illness is spurious, destructive nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position is that the purpose of DSM is to expand psychiatric turf and to legitimize the pushing of mood/behavior-altering pharmaceuticals. In the US (and I believe in most developed countries) you can’t prescribe a drug without a diagnosis.  And the APA has never neglected its primary mission in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Psychiatrists, the Drug Reps, and the Green, Green, Dollars</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-psychiatrists-the-drug-reps-and-the-green-green-dollars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 10:26:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-psychiatrists-the-drug-reps-and-the-green-green-dollars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve known for years that drug companies give gifts to physicians.  The gifts have taken many forms – pens, vacations, meals, free samples, etc&amp;hellip;  Physicians always insisted that these gifts didn’t influence their prescribing practice – that they always prescribed strictly in the best interests of their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two trends have been exposed in recent years which demonstrate just how depraved this hand-in-glove relationship has become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the “thought leader” ruse.  Here’s how it works.  A drug rep, usually an attractive young, perfectly groomed female, approaches a physician, usually male, and tells the physician that he has been identified as a thought leader in his area, and that they would like to recruit him to give presentations to groups of physicians and other healthcare workers.  The physician, of course, will be paid generously for his time.  He says “sure,” and the dance begins.  The drug rep arranges the “training” sessions.  The drug company provides the script and the refreshments.  The mark – I mean the physician – delivers the script, in which the merits of the drug company’s product are lauded to the detriment of competitors.  At the end of the session, the physician receives a check and goes away contented.  Over the next few months more such sessions will be organized and the physician begins to think of his “speech” checks as regular income.  He will also receive “coaching” from the drug rep if his presentation seems to lack the kind of conviction that the drug company feels warranted.  (After all, they are paying the piper).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
