<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ECT on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/ect/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ECT on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 05:30:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/ect/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deep Sleep &#34;Therapy&#34; in Australia in the 1960&#39;s and 70&#39;s. Could Something Like This Happen Today?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/deep-sleep-therapy-in-australia-in-the-1960-s-and-70-s-could-something-like-this-happen-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/deep-sleep-therapy-in-australia-in-the-1960-s-and-70-s-could-something-like-this-happen-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting story from Australia, recently back in the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1962 to 1979, psychiatrist Harry Bailey, MD, serving as chief psychiatrist at Chelmsford Private Hospital in New South Wales, practiced &amp;ldquo;deep sleep therapy&amp;rdquo;, which involved keeping people in barbiturate-induced comas for days or even weeks.  Twenty-four of the individuals who received this &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; died while still in the hospital.  Many more died or showed permanent brain damage after discharge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances: Still Spinning the Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-still-spinning-the-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 05:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-still-spinning-the-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 4, 2020, the very eminent Allen Frances, MD, published an article in Aeon, which according to its &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/about&#34;&gt;About page&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;a digital magazine, publishing some of the most profound and provocative thinking on the web. We ask the big questions and find the freshest, most original answers, provided by leading thinkers on science, philosophy, society and the arts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/the-lure-of-cool-brain-research-is-stifling-psychotherapy&#34;&gt;The lure of ‘cool’ brain research is stifling psychotherapy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  The central theme is that prior to 1990, the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) &amp;ldquo;appreciated the need for a well-rounded approach [to mental health] and maintained a balanced research budget that covered an extraordinarily wide range of topics and techniques.&amp;rdquo;  However, since 1990, the opening year of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decade_of_the_Brain&#34;&gt;Decade of the Brain&lt;/a&gt;, the NIMH has &amp;ldquo;increasingly narrowed its focus almost exclusively to brain biology – leaving out everything else that makes us human, both in sickness and in health.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I was a Victim and Came Back: My Empowerment Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/i-was-a-victim-and-came-back-my-empowerment-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 09:35:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/i-was-a-victim-and-came-back-my-empowerment-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;  &lt;img class=&#34;alignnone wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;               &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;                                              &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own story, some fortunate, some less so. Mine is a story of abuse, neglect and mental illness, and the long road back.  I offer it for whatever hope and guidance it may provide for others currently suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Me, A Victim &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1956 when I was thirteen and starting in middle school, my mother had the first of her several operations for intestinal cancer. She told me that she had “tumors,” but that meant one thing to me— cancer.  Around the same time, I, too, began having stomach pains along with constipation like hers. I always had problems getting along with other kids, being teased and harassed, and being nervous, and now I was in great distress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speaking Out Against Electric Shocks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/speaking-out-against-electric-shocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 05:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/speaking-out-against-electric-shocks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&#34;…they&#39;re human beings, for God&#39;s sake!  In the name of
everything holy, how can they do that to them?&#34; (p 108)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Other Mrs. Smith, &lt;/em&gt;by Bonnie Burstow, 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;In the March 2017 issue of the Journal of ECT, there was an editorial titled:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/ectjournal/Citation/2017/03000/Electroconvulsive_Therapy__ECT__in_the_News__.1&#34;&gt;Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT) in the News: &amp;ldquo;Balance&amp;rdquo; Leads to Bias.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors are Melissa Choy, BA; Kate Farber, BA; and Charles Kellner, MD.  Dr. Kellner is Chief of Geriatric Psychiatry and Director of ECT Services at Mt. Sinai Medical Center, NY, and is clearly the senior author.  I was unable to find much information concerning Ms. Choy or Ms. Farber.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECT:  Safe and Effective for Agitation and Aggression in Cases of Dementia?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-safe-and-effective-for-agitation-and-aggression-in-cases-of-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 05:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-safe-and-effective-for-agitation-and-aggression-in-cases-of-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 25 of this year, Psychiatric Times published an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/UjKaj-March-25-2015Psychiatric_Times_-_Dementia_Agitation_and_Aggression_The_Role_of_Electroconvulsive_Therapy_-_2015-03-25.pdf&#34;&gt;Dementia, Agitation, and Aggression: The Role of Electroconvulsive Therapy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  The author is Manjola Ujkaj, MD PhD, and the article&amp;rsquo;s subtitle is &amp;ldquo;What role might electroconvulsive therapy play for short-term treatment of agitation and aggression in patients with dementia?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/contribute-site&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt; Psychiatric Times is a medical trade publication that covers news, reports, and clinical content related to psychiatry &amp;ldquo;for psychiatrists and allied mental health professionals who treat mental disorders.&amp;rdquo;  The circulation of the monthly print publication is approximately 40,000.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECT for Agitation and Aggression in Dementia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-for-agitation-and-aggression-in-dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 05:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-for-agitation-and-aggression-in-dementia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, 2014, the International Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry published an article by Deepa Archarya, PhD, et al.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Archaya%2C+Harper%2C+Achtyes%2C+seiner+2014&#34;&gt;Safety and utility of acute electroconvulsive therapy for agitation and aggression in dementia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  Here are the authors&amp;rsquo; conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Electroconvulsive therapy may be a safe treatment option to reduce symptoms of agitation and aggression in patients with dementia whose behaviors are refractory to medication management.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
In their Introduction section, the authors write:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite the high prevalence of these agitated and aggressive behaviors, there are currently no treatment options approved by US Food and Drug Administration for this indication. Nonpharmacological interventions, including environmental and behavioral modification, are difficult to implement in nursing home settings because of low staff-to-resident ratios.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Macabre Celebration:  80 Years of Convulsive &#39;Therapy&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-macabre-celebration-80-years-of-convulsive-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 05:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-macabre-celebration-80-years-of-convulsive-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the June 2014 issue of the Journal of ECT.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Max Fink, MD, and is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/ectjournal/citation/2014/06000/celebrating_80_years_of_inducing_brain_seizures_as.3.aspx&#34;&gt;Celebrating 80 Years of Inducing Brain Seizures as Psychiatric Treatment.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/em&gt;Dr. Fink is a psychiatrist and neurologist, and professor emeritus of psychiatry and neurology at the State University of New York, Stony Brook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is short (approximately 400 words), and is essentially a tribute to Ladislas Meduna for his discovery  &amp;ldquo;…that induced seizures alleviated severe psychiatric disorders…&amp;rdquo;, which Dr. Fink describes as  &amp;ldquo;…a remarkable medical advance…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/transcranial-magnetic-stimulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 05:58:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/transcranial-magnetic-stimulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;TMS is a psychiatric treatment that uses a rapidly alternating magnetic field to induce electric currents in the brain.  These currents stimulate neurons, causing them to &amp;ldquo;fire.&amp;rdquo; When used repetitively, TMS is said to alter the excitability of the brain area that has been stimulated.  In the psychiatric field, TMS is being used increasingly as a treatment for depression, particularly with so-called treatment-resistant clients.  I Googled the string &amp;ldquo;TMS + depression&amp;rdquo; and got 1.35 million hits.  So the idea is attracting attention.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Human Behavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 05:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A couple of months ago I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/11/21/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/&#34;&gt;article concerning ECT&lt;/a&gt; which generated some controversy.  One of the issues that came up was the relationship between &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;biological &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;explanations of human activity and more global explanations, which, for want of a better term, I&amp;rsquo;ll call person-centered explanations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any human activity can be viewed from different levels of abstraction.  Suppose, for instance, that I am sitting in my living room reading a book.  Then I put the book down, stand up, and go outside.  If the question were to be asked:  why did he put the book down and go outside? A wide range of perspectives and answers are possible.  One could, for instance, focus on the fact that I am a biological organism, and one could develop a detailed and comprehensive flow sheet of every muscle movement, every heartbeat, every sensory input, neural impulse etc., that had occurred from the moment that I put the book down until I was standing outside.  Such an account might be more or less detailed.  There would, of course, be physical limitations on the amount of information of this sort that is attainable, but from a theoretical point of view, one could compile a detailed, complete, and accurate biological account of the actions in question.  And such an account would be a valid response to the question:  why did he put the book down and go outside.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT) Effective?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 05:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ECT, or shock treatment as it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes called, is a controversial topic.  Adherents describe it as safe and effective; opponents condemn its use as damaging and ineffective.  But it is still widely used in the US and in other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The treatment consists essentially of passing sufficient electricity across the brain to cause a seizure.  Clients are anesthetized during the process.  It is used primarily in cases of severe depression.  Typically, shock treatment is administered twice a week until the depression remits or until no further improvement is noted in two successive sessions.  Most courses of treatment involve about eight sessions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECT And Adolescents At The Mayo Clinic</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-and-adolescents-at-the-mayo-clinic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 07:01:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-and-adolescents-at-the-mayo-clinic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the APA annual convention in San Francisco in May of this year, Chad Puffer, DO, of the Mayo Clinic, presented a poster display titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Puffer_Wall_APA_2013-05-13-1.pdf&#34;&gt;ECT Use in Adolescents at the Mayo Clinic&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;The poster was reported by Caroline Cassels of Medscape.com, a month later (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/806923&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ECT in Kids:  Safe, Effective, Robust and …Underutilized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), and drew critical &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cchrint.org/2013/07/02/another-assault-on-americas-children-electroshocking-kids-promoted-as-safe-effective/&#34;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; a week later (July 2) from Kelly Patricia O&amp;rsquo;Meara of CCHR International.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t spot any of this until last week, when it came up on the Twitter feed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dxrevisionwatch&#34;&gt;DxRevision Watch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/peterkinderman&#34;&gt;Peter Kinderman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Involuntary Shock Treatment To Be Banned in Ireland</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-shock-treatment-to-be-banned-in-ireland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 05:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/involuntary-shock-treatment-to-be-banned-in-ireland/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Talla Trialogue on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I recently read an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejournal.ie/electro-shock-therapy-unwilling-patients-ireland-983018-Jul2013/&#34;&gt;article in journal.ie&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kathleen Lynch, Minister of State for Disability, Equality, Mental Health and Older People, has reportedly stated that &amp;ldquo;…the law will be changed so that unwilling patients will no longer be forced to receive ECT.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, if an individual refuses ECT, his refusal can be overridden by the signatures of two psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, not everyone is in favor of the ban on forced ECT.  There&amp;rsquo;s an article by Marie Feely, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imn.ie/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=4493:proposed-ban-on-involuntary-ect-criticised&amp;amp;catid=61:news&amp;amp;Itemid=28&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Proposed ban on Involuntary ECT criticized &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;published in irishmedicalnews in January 2012.  The article reports on &lt;i&gt;a survey of consultant psychiatrists&lt;/i&gt; published in December 2011.  Ms. Feely writes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Has the Moral High Ground (According to Jeffrey Lieberman)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 05:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I suppose everyone knows by now, psychiatry has been on the receiving end of some very serious criticism in recent years.  The criticism has come from many sources, including: survivors of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; non-psychiatric mental health practitioners, journalists, the general public, and even from some psychiatrists themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the criticisms has been equally varied, and includes:  that the concept of mental illness is fundamentally spurious and devoid of explanatory significance; that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; (i.e. drugging people) is ineffective, physically damaging and disempowering; that psychiatry has forged and continues to maintain corrupt and corrupting relationships with the pharmaceutical industry with regards to the peddling of drugs and the hijacking of research for commercial ends; etc…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECT – New and Improved?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-new-and-improved/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 13:15:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ect-new-and-improved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just come across a strange article on Mad in America.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Researchers look at therapeutic benefits of ketamine&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manchester.ac.uk/aboutus/news/display/?id=9956&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It doesn&amp;rsquo;t identify an author, but it&amp;rsquo;s from the University of Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening paragraph says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The largest trial into the use of Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT) in the UK in more than 30 years will look into how the use of the Class C drug ketamine might reduce the side effects of ECT for those being treated for severe depression.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock &#34;Treatment&#34; Is Not Safe and Provides Little If Any Benefit</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DELICATE THINGS REQUIRE DELICATE HANDLING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, one of my hobbies was making small transistor radios.  It sounds complicated, but is well within the reach of an average 15-year-old.  You get some magazine articles, learn how to read a circuit, and learn how to use a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transistor is a small device – about half the size of a pencil eraser – with three wires coming out of it.  In building a radio receiver, the transistors have to be soldered to other devices which are in turn soldered to other devices, etc…  The soldering iron is plugged into a wall outlet, but no mains electricity reaches the tip of the iron.  However, tiny eddy currents can circulate in the tip, and although they are only of the order of &lt;i&gt;milliamps&lt;/i&gt;, they can burn a transistor in seconds.  What you have to do is unplug the iron from the socket, make the joint with the tip&amp;rsquo;s retained heat, and then replug the iron to have it ready for the next joint.  The point being that &lt;i&gt;delicate things require delicate handling&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;strong&gt;electricity can be very destructive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
