<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Antidepressants on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/antidepressants/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Antidepressants on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 05:30:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/antidepressants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deep Sleep &#34;Therapy&#34; in Australia in the 1960&#39;s and 70&#39;s. Could Something Like This Happen Today?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/deep-sleep-therapy-in-australia-in-the-1960-s-and-70-s-could-something-like-this-happen-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/deep-sleep-therapy-in-australia-in-the-1960-s-and-70-s-could-something-like-this-happen-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting story from Australia, recently back in the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1962 to 1979, psychiatrist Harry Bailey, MD, serving as chief psychiatrist at Chelmsford Private Hospital in New South Wales, practiced &amp;ldquo;deep sleep therapy&amp;rdquo;, which involved keeping people in barbiturate-induced comas for days or even weeks.  Twenty-four of the individuals who received this &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; died while still in the hospital.  Many more died or showed permanent brain damage after discharge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances and the Increasing Use of Antidepressants</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 05:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, 2018, the prestigious and venerable psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, gave an interview to Christiane Amanpour on CNN.  You can see the video &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/videos/tv/2018/05/17/amanpour-allen-frances-antidepressants-interview.cnn&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;em&gt;How Antidepressant Withdrawal &amp;ldquo;Can Trap People&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how the interview opened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;CA:  &#34;So you know, I just wanted to start by saying that who knew that antidepressants were addictive.  It&#39;s not what you associate with things like antidepressants.  You think of pain-killers, obviously, and drugs and alcohol, and cigarettes.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Responds:  Antidepressants Really Work.  Really?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-responds-antidepressants-really-work-really/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-responds-antidepressants-really-work-really/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 25, 2017, Fredrik Hieronymus et al published a meta-analysis in Molecular Psychiatry.  The study is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/Hieronymus-mp2017147a.pdf&#34;&gt;Efficacy of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors in the absence of side effects: a mega-analysis of citalopram and paroxetine in adult depression&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Elias Eriksson, PhD, Head of the Department of Pharmacology, University of Gothenburg, Sweden, is the principal author, but as Fredrik Hieronymus is the first author listed, I will refer to the article as Hieronymus et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRIs:  Minimal Effectiveness and High Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssris-minimal-effectiveness-and-high-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 05:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssris-minimal-effectiveness-and-high-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month (February 2017), the journal BMC Psychiatry published a study by James Christian  Jakobsen et al.  The study is titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Jakobsen-et-al-SSRI-study.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;versus placebo in patients with major depressive disorder. A systematic review &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;with meta-analysis and Trial Sequential Analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research was a meta-analysis – i.e. it combined the findings from several earlier studies.  Here are the authors&amp;rsquo; conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;SSRIs might have statistically significant effects on depressive symptoms, but all trials were at high risk of bias and the clinical significance seems questionable. SSRIs significantly increase the risk of both serious and non-serious adverse events. The potential small beneficial effects seem to be outweighed by harmful effects.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances:  Still Blaming Everyone But Himself</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-still-blaming-everyone-but-himself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-still-blaming-everyone-but-himself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 7, Allen Frances, MD, posted an article on the HuffPost site.  The piece was titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/antidepressants-work-but-_b_9849478.html&#34;&gt;Antidepressants Work, But Only For Really Depressed People&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superficially, the article presents itself as a call to limit the prescribing of the so-called antidepressant drugs to severe cases; but the piece can, I suggest, be more accurately characterized as Dr. Frances&amp;rsquo;s latest attempt to distance himself, and psychiatry in general, from the pill-peddling frenzy that has characterized the profession for the past thirty or forty years&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klonopin and prozac withdrawal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/klonopin-and-prozac-withdrawal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 05:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/klonopin-and-prozac-withdrawal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been almost 3 months since I have ingested any antidepressants or benzos. Almost died after drinking a large amount of vodka with the daily does of pills. Went to a rehab for a month and have been clean since. This is after over 27 years of benzos and prozac. I am 60 years old and am finally coming a awake. The Withdrawals, notably the restless leg and horrible cramping have been horrid at night, but I am totally committed to staying off the evil pills! Thanks for listening!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Germanwings Crash:  Flying Under the Influence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-germanwings-crash-flying-under-the-influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 05:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-germanwings-crash-flying-under-the-influence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 24, 2015, a twenty-seven-year-old German pilot named Andreas Lubitz flew an Airbus A 320 into a French mountainside, killing himself and the 149 other people on board.  Mr. Lubitz was co-piloting the flight, and he caused the aircraft to crash by locking the pilot out of the flight deck and setting the autopilot to descend to 100 feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the descent, he was contacted by civilian and military traffic controllers, and by the crew of another aircraft, but he made no response.  He also ignored repeated and increasingly urgent requests from the captain to be readmitted to the flight deck.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting The Placebo Effect:  Deceiving People For Their Own Good?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/exploiting-the-placebo-effect-deceiving-people-for-their-own-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 05:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/exploiting-the-placebo-effect-deceiving-people-for-their-own-good/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Readers may remember that a few weeks ago I became involved in an online debate with the very eminent and scholarly psychiatrist Ronald Pies, MD.  That exchange was initiated by a post I wrote concerning a paper on the chemical imbalance theory that Jeffrey Lacasse, PhD, and Jonathan Leo, PhD, had published in the Behavior Therapist in October 2015.  In that paper, Drs. Lacasse and Leo had drawn attention to certain aspects of Dr. Pies&amp;rsquo; work, but they had also focused some attention on Daniel Carlat, MD, psychiatrist, and author of &lt;em&gt;Unhinged:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Trouble with Psychiatry - A Doctor&amp;rsquo;s Revelations about a Profession in Crisis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Link Between Psychiatric Drugs and Violence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-link-between-psychiatric-drugs-and-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 05:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-link-between-psychiatric-drugs-and-violence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s most obvious vulnerabilities is the fact that various so-called antidepressant drugs induce homicidal and suicidal feelings and actions in some people, especially late adolescents and young adults.  This fact is not in dispute, but psychiatry routinely downplays the risk, and insists that the benefits of these drugs outweigh any risks of actual violence that might exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two research studies that indicate a link between SSRI&amp;rsquo;s and violence, but both studies have limitations that make it difficult to draw firm conclusions.  The studies are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants:  Drugs, Not Medication</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 05:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 7, John Read, PhD, a psychologist at Swinburne University of Technology in Melbourne, published a short article on Mad in America.  The title is:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/04/largest-survey-date-finds-high-rates-emotional-interpersonal-adverse-effects-antidepressants/&#34;&gt;Largest Survey of Antidepressants Finds High Rates of Adverse Emotional and Interpersonal Effects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article presents the results of a survey conducted in New Zealand and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy-journal.com/article/S0165-1781%2814%2900083-3/abstract&#34;&gt;published online&lt;/a&gt; in February, 2014 in Psychiatry Research.  The survey involved 1,827 individuals who were taking antidepressants.  Dr. Read is widely published. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressant Drugs and Suicide Rates</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-drugs-and-suicide-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-drugs-and-suicide-rates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2010, Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica published a study by Göran Isacsson et al.  The paper was titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20384599&#34;&gt;Antidepressant medication prevents suicide in depression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Here&#39;s the conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The finding that in-patient care for depression did not increase the probability of the detection of antidepressants in suicides is difficult to explain other than by the assumption that a substantial number of depressed individuals were saved from suicide by postdischarge treatment with antidepressant medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurring Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/recurring-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/recurring-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft wp-image-1519 size-full&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I am 46 years old and have taken antidepressants (Lexapro, Paxil, now Zoloft) for 10 years.  But the reason I began taking them wasn&amp;rsquo;t due to my own need for relief from depression or anxiety.  It was actually an effort to improve my relationship with my husband at the time.  He suffered from depression and took medication, but said that I was overly critical, driven, intense, etc. and I think he was right.  But I was also young and immature, and am an engineer by profession.  I do have a critical thought process, no doubt.  We were mismatched from the start and separated not long after I started the medication, but have a 11 year old son together.  The divorce process, and going back to work full time as a single mom was difficult and stressful.  But after taking the Lexapro for over 4 years, I actaully began feeling lethargic and depressed and decided to stop taking it cold turkey.  Big mistake, I learned the hard way, and ended up on Paxil after a few months. Now I am having the same problem with the Paxil, and I really just want to get off the medication all together because I feel that it is causing the depression.  I was never depressed to begin with, but now I am!  After a couple of bad experiences with withdrawal symptoms from coming off the meds, I am really apprehensive about trying to taper off of them, but I want myself back, not this medicated, lethargic, irritable, unproductive person.  I was far from perfect, as my ex-husband made painfully clear, but I always had hope for a better future and energy to work for it.  I can&amp;rsquo;t help but feel that the meds have done more harm than good in my particular situation.  I just wonder if others have had similar experiences?  Thank you and best wishes in whatever you are searching for&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting the Placebo Effect:  Legitimate Practice or Chicanery?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/exploiting-the-placebo-effect-legitimate-practice-or-chicanery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/exploiting-the-placebo-effect-legitimate-practice-or-chicanery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 13, 2014, Psychiatric Times published an article by Steve Balt, MD.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/psychopharmacology/assessing-and-enhancing-effectiveness-antidepressants&#34;&gt;Assessing and Enhancing the Effectiveness of Antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; and is a good deal more candid as to the efficacy of antidepressants than one normally encounters from psychiatry.  Dr. Balt is a private practice psychiatrist in California.  He is the editor-in-chief of The Carlat Psychiatry Report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article opens with the observation that despite the large number of antidepressants on the market, and decades of clinical experience, no particular product seems to have emerged as substantially better than the rest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressant-induced Mania</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-induced-mania/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-induced-mania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is generally recognized in antipsychiatry circles that antidepressant drugs induce manic or hypomanic episodes in some of the individuals who take them.  Psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s usual response to this is to assert that the individual must have had an underlying latent bipolar disorder that has &amp;ldquo;emerged&amp;rdquo; in response to the improvement in mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with such a notion is that it is fundamentally unverifiable.  Psychiatry defines &amp;ldquo;bipolar disorder&amp;rdquo; by the presence of certain behaviors and feelings.  If a person meets these criteria, he/she is said to &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; bipolar disorder.  What immediately needs to be noted is that bipolar disorder, in common with psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s other &amp;ldquo;disorders&amp;rdquo; has no explanatory value.  To illustrate this, consider the following hypothetical conversation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murderers and Psychiatric Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murderers-and-psychiatric-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 05:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murderers-and-psychiatric-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the current issue of the National Psychologist written by David Kirschner, PhD, a New York psychologist.  The National Psychologist is a newspaper-type magazine that publishes articles of general interest to psychologists and others working in this field.  Most issues contain a mix of opinion pieces, news, changes in government regulations, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kirschner&amp;rsquo;s article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nationalpsychologist.com/2014/09/mass-shooters-received-only-limited-treatment/102638.html&#34;&gt;Mass shooters received only limited treatment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Bogus Conclusions From More Bogus Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-bogus-conclusions-from-more-bogus-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-bogus-conclusions-from-more-bogus-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robert Findling, MD, is a pediatrician and a psychiatrist.  He is the Director of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry at Johns Hopkins Children&amp;rsquo;s Center, and Vice President of Psychiatric Services and Research at the Kennedy Krieger Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 31, Dr. Findling published a brief video (and article) on Medscape:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/828984&#34;&gt;Adverse Events Caused by a Drug Warning?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Findling&amp;rsquo;s article is essentially a commentary on a study by Christine Lu et al, which was published by the BMJ on June 18.  Here is the conclusion paragraph from the Lu et al report:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants and Overall Wellbeing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-overall-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-overall-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting article published on April 12, 2014 in Psychotherapy and Psychosomatics.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24732909&#34;&gt;The Efficacy of Antidepressants on Overall Well-Being and Self-Reported Depression Symptom Severity in Youth: A Meta-Analysis&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by Gary Spielmans and Katherine Gerwig, both of the Psychology Department, Metropolitan State University, St. Paul, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors conducted a word-search in Medline, PsychINFO, and the Cochrane Central Register, and identified 8 studies that met their criteria.  They combined the data from these studies and concluded:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suicidal Behavior After FDA Warnings</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicidal-behavior-after-fda-warnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 05:45:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicidal-behavior-after-fda-warnings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 18, the British Medical Journal published an article by Christine Lu et al, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmj.com/content/348/bmj.g3596&#34;&gt;Changes in antidepressant use by young people and suicidal behavior after FDA warnings and media coverage: quasi-experimental study&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the conclusion paragraph from the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Safety warnings about antidepressants and widespread media coverage decreased antidepressant use, and there were simultaneous increases in suicide attempts among young people. It is essential to monitor and reduce possible unintended consequences of FDA warnings and media reporting.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Client&#39;s Perspective on &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-client-s-perspective-on-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2014 08:50:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-client-s-perspective-on-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A very important and compelling article was posted on Mad in America on June 18.  It&amp;rsquo;s by Andrew L. Yoder, and is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/06/open-letter-persons-self-identifying-mentally-ill/&#34;&gt;An Open Letter to Persons Self-Identifying as Mentally Ill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;My physician was not so cautious.  He was a very pleasant man that always seemed to take his time with me and did not talk down to me.  Yet as I described some of the emotional distress I was experiencing, and the ways it was affecting my life, he told me with great certainty that mine was a totally common experience.  He told me that I had a biological condition in my brain, one in which certain chemicals were &#39;imbalanced.&#39;  He told me that there should be no stigma about asking for assistance from him.  Specifically he told me, &#39;Trying to not be depressed is like telling a diabetic to just make more insulin.&#39;  He prescribed an antidepressant medication, saying that this was no different than taking medication to regulate blood pressure or manage cholesterol.  I was told of the likelihood that I would need to remain on some form of medication for an indefinite future.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Underestimate the Benefits of Antidepressants?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 05:58:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 19, 2014, The Lancet published an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants.pdf&#34;&gt;Do we underestimate the benefits of antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by German psychiatrists Mazda Adli and Ulrich Hegerl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lancet, founded in 1823, is a weekly, general medical journal which since 1991 has been owned by Elsevier, a private, Amsterdam-based, publishing house with offices in the UK, USA, and other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article can be gathered from the opening paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression vs. Normal Unhappiness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-vs-normal-unhappiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 05:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-vs-normal-unhappiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alex Langford is a British trainee psychiatrist.  He blogs at The Psychiatric SHO, and on April 21, he posted an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychiatrysho.wordpress.com/2014/04/21/antidepressants-are-not-happy-pills/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antidepressants are not &amp;lsquo;happy pills.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeandavisonwriter.wordpress.com/2014/04/26/more-support-and-understanding-needed-for-people-wanting-to-try-a-no-meds-approach/&#34;&gt;Jean Davison&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is an impassioned attack on psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s critics.  Here are some quotes, with my responses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I am sick and tired of the way the press portrays depression as unhappiness and antidepressants as ‘happy pills’.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This is interesting, though my general impression is that the mainstream media lean a good deal more towards psychiatry than towards our side of the debate.  In addition, the words &#34;depression&#34; and unhappiness are pretty much synonymous.  So it&#39;s difficult to see why that, or the characterization of antidepressants as &#34;happy pills,&#34; should be so upsetting to Dr. Langford.  We all, of course, have our linguistic likes and dislikes.  I personally don&#39;t care much for the growing trend to pronounce the indefinite article as &#34;ay,&#34; or for psychiatry&#39;s insistence on calling neuroleptic drugs &#34;anti-psychotics.&#34;  But what can you do?  I just Googled the phrase &#34;antidepressants are happy pills&#34; and got 204,000 hits!  So the notion has some traction and is probably here to stay.  One can&#39;t legislate for the way people use words.  Or perhaps psychiatrists imagine that they can.
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;For problems in other areas of health we’d only trust the experts to comment, but when it comes to mental health it seems like anyone can cast judgement.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants Make Things Worse in the Long Term</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-make-things-worse-in-the-long-term/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 05:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-make-things-worse-in-the-long-term/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In June 2011, Rif El-Mallakh, MD, et al. published an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toxicpsychiatry.com/storage/antidep%20El-Mallakh-tardivedysphoriadarticle1.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tardive dysphoria:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The role of long term antidepressant use in inducing chronic depression&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in Medical Hypotheses.  The article is a thorough and wide-ranging study review.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Here are some quotes from the abstract:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;Treatment-resistant and chronic depression appear to be increasing.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;Depressed patients who ultimately become treatment resistant frequently have had a positive initial response to antidepressants and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;invariably&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; have received these agents for prolonged time periods at high doses.&#34; [Emphasis added]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRIs and Persistent Pulmonary Hypertension of the Newborn (PPHN)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssris-and-persistent-pulmonary-hypertension-of-the-newborn-pphn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 05:45:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssris-and-persistent-pulmonary-hypertension-of-the-newborn-pphn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new study in the January 2014 issue of the BMJ:  Grigoriadis et al, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmj.com/highwire/filestream/682037/field_highwire_article_pdf/0/bmj.f6932&#34;&gt;Prenatal exposure to antidepressants and persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn: systematic review and meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Thanks to Nanu Grewal for the link.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PPHN is a relatively rare condition.  The authors report that the estimated prevalence is about 1.9 per 1000 live births.  The disease is essentially a failure of the newborn&amp;rsquo;s circulatory system to switch from oxygen supply via the placental blood, to oxygen supply via the baby&amp;rsquo;s own lungs.  The condition is usually diagnosed at birth or shortly thereafter.  Symptoms include:  rapid and difficult breathing, fast heart rate, and blue skin color.  PPHN is a serious condition.  A 2010 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2843001/&#34;&gt;article by Robin Steinhorn, MD&lt;/a&gt;, states:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants and Suicide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-suicide/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 05:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-suicide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There was an interesting article, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cphpost.dk/news/antidepressant-regulations-tightened-following-suicide.8243.html&#34;&gt;Antidepressant regulations tightened following suicide&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; in the Copenhagen Post on January 7.  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/01/denmark-hold-psychiatrist-responsible-suicide-restrict-antidepressants/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; for the link. It is reported that Danilo Terrida, aged 20, committed suicide in 2011 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;…eleven days after he was prescribed antidepressants following an eight-minute-long conversation with a doctor.&#34;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The doctor has been deemed responsible for the suicide by the National Agency for Patients&#39; Rights and Complaints.  According to its website:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The National Agency for Patients&#39; Rights and Complaints functions as a single point of access for patients who wish to complain about the professional treatment in the Danish health service.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants and Liver Failure</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-liver-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 05:46:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-and-liver-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Last month (December 2013) the American Journal of Psychiatry published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=1795083&amp;amp;resultClick=1&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Antidepressant-Induced Liver Injury: A Review for Clinicians&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, by Voican C.S. et al.  The study was a literature search from 1965 onwards.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the authors&amp;rsquo; results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;All antidepressants can induce hepatotoxicity, especially in elderly patients and those taking more than one drug&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Liver damage is generally unpredictable and unrelated to dose&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Liver damage can occur within a few days of initiation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Antidepressant-induced liver failure can be life threatening&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Antidepressants with &lt;i&gt;higher&lt;/i&gt; risk for liver failure include: iproniazid, nefazodone, phenelzine, imipramine, amitriptyline, duloxetine, bupropion, trazodone, tianeptine, and agomelatine&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Antidepressants with &lt;i&gt;lower&lt;/i&gt; risk: citalopram, escitalopram, paroxetine, and fluvoxamine&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Although an infrequent event, antidepressant-induced liver injury may be irreversible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sandy Hook Massacre:  The Unanswered Question</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sandy-hook-massacre-the-unanswered-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 05:50:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sandy-hook-massacre-the-unanswered-question/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On December 27, 2013, Connecticut State Police issued a 7,000-page, heavily redacted, report on the massacre that occurred at Sandy Hook Elementary School just over a year earlier (December 14, 2012).  For the record, I have &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;not&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; read the 7,000-page report, but I have read the Wikipedia article &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook_Elementary_School_shooting&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Sandy Hook Elementary School shooting&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, last updated January 4, 2013, and several media reports on the matter, including reports from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/28/nyregion/with-release-of-final-sandy-hook-shooting-report-investigation-is-said-to-be-over.html?hpw&amp;amp;rref=nyregion&amp;amp;_r=0&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.courant.com/2013-12-28/news/hc-lanza-sandy-hook-report1228-20131227_1_peter-lanza-adam-lanza-nancy-lanza&#34;&gt;Hartford Courant&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/police-file-to-be-released-on-newtown-shooting/2013/12/27/36612944-6ec5-11e3-a5d0-6f31cd74f760_story.html&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causes of High Mortality in People Labeled &#39;Mentally Ill&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 06:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ANOTHER VIDEO FROM DR. LIEBERMAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, made another video.  This one is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/813056&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;An Important Look at Mortality in Mental Illness: A Decade of Data on Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was made for Medscape.  You can see the transcript at the same site.  Medscape is a web resource for medical practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s commentary on an article that appeared in JAMA Psychiatry online on August 28:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1733743&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Comparative Mortality Risk in Adult Patients With Schizophrenia, Depression, Bipolar Disorder, Anxiety Disorders, and Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Participating in Psychopharmacology Clinical Trials&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Arif Khan, MD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dangers of SSRI&#39;s</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 06:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SSRI&amp;rsquo;S AND SUICIDE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Fiddaman has a post up today called &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.com/2013/11/mhra-consultant-calls-for.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;MHRA Consultant Calls for Antidepressant Use in Young&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The article highlights some of the dangers associated with SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, and also describes some of the attempts to suppress or discount the significance of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2010, Swedish psychiatrist Göran Isacsson, MD, PhD, published a paper in Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica.  The piece was titled &lt;i&gt;Antidepressant medication prevents suicide in depression,&lt;/i&gt; and reported that of a group of 1,077 depressed people who had committed suicide, only 15.2% had measurable amounts of antidepressants in the blood stream at the time of the suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Corruption of Healthcare</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-corruption-of-healthcare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 09:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-corruption-of-healthcare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading another great book:  &lt;i&gt;Deadly Medicines and Organised Crime: How big pharma has corrupted healthcare&lt;/i&gt;, by Peter C. Gotzsche [Radcliffe Publishing, 2013].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is an exposé of pharma&amp;rsquo;s fraudulent research and marketing.  The author is a Danish physician who has been involved in clinical trials of drugs, and in drug regulatory matters.  He is a professor at the University of Copenhagen.  He has published more than 50 papers, including papers in the BMJ, Lancet, JAMA, Annals of Internal Medicine, and the New England Journal of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants Being Handed Out Like Candy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-being-handed-out-like-candy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 05:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressants-being-handed-out-like-candy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting exposé in the London Daily Mail, September 29, titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/femail/article-2437657/Happy-pills-Critics-claim-antidepressants-handed-like-sweets-Now-shocking-experiment-uncovers--The-proof-doctors-doling-happy-pills-asks.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Critics claim antidepressants are being handed out like sweets…&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/leoniefen&#34;&gt;Leonie&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AntiDepAware&#34;&gt;Antidepaware&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out how easily people could get prescriptions for antidepressants, the Mail sent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…three women of differing ages — all of whom had no current mental health issues — to their doctors, reporting fictional symptoms of mild depression which had lasted for three to six weeks.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Antidepressant Use Increase the Risk for Type 2 Diabetes?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/does-antidepressant-use-increase-the-risk-for-type-2-diabetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 06:06:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/does-antidepressant-use-increase-the-risk-for-type-2-diabetes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 25, PsychCentral ran an &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychcentral.com/news/2013/09/25/do-antidepressants-increase-risk-of-diabetes/59914.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.  The article was a commentary on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/36/10/3337&#34;&gt;2013 meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Katharine Barnard, PhD, et al of the University of Southamptom, UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meta-analysis examined three systemic reviews and 22 studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESULTS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;There was evidence that antidepressant use is associated with type 2 diabetes. Causality is not established, but rather, the picture is confused, with some antidepressants linked to worsening glucose control, particularly with higher doses and longer duration, others linked with improved control, and yet more with mixed results. The more recent, larger studies, however, suggest a modest effect.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Spin on the Navy Yard Murders</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 05:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has written a guest post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.everydayhealth.com/columns/health-answers/in-the-wake-of-the-navy-yard-shooting-a-way-forward/&#34;&gt;In the Wake of the Navy Yard Shooting: A Way Forward&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;on EverydayHealth.  Everyday Health Inc. is a media company which operates for-profit websites on health and related matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been confirmed that the Navy Yard shooter had been taking trazadone, an antidepressant of the serotonin antagonist and reuptake inhibitor (SARI) class, and the House Committee on Veterans&amp;rsquo; Affairs has indicated that it &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenewamerican.com/usnews/crime/item/16595-did-psychiatric-meds-cause-navy-yard-tragedy&#34;&gt;plans to investigate&lt;/a&gt; to what extent the drug might have been a causative factor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More SSRI Side Effects: Upper GI Bleeding</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-ssri-side-effects-upper-gi-bleeding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 07:31:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-ssri-side-effects-upper-gi-bleeding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, the American Journal of Psychiatry published an article by Yen-Po Wang, M.D., et al, titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=1738031&#34;&gt;Short-Term Use of Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors and Risk of Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  [Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/09/short-term-ssri-use-associated-gastrointestinal-bleeding/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; for the link]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research was conducted in Taiwan.  The authors studied the records of 5,377 psychiatric inpatients with gastrointestinal bleeding between 1998 and 2009.  Study subjects served as their own controls, i.e. the incidence of bleeding in the period following the antidepressant prescription was compared with the incidence of bleeding during a period when they were not taking antidepressants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tide Has Turned</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-tide-has-turned/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 05:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-tide-has-turned/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Those of us on this side of the psychiatric debate have long maintained that there is a link between the so-called antidepressant drugs and the mass murders that have become an increasingly common feature of American society in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call for a formal investigation of this link, however, has been consistently resisted, and instead there has been a well-orchestrated medical campaign clamoring for more mental health services and more active outreach and prevention services.  As an example, see Jeffrey Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s guest post on Everyday Health, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.everydayhealth.com/columns/health-answers/in-the-wake-of-the-navy-yard-shooting-a-way-forward/&#34;&gt;In the Wake of the Navy Yard Shooting: A Way Forward&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Suicide Prevention:  A 30-year Failed Experiment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-suicide-prevention-a-30-year-failed-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2013 06:38:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-suicide-prevention-a-30-year-failed-experiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Mad in America dated September 17, 2013.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/09/nz-psychiatrist-psychiatrys-medical-model-suicide-prevention-30-year-failed-experiment/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry &amp;amp; Suicide Prevention: A 30-year Failed Experiment&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Maria Bradshaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria Bradshaw is the founder of CASPER, an organization that rejects the medical model of suicide prevention in favor of a sociological model.  Ms. Bradshaw founded CASPER after her son&amp;rsquo;s antidepressant-induced suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the gist of Ms. Bradshaw article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Mulder, MD, is head of psychiatry at Otago University in New Zealand.  For at least the last 15 years, he has supported the notion of psychiatric intervention as a suicide-prevention measure.  For instance, here&amp;rsquo;s something he wrote in 2008 in an article published in &lt;a href=&#34;http://lefnet.hu/resources/userfiles/file/Rihmer/Mulder%20APS%2008,%20suic%20during%20AD.pdf&#34;&gt;Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressant-induced Seizures in Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-induced-seizures-in-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 05:38:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-induced-seizures-in-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article in the current issue of Clinical Toxicology, titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://informahealthcare.com/doi/abs/10.3109/15563650.2013.829233&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Drug-induced seizures in children and adolescents presenting for emergency care: Current and emerging trends&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, authored by Y. Finkelstein et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors conducted an observational study, on 37 sites, of all pediatric Emergency Room reports which included a chemical or drug-induced seizure and required a toxicology consultation between April 2010 and March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESULTS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Antidepressants were the most commonly identified agents ingested…&#34;(42%).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s Impair Learning.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-impair-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 06:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-impair-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience.  It&amp;rsquo;s called&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Learning-from-Negative-Feedback-SSRI.pdf&#34;&gt; Learning from Negative Feedback in Patients with Major Depressive Disorder is Attenuated by SSRI Antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers evaluated learning ability in three groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;medication-naïve individuals who met the criteria for Major Depressive Disorder&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;individuals who met the criteria for MDD and were receiving the SSRI paroxetine (Paxil)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&#34;healthy&#34; controls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
All subjects were given a learning task that allowed the researchers to distinguish learning from positive feedback versus learning from negative feedback
&lt;p&gt;The results were:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Mass Shooting: Link to SSRIs?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-mass-shooting-link-to-ssris/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 09:45:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-mass-shooting-link-to-ssris/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A mass murder occurred yesterday, September 16, at the U.S. Navy Yard in Washington D.C.  There are reports of at least 12 dead, and several wounded.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.yahoo.com/contract-worker-behind-navy-yard-shooting-rampage-111847531.html&#34;&gt;Early news stories&lt;/a&gt; describe the perpetrator as having &amp;ldquo;mental issues,&amp;rdquo; and it is reported that he &amp;ldquo;…had been &lt;strong&gt;treated since August by the Veterans Administration for his mental problems&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  It is likely that this &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; involved the prescription of psychiatric drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And still no government inquiry into the &lt;strong&gt;link between psycho-pharmaceutical products, especially SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, and acts of violence/suicide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s and Postpartum Hemorrhaging</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-postpartum-hemorrhaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 06:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-postpartum-hemorrhaging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting study in the British Medical Journal (August 2013).  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmj.com/content/347/bmj.f4877&#34;&gt;Use of antidepressants near delivery and risk of postpartum hemorrhage: cohort study of low income women in the United States&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and it was written by Kristin Palmsten et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study examined nationwide Medicaid data from 2000-2007, and followed 106,000 pregnant women aged 12-55 who had been given a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of a mood or anxiety disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The women were categorized into four mutually exclusive groups on the basis of information obtained from Medicaid&amp;rsquo;s pharmacy dispensing data.  The criterion for categorization was exposure to SRI&amp;rsquo;s or to Non-SRI&amp;rsquo;s and the groupings were:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another School Shooting: Unanswered Questions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-school-shooting-unanswered-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 07:05:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-school-shooting-unanswered-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week (August 21), a 20-year-old gunman entered a school in Atlanta, apparently intending to kill people, but was talked down by a school bookkeeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone knows, we&amp;rsquo;ve had a great many incidents of this sort in the past fifteen years, most of which ended more tragically than this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reporting of these incidents in the media often mentions the fact that the perpetrators of these murders had a history of &amp;ldquo;mental health problems.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FDA Goes Against Its Advisory Panel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/fda-goes-against-its-advisory-panel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 04:38:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/fda-goes-against-its-advisory-panel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The FDA recently approved paroxetine (which in higher doses is marketed as the antidepressant Paxil) as a nonhormonal treatment for hot flashes in menopausal women.  The drug will be marketed as Brisdelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a New York Times article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/29/business/fda-approves-a-drug-for-hot-flashes.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;F.D.A. Approves a Drug for Hot Flashes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;the approval was granted despite the fact that FDA&amp;rsquo;s own advisory committee voted 10 to 4 last March &lt;i&gt;against approval.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reported reason for the negative vote was that in clinical trials, &lt;strong&gt;Brisdelle proved only minimally effective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blaenau Gwent, Wales: One in Six on Antidepressants!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 05:33:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a Mail Online article about &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2351291/One-people-town-anti-depressants-Is-local-GPs-fear-benefits.html&#34;&gt;high numbers of antidepressant prescriptions in Blaenau Gwent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article is dated June 29, and was drawn to my attention by Nanu Grewal from Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is about a town in Wales where reportedly one sixth of the population is taking antidepressants.  That&amp;rsquo;s about 17%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So presumably all these people have brain disease.  Or perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s because the unemployment rate is double the national average.  That in itself is depressing, but to make matters even worse, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of depression can reportedly help a person qualify for additional government benefits – a strong temptation for people living below the poverty line.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Grieving Mother</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-grieving-mother/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2013 14:29:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-grieving-mother/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a must-read article on Leonie&amp;rsquo;s Blog: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/06/29/the-grieving-mother-is-at-it-again/&#34;&gt;The grieving mother is at it again!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie lost a son to suicide four years ago.  The suicide occurred 17 days after he started citalopram, an SSRI, marketed as Celexa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie heard a &amp;lsquo;science expert&amp;rsquo; on the radio this week attributing depression to low serotonin levels in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie asks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;How can these idiots keep spouting the ‘chemical imbalance’ rubbish? It is drug company propaganda at its best and has no scientific basis, no factually based evidence whatsoever to conclude that depression is anything other than a reaction to life itself.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s and Birth Defects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-birth-defects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 05:25:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-birth-defects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of Nanu Grewal in Australia, I&amp;rsquo;ve come across this interesting paper:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://anp.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/06/11/0004867413492219.abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Systematic meta-analysis of individual selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor medications and congenital malformations&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Nicholas Myles et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors note that there is some suggestion of a link between SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, as a group, and birth defects, but that the teratogenicity of individual members of this drug class have not been systematically compared by meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta-analysis is essentially a systematic review of previous studies and combining of the results of those that meet certain pre-determined criteria for research quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Akathisia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/akathisia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 05:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/akathisia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Melissa, a commenter on a recent post, asked if I would do a post on akathisia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Akathisia literally means inability to sit.  People with this problem typically pace for long periods, and if they do sit down, they continue to keep moving and shifting their position in the chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In severity it can range from a generalized sense of uneasiness or agitation, to severe discomfort and even pain.  The discomfort tends to be located in the legs, but can also occur in the hip and pelvic area.  In severe cases, the victims pace to the point of exhaustion, but even then sitting does not relieve the discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric Drugs and Suicide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-drugs-and-suicide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2013 14:25:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-drugs-and-suicide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yobluemama2&#34;&gt;yobluemama2&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, I&amp;rsquo;ve come across an interesting article.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/articles/081130JanneLarssonpsychiatricdrugssuicide.pdf&#34;&gt;Psychiatric Drugs and Suicide&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; by Janne Larsson, a reporter.  It&amp;rsquo;s posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/index.htm&#34;&gt;PsychRights.org&lt;/a&gt;, a law project for psychiatric rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article focuses on suicides committed in Sweden in 2006-2007, and the proportions of victims who had taken psychiatric drugs in the period prior to the suicide.  The study also covers data from autopsy reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information for the study was gathered under Sweden&amp;rsquo;s freedom of information act.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of the main findings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s: The Down Side</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-the-down-side/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2013 06:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-the-down-side/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;David Healy, MD, is a controversial figure.  On the one hand, he is a fierce and determined opponent of the escalating use of antidepressant drugs.  On the other hand, he is one of the world&amp;rsquo;s leading proponents of electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the latter reason, I&amp;rsquo;m somewhat hesitant to quote his work, but he writes good anti-antidepressant articles, and his points are usually well-researched and compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://davidhealy.org/prozac-and-ssris-twenty-fifth-anniversary/&#34;&gt;Prozac and SSRIs: Twenty-fifth Anniversary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; which Dr. Healy wrote in February of this year.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opposition to Psychiatric Drugs is Fuelled by Puritanism!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/opposition-to-psychiatric-drugs-is-fuelled-by-puritanism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 08:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/opposition-to-psychiatric-drugs-is-fuelled-by-puritanism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an article by Ronald Pies MD on PsychCentral.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychcentral.com/blog/archives/2011/09/13/are-the-puritans-behind-the-war-on-antidepressants/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Are the Puritans Behind the War on Antidepressants?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the opening paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;These are not good times for Prozac and its progeny. In the popular media, the use of antidepressants has been likened to swallowing &#39;expensive Tic-Tacs&#39;, while in professional journals, the effectiveness of these medications has been challenged, if not discounted. And even a casual Google search under the terms, “Antidepressants damage” turns up thousands of websites and articles claiming that these drugs cause brain damage, induce suicide, or lead to &#39;addiction.&#39; Yikes!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suicide and Antidepressants:  Psychiatry&#39;s Watergate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-and-antidepressants-psychiatry-s-watergate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 22:09:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-and-antidepressants-psychiatry-s-watergate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carl Elliot has an interesting post up about the possible link between the military&amp;rsquo;s increased use of psychotropic drugs and the concomitant increase in soldiers&amp;rsquo; suicide rates.   It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://loathingbioethics.blogspot.com/2013/05/note-to-new-york-times-reporters-read.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note to New York Times reporters: Read the New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Like many reporters before them, James Dao and Andrew Lehren, [NY Times reporters], report that suicides in the military have risen to record levels.  What they don&#39;t mention is the fact that prescriptions of psychotropic drugs, many of them with black box warnings for suicide, have also risen to record levels.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s During Pregnancy and APGAR Scores</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-during-pregnancy-and-apgar-scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 18:34:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-during-pregnancy-and-apgar-scores/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on this topic by Hans Jensen et al, in the February 21, 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  You can see an abstract &lt;a href=&#34;http://bjp.rcpsych.org/content/early/2013/02/11/bjp.bp.112.115931.abstract&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors conducted a register study on all pregnant women in Denmark from 1996 to 2006, linking data from the Medical Birth Register, the Psychiatric Central Register, and the National Prescription Database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They found that the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;… use of SSRIs during pregnancy increases the risk of a low Apgar score independently of maternal depression.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Antidepressant Risks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-antidepressant-risks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 15:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-antidepressant-risks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article in Science Daily (April 29, 2013) titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;i&gt;Antidepressants Linked with Increased Risks After Surgery&lt;/i&gt;,&amp;rdquo; which I found courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/04/130429164638.htm#.UX-m2v4zuaI.twitter&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  The article is a report of a study published in JAMA Internal Medicine.  You can see an abstract of the study &lt;a href=&#34;http://archinte.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1682366&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted by Andrew Auerbach MD et al, and involved examining the records of 530,416 patients who had undergone major surgery between January 2006 and December 2008 at 375 US hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suicide Risk with Antidepressants</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-risk-with-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 15:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/suicide-risk-with-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There has been a great deal of discussion on this topic in recent years.  Families of suicide victims tend to blame the pills; the pharma companies blame the depression for which the pills were prescribed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;rsquo;ve read and heard a good many reports from people who have taken the pills and shortly afterwards experienced fairly strong suicidal urges pretty much out of the blue.  The frequency and similarity of these accounts is – at the very least – cause for concern.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Prescription Drugs Associated with Reports of Violence Towards Others&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 12:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the title of a 2010 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0015337&#34;&gt;research report &lt;/a&gt;by Thomas J. Moore, Joseph Glenmullen, and Curt D. Furberg, published in PLOS One, an online peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of the study searched the FDA&amp;rsquo;s Adverse Event Reporting System from 2004 to September 2009, and flagged reports indicating violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They concluded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Acts of violence towards others are a genuine and serious adverse drug event associated with a relatively small group of drugs.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI’s and Suicide Risk for Adolescents</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-suicide-risk-for-adolescents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 10:50:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ssri-s-and-suicide-risk-for-adolescents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This issue has been debated for years, but was finally considered to have been put to rest by NIMH’s 2004 Treatment for Adolescents with Depression Study (TADS).  This study essentially “found” that fluoxetine (Prozac) was effective in treating depression and did not involve an increased risk of suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Whitaker’s most recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/mad-in-america/201202/the-real-suicide-data-the-tads-study-comes-light&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; points out that TADS actually found that adolescents treated with fluoxetine had a markedly higher risk for suicidal activity than those who received a placebo.  Robert also outlines the various statistical and methodological ploys that were used to conceal this finding and to sanitize the final report.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More about Antidepressants and Placebos</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-about-antidepressants-and-placebos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 10:39:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-about-antidepressants-and-placebos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The debate is over.  Antidepressants are only very marginally more effective than placebos.  And yet the “depression-is-an-illness” lobby continues to grasp for straws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiona Godlee, editor of the British Medical Journal, recently cited “evidence” of the efficacy of antidepressants.  For a &lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/2012/02/everybody-has-won-and-all-must-have.html&#34;&gt;critique&lt;/a&gt; of the Godlee article go to Duncan Double’s website “&lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Critical Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprise finding! - Antidepressants are only very marginally more effective than placebos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means in effect is that people are “curing” their own depression (gasp), and perhaps don’t really need the mental health practitioners (double gasp).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
