<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Myth of Mental Illness on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/myth-of-mental-illness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Myth of Mental Illness on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 05:30:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/myth-of-mental-illness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  A Destructive Psychiatric Hoax</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-psychiatric-hoax/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-psychiatric-hoax/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, Alan Schwarz, an investigative reporter for the New York Times, published his latest book:  &lt;em&gt;ADHD Nation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blurb on the jacket states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;More than 1 in 7 American children get diagnosed with ADHD—three times what experts have said is appropriate—meaning that millions of kids are misdiagnosed and taking medications such as Adderall or Concerta for a psychiatric condition they probably do not have.  The numbers rise every year.  And still, many experts and drug companies deny any cause for concern.  In fact, they say that adults and the rest of the world should embrace ADHD and that its medications will transform their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Saving Psychiatry From Itself?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 12, 2014, the eminent psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, participated in a panel discussion at the Mad In America film festival in Gothenburg, Sweden.  After the festival, he wrote an article – &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/finding-a-middle-ground-between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry_b_6010890.html&#34;&gt;Finding a Middle Ground Between Psychiatry and Anti-Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;– for the Huffington Post Blog, summarizing the positions he had discussed at the festival. The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/10/between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry-mad-in-america-opens-a-dialogue/&#34;&gt;re-published on MIA&lt;/a&gt; on October 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is ostensibly an attempt to find common ground between psychiatry and its critics, but the piece contains numerous distortions and omissions which I think need to be identified and discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances and the Spurious Medicalization of Everyday Problems</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-spurious-medicalization-of-everyday-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 05:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-spurious-medicalization-of-everyday-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 5, Allen Frances MD, published an article on the Huffington Post blog.  The title is &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/can-we-replace-misleading-terms-like-mental-illness-patient-schizophrenia_b_7000762.html&#34;&gt;Can We Replace Misleading Terms Like &amp;lsquo;Mental Illness,&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Patient,&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Schizophrenia&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting piece, and it raises some fundamental issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the article, interspersed with my comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Those of us who worked on DSM IV learned first-hand and painfully the limitations of the written word and how it can be tortured and twisted in damaging daily usage, especially when there is a profit to be had.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dehumanizing Aspect of DSM</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-dehumanizing-aspect-of-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2014 05:45:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-dehumanizing-aspect-of-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In January 2014, the journal Research on Social Work Practice published a special issue: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rsw.sagepub.com/content/24/1.toc&#34;&gt;A Critical Appraisal of the DSM-5: Social Work Perspectives&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  There were many excellent articles in this volume, some of which I have highlighted in earlier posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the very outstanding articles is &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rsw.sagepub.com/content/24/1/13.abstract&#34;&gt;The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders as a Major Form of Dehumanization in the Modern World&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by Eileen Gambrill, PhD, a graduate school Professor at the School of Social Welfare, University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Psychiatric &#39;Myth&#39; Debunking</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-psychiatric-myth-debunking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 05:30:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-psychiatric-myth-debunking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 15, I wrote a post called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/07/15/psychiatry-debunks-the-myths/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry Debunks the &amp;lsquo;Myths.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  In that article I focused on the myth-debunking of Cognitive Psychiatry of Chapel Hill, but in researching the topic for that post, I came across a psychiatry resident named Shan (no last name) who blogs on a website called E&lt;em&gt;xploratory Encephalotomy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to the name of the website, Dr. Shan explains on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://encephalotomy.com/about-the-blog/&#34;&gt;About the blog&lt;/a&gt; page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…&#39;exploratory encephalotomy&#39; implies opening up somebody’s brain in order to search for something.  To the best of my knowledge, it’s not a real medical procedure yet…&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Debunks the &#39;Myths&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-debunks-the-myths/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-debunks-the-myths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;Psychiatry has always had its share of critics, but in the past two decades these criticisms have increased in frequency and intensity.  Psychiatry&#39;s underlying concepts are being denounced as spurious to the point of inanity, and its practices are being accurately and forcefully exposed as destructive, disempowering, and stigmatizing.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychiatry has no rational or logical response to these criticisms.  Its leadership and its rank and file remain stubbornly blind to the arbitrariness and invalidity of its so-called diagnoses, the unquestioning adoption of which distorts their perceptions of people and their problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;ADHD&#39; and Dangerous Driving</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 05:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Laurence Jerome, a Canadian psychiatrist, and two colleagues wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/ADHD-and-Driving-Jerome-et-al-ccap15_3p105.pdf&#34;&gt;What We Know About ADHD and Driving Risk: A Literature Review, Meta-Analysis and Critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It was published in the Journal of the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry in August, 2006. The primary result of the meta-analysis was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Current data support the utility of stimulant medication in improving driving performance in younger ADHD drivers.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The study is lengthy and well-referenced, but in keeping with standard psychiatric practice, it conceptualizes and presents ADHD as a &#34;…common psychiatric disorder…&#34; with symptoms of &#34;…inattention, impulsiveness and hyperactivity…&#34;  In other words, they present ADHD as something that a person &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; rather than as something that a person &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; The problem with this approach is that it creates the impression that meaningful or significant correlations/effects have been found, where in fact all that has happened is an elucidation of the terms used.
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the authors refer to a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Fried%2C+R.%2C+Petty%2C+C.R.%2C+Surman%2C+C.B.%2C+Reimer%2C+B.%2C+Aleardi%2C+M.%2C+Martin%2C+J.M.+2006&#34;&gt;Fried et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2006) and state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Szasz Refuted:  I Don&#39;t Think So!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-szasz-refuted-i-don-t-think-so/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 05:58:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-szasz-refuted-i-don-t-think-so/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On February 28, Awais Aftab, MD, a psychiatrist working in Qatar, published an interesting article on Psychiatric Times.  The article, which is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/dsm-5-0/mental-illness-vs-brain-disorders-szasz-dsm-5&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Mental Illness vs Brain Disorders: From Szasz to DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, is an attempt to validate the concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and, in particular, claims to refute the position of the late Thomas Szasz, MD, that mental illness is a spurious concept.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The validity or otherwise of the concept of mental illness is fundamental to psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s claim to legitimacy, and for this reason, Dr. Aftab&amp;rsquo;s article deserves close scrutiny.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Human Behavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 05:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A couple of months ago I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/11/21/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/&#34;&gt;article concerning ECT&lt;/a&gt; which generated some controversy.  One of the issues that came up was the relationship between &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;biological &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;explanations of human activity and more global explanations, which, for want of a better term, I&amp;rsquo;ll call person-centered explanations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any human activity can be viewed from different levels of abstraction.  Suppose, for instance, that I am sitting in my living room reading a book.  Then I put the book down, stand up, and go outside.  If the question were to be asked:  why did he put the book down and go outside? A wide range of perspectives and answers are possible.  One could, for instance, focus on the fact that I am a biological organism, and one could develop a detailed and comprehensive flow sheet of every muscle movement, every heartbeat, every sensory input, neural impulse etc., that had occurred from the moment that I put the book down until I was standing outside.  Such an account might be more or less detailed.  There would, of course, be physical limitations on the amount of information of this sort that is attainable, but from a theoretical point of view, one could compile a detailed, complete, and accurate biological account of the actions in question.  And such an account would be a valid response to the question:  why did he put the book down and go outside.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Valid Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 05:58:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 23, I wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/23/dsm-5-dimensional-diagnoses-more-conflicts-of-interest/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  In the article I sketched out the role of David Kupfer, MD, in promoting the concept of dimensional assessment in DSM-5, and I speculated that at least part of his motivation in this regard might have stemmed from the fact that he is a major shareholder in a company that is developing a computerized assessment instrument.  I ended the piece with a general criticism of psychiatry:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness: A Man-made Monster</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 05:45:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-a-man-made-monster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3758&#34; alt=&#34;Nelson Mandela quote&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Nelson-Mandela-quote-300x210.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the above image online yesterday, at the site &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thethingswesay.com/&#34;&gt;The Things We Say&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental illness is also man-made.  It is the invention of psychiatry - their spurious medicalization of all significant problems of thinking, feeling, and/or behaving.  Its purpose is to legitimize the prescription of dangerous psychotropic drugs to as many people as possible.   &lt;strong&gt;It benefits psychiatrists and drug companies, but damages, stigmatizes, and disempowers its victims.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman and &#39;60 Minutes&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 23, Psychiatric News (the APA&amp;rsquo;s media outlet) ran an article titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=1762017&#34;&gt;‘60 Minutes’ Interviews APA President on Schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The article was written by Mark Moran, a Psychiatric News reporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece opens with a quote from Jeffrey Lieberman, MD (President of the APA):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;&#39;60 Minutes&#39; showed a genuine interest beyond simply producing what was expected to be a popular segment and indicated a desire to do follow-up reporting on psychosis and violence.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critique of Psychiatry&#39;s Medical Model</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 06:15:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read &lt;i&gt;De-Medicalizing Misery&lt;/i&gt; [palgrave macmillan, 2011].  It&amp;rsquo;s a comprehensive collection of articles, edited by Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon.  The table of contents provides a sense of the book&amp;rsquo;s scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Carving Nature at its Joints?  DSM and the Medicalization of Everyday Life&lt;/i&gt;, Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dualisms and the Myth of Mental Illness&lt;/i&gt;, Philip Thomas and Patrick Bracken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Making the World Go Away, and How Psychology and Psychiatry Benefit&lt;/i&gt;, Mary Boyle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cultural Diversity and Racism: An Historical Perspective&lt;/i&gt;, Suman Fernando&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Social Context of Paranoia&lt;/i&gt;, David J. Harper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;From Bad Character to BPD: The Medicalization of &#39;Personality Disorder&#39;&lt;/i&gt;, James Bourne&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Medicalizing Masculinity&lt;/i&gt;, Sami Timimi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Can Traumatic Events Traumatize People?  Trauma, Madness, and Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Lucy Johnstone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children Who Witness Violence at Home&lt;/i&gt;, Arlene Vetere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Discourses of Acceptance and Resistance:  Speaking Out about Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, Ewen Speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Personal &lt;/i&gt;is&lt;i&gt; The Political&lt;/i&gt;, Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&#39;I&#39;m Just, You Know, Joe Bloggs&#39;:  The Management of Parental Responsibility for First-episode Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Carlton Coulter and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Myth of the Antidepressant:  An Historical Analysis&lt;/i&gt;, Joanna Moncrieff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Antidepressants and the Placebo Response&lt;/i&gt;, Irving Kirsch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Why Were Doctors So Slow to Recognize Antidepressant Discontinuation Problems?&lt;/i&gt; Duncan Double&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Toxic Psychology&lt;/i&gt;, Craig Newnes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychotherapy:  Illusion with No Future?&lt;/i&gt; David Smail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Psychologization of Torture&lt;/i&gt;, Nimisha Patel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;What Is to Be Done? &lt;/i&gt;Joanna Moncrieff, Jacqui Dillon, and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Each author brings to the general topic his or her unique perspectives, and the result is persuasive and inspiring.
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from the final chapter:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Stigma Attached to &#39;Mental Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 06:30:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Monday, October 7, 2013, The Sun, a British tabloid newspaper ran the following headline:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/5183994/1200-killed-by-mental-patients-in-shock-10-year-toll.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1,200 Killed By Mental Patients.  Shock 10-year toll exposes care crisis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  It took up almost all of the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The headline precipitated a great deal of protest from politicians, advocacy groups, mental health professionals, and others.  The general points in most of these protests were that the headline was sensationalistic, misleading, and would serve to increase the stigma associated with &amp;ldquo;mental illness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Concept of Mental Illness:  Spurious or Valid?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 05:35:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 17, 2013, Peter Kinderman, PhD, Professor of Clinical Psychology at the University of Liverpool, wrote an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-20986796&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Grief and Anxiety are not mental illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 4, 2013, Steven Novella, MD, wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/dsm-v-mental-illness-vs-normal-behavior/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 20, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Novella&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, on September 17, Dr. Novella wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/more-on-mental-illness-denial-and-how-not-to-argue/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;More On Mental Illness Denial and How Not to Argue&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a critique of my critique.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jon Rappoport&#39;s Blog</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 05:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Jon Rappoport&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, please take a look.  Here are two quotes from his September 22 post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/2013/09/22/psychiatry-targets-college-students-for-destruction/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry targets college students for destruction&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The concept called &#39;mental disorder&#39; is a sales pitch backed up by extraordinary PR, money, academic gibberish, and government-granted official status.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;People need to wake up to the fact that the whole panoply of human suffering has been co-opted, taken over, redefined, re-translated into a lexicon of pseudoscience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Submitting Claims for Off-label Prescriptions to Medicaid May Constitute Fraud</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/submitting-claims-for-off-label-prescriptions-to-medicaid-may-constitute-fraud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 08:03:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/submitting-claims-for-off-label-prescriptions-to-medicaid-may-constitute-fraud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my view, one of the most destructive developments in psychiatry in recent years is the &lt;strong&gt;prescribing of neuroleptic drugs to children&lt;/strong&gt;.  Much of this prescribing is off-label, meaning that the prescribed use is not approved by the FDA.  Off-label drug prescribing is &lt;i&gt;legal&lt;/i&gt;, however.  Once the FDA has approved a drug for one purpose, a physician may prescribe it for &lt;i&gt;another &lt;/i&gt;purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;i&gt;under Medicaid rules&lt;/i&gt;, the physician is not permitted to bill Medicaid for writing this prescription unless the use of the drug in the specific circumstances is endorsed by any of the three pharmaceutical compendia approved by Congress for this purpose.  A physician who deliberately submits a bill to Medicaid and, thereby, effectively causes Medicaid to pay for, a prescription that is both off-label &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; unapproved by any of the compendia &lt;strong&gt;is open to a charge of Medicaid fraud&lt;/strong&gt;.  Medicaid, incidentally, is the US government&amp;rsquo;s health insurance system for poor people.  Eligibility is based on income.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Burden of Mental &#39;Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 09:51:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GrahamCLDavey&#34;&gt;Graham Davey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/socratext&#34;&gt;Richard Pemberton&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link to an interesting article in the August 29, 2013 issue of the Lancet.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/GBD-Mental-2010-from-Lancet.pdf&#34;&gt;Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Harvey A. Whiteford, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Burden of Disease survey is a systematic, scientific attempt to quantify the comparative magnitude of disease, injuries, and risk factors by age, sex, and geography over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Illness Theory Is Everywhere</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-illness-theory-is-everywhere/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 06:22:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-illness-theory-is-everywhere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, there was an interesting item in the Dear Abby column of our local newspaper.  Dear Abby is a general advice column written by Jeanne Phillips, and is widely read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter in question was written by &amp;ldquo;Sibling Standing By,&amp;rdquo; who described his/her 63 year old sister as someone who &amp;ldquo;…takes no responsibility for her health.&amp;rdquo; The sibling goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;She’s extremely overweight because she overeats and doesn’t exercise.  She complains every day that she feels &#39;terrible.&#39;  (I call it self-pitying whining.)&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman is Back</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 05:45:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FearLoathingBTX&#34;&gt;Carl Elliott via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s latest post on Psychiatric News. It&amp;rsquo;s called – believe it or not – &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1723795&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Time to Re-Engage With Pharma? &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;dated August 1, 2013.  And it&amp;rsquo;s classic Dr. Lieberman sleight of hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His opening statement, for instance, reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drug companies aren’t held in high esteem by the public these days.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This may or may not be true.  But note what he&#39;s done.  The issue here is the long-standing and corrupt relationship &lt;i&gt;between psychiatry and the manufacturers of drugs&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;But from his first sentence, Dr. Lieberman has taken psychiatry out of the equation.  He has also lumped the makers of legitimate medicines in with the makers of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Medical Model vs. Psychosocial/Behavioral Model</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/medical-model-vs-psychosocial-behavioral-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 05:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/medical-model-vs-psychosocial-behavioral-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously there are many points of contention between mainstream biological psychiatrists on the one hand, and those of us who condemn this system as spurious and destructive.  Much of what I&amp;rsquo;ve written on this website over the past four years has been an elucidation of these differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I would like to focus on just one of these differences:  &lt;i&gt;disempowerment&lt;/i&gt; of clients in the psychiatric system, and &lt;i&gt;empowerment&lt;/i&gt; within frameworks that are more psychosocial/behavioral in nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Is Back!  More Of The Same</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back-more-of-the-same/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 08:36:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back-more-of-the-same/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, thanks to a tweet from&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GingerBreggin&#34;&gt; Ginger Breggin&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Jeffrey Lieberman entitled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1715655&#34;&gt;Psychiatry: Nothing to Be Defensive About&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Dr. Lieberman is president of the APA, and has gone on record more than once as saying that all these dreadful criticisms of psychiatry are very unfair, and that psychiatrists are good guys who have the high moral ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, he&amp;rsquo;s back, and his current article is about on a par with previous efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agitation and Neuroleptics</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/agitation-and-neuroleptics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 06:12:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/agitation-and-neuroleptics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sandra Steingard, MD, is a practicing psychiatrist who from time to time posts articles on Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s Mad in America website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Steingard apparently prescribes psychotropic drugs in her practice, but she is by no means a pill-for-every-problem practitioner, and her articles are always interesting and thought-provoking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Steingard posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/07/a-paradox-revealed-again/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;A Paradox Revealed – Again&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Mad in America on July 7, 2013.  In this article she mentions the recent study by Lex Wunderink et al, which found that people being treated for first episode psychosis were doing a great deal better functionally after seven years if their neuroleptic drugs had been discontinued or reduced relatively early in the process, as compared to individuals who were retained on the drugs for two years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Intrinsically Flawed and Rotten</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter yesterday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobStamatakis&#34;&gt;Robert Stamatakis&lt;/a&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have to ask, I don&#39;t understand.  Do you work in the UK?  Your descriptions of psychiatry are nothing I recognize.  These descriptions of psychiatry are nothing like the practice I see on a daily basis.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
I am certainly a very outspoken critic of psychiatry, and in that regard Robert&#39;s question/challenge is a fair one, to which I will try to respond.
&lt;p&gt;My primary criticism of modern psychiatry – and indeed the criticism that underpins all the others – is that its fundamental concepts are spurious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry: The Science That Isn&#39;t</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-science-that-isn-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2013 13:37:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-science-that-isn-t/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very important article on Mad in America.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/07/does-nimh-follow-the-rules-of-science-a-startling-study-2/&#34;&gt;Does NIMH Follow the Rules of Science? A Startling Study&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;by Niall McLaren, MD, dated July 9, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. McLaren is an Australian psychiatrist who has relentlessly combed the literature for proof of the fundamental psychiatric claim – &amp;ldquo;…that a full understanding of the brain will give a full understanding of mental disorder, with no questions unanswered.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He found &lt;i&gt;nothing&lt;/i&gt; in the way of proof!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PTSD:  The Spurious Medicalization of Painful Memories</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 04:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read &lt;i&gt;Crazy Like Us: The Globalization of the American Psyche,&lt;/i&gt; by Ethan Watters (Free Press, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, the theme of which is that western countries, especially America, are &lt;strong&gt;exporting the medicalization of human problems to less developed regions of the world&lt;/strong&gt;.  The new &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; are being avidly promoted as if they had the same kind of reality as pneumonia or cancer, and are being foisted on vulnerable populations, with little regard for their impact on the cultures, ideas, sensitivities, and health of the recipients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blaenau Gwent, Wales: One in Six on Antidepressants!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 05:33:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a Mail Online article about &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2351291/One-people-town-anti-depressants-Is-local-GPs-fear-benefits.html&#34;&gt;high numbers of antidepressant prescriptions in Blaenau Gwent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article is dated June 29, and was drawn to my attention by Nanu Grewal from Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is about a town in Wales where reportedly one sixth of the population is taking antidepressants.  That&amp;rsquo;s about 17%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So presumably all these people have brain disease.  Or perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s because the unemployment rate is double the national average.  That in itself is depressing, but to make matters even worse, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of depression can reportedly help a person qualify for additional government benefits – a strong temptation for people living below the poverty line.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Grieving Mother</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-grieving-mother/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2013 14:29:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-grieving-mother/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a must-read article on Leonie&amp;rsquo;s Blog: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/06/29/the-grieving-mother-is-at-it-again/&#34;&gt;The grieving mother is at it again!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie lost a son to suicide four years ago.  The suicide occurred 17 days after he started citalopram, an SSRI, marketed as Celexa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie heard a &amp;lsquo;science expert&amp;rsquo; on the radio this week attributing depression to low serotonin levels in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonie asks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;How can these idiots keep spouting the ‘chemical imbalance’ rubbish? It is drug company propaganda at its best and has no scientific basis, no factually based evidence whatsoever to conclude that depression is anything other than a reaction to life itself.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Need for Social Change</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-need-for-social-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2013 14:23:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-need-for-social-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a recent post,&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://peterkinderman.blogspot.com/2013/06/the-role-of-psychologist-in-social.html&#34;&gt;The role of the psychologist in social change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, on Peter Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s blog that is well worth reading. Peter begins with Martin Luther King&amp;rsquo;s 1967 statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“…there are some things in our society, some things in our world, to which we … must always be maladjusted if we are to be people of good will.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
It is a fact that many, probably most, of the problems that bring people into the mental health system are rooted in poverty, victimization, discrimination and other negative life circumstances.
&lt;p&gt;Peter reminds us that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: How to Salvage a Shipwreck</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 05:48:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 was published on May 18, 2013, amidst great criticism.  The fundamental criticism was, and is, that the &lt;b&gt;problems listed in the manual are not &lt;i&gt;illnesses&lt;/i&gt; in any ordinary sense of the term&lt;/b&gt;.  Other critics focused on the pathologizing of normality, the expansion of the diagnostic net by the lowering of thresholds, and the lack of reliability of the so-called diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response from the psychiatric community has been mixed.  Some, probably most, psychiatrists are keeping their heads down, getting on with the business of selling pills, and hoping that the gravy train won&#39;t derail.  Others are busy at damage control&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Doesn&#39;t Get It</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 3-4 June, the Institute of Psychiatry in London hosted an international conference to mark the publication of DSM-5.  On June 10, Sir Simon Wessely, a department head at the Institute, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slam.nhs.uk/our-blog/brcu/dsm-5-at-the-iop&#34;&gt;DSM-5 at the IoP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The paper is a summary of the conference proceedings, and also, in many respects, a defense of DSM-5.  The article touches on many issues that are central to the current anti-psychiatry debate, and for this reason, I thought it might be helpful to take a close look at the piece.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What &lt;em&gt;Is&lt;/em&gt; Mental Illness?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 08:50:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently received the following question from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ambtax1&#34;&gt;Disparity&lt;/a&gt;, on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I&#39;m interested in all your posts, but they&#39;re always telling us what mental illness &#39;isn&#39;t.&#39;  Do you have many on what it &#39;is&#39;?&lt;/p&gt;
I referred him/her to the post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2012/06/01/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;There are No Mental Illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and received the following reply:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have read it a few times.  I largely agree with it.  But &#39;something&#39; happens to people.  Whatever the label.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
Questions of this sort arise fairly frequently, and I thought it might be helpful to write a post.
&lt;p&gt;WHAT HAPPENS TO PEOPLE?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Really Want to Expand Mental Health Services?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 08:02:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT&amp;rsquo;S SPEECH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 3, President Obama delivered a &lt;a href=&#34;http://m.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2013/06/03/remarks-president-national-conference-mental-health&#34;&gt;speech on the expansion of mental health services&lt;/a&gt;.  The occasion was the National Conference on Mental Health, which was held at the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The truth is,&#34; the President told us, &#34;in any given year, one in five adults experience a mental illness — one in five.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
In most human endeavors something is true only if it can be shown to be so.  In psychiatry and politics, however, a statement becomes true if it&#39;s repeated often enough.  For the past 60 years, the APA has been systematically expanding their diagnostic net until – surprise, surprise – it now envelops 20% of the population.  With the lowering of thresholds in DSM-5, we can be sure that this number will continue to rise, and whoever is President then will be able to tell us that one in &lt;i&gt;four&lt;/i&gt; of the population has a mental illness.  Gosh!
&lt;p&gt;Note also that the President uses the term &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;mental disorder.&amp;rdquo;  The APA use the latter term in their manual to make the concept somehow more acceptable.  But these &amp;ldquo;disorders&amp;rdquo; always morph into illnesses in application.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kinderman-Pies Debate</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 08:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 15, Peter Kinderman, PhD, of the University of Liverpool, posted an article on DxSummit.org.  It was called &lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/197&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;So…What Happens Next?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article was that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are conceptually spurious, unhelpful, and even hindersome in practice, and discourage practitioners from pursuing genuine explanations for the problems clients bring to their attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an excellent piece, and I did a short post in which I recommended it strongly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Abuse in Childhood Make You Crazy?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2013 09:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/can-abuse-in-childhood-make-you-crazy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A NEW PARADIGM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an interesting article by Jacqui Dillon, Lucy Johnstone and Eleanor Longden.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp; Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&#34; href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Trauma-Dissociation-Attachment-and-Neuroscience-Dillo-Johnstone-Longden.pdf&#34;&gt;Trauma, Dissociation, Attachment &amp;amp;Neuroscience: A new paradigm for understanding severe mental distress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article was published in the Journal of Critical Psychology, Counselling and Psychotherapy (Vol 12, No 3, September 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;A new and profoundly important paradigm for understanding overwhelming emotional pain has emerged over the last few years, with the potential to change the way we conceptualise human suffering across the whole spectrum of mental health difficulties. It is a strongly evidence-based synthesis of findings from trauma studies, attachment theory and neuroscience, which offers new hope for recovery. It also presents a powerful challenge to biomedical model psychiatry in that it is based on scientific evidence that substantiates and attests to what many individuals with first-hand experience of mental health problems have always known –– that the bad things that happen to you can drive you mad.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>George Albee, PhD (1921-2006)</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/george-albee-phd-1921-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2013 07:08:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/george-albee-phd-1921-2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The late George Albee, psychologist, never accepted the medical model of behavioral/emotional problems.  He fought tirelessly for years to insulate psychology from the encroaching medicalization of its subject matter, and he died in 2006 believing that his efforts had failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He authored more than 200 articles.  As early as the 50&amp;rsquo;s and 60&amp;rsquo;s, he argued that &lt;strong&gt;social factors such as racism, poverty, and child abuse were largely responsible for the conditions known as mental illness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 08:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 27, David Brooks, a New York Times columnist, wrote a piece on psychiatry called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/28/opinion/brooks-heroes-of-uncertainty.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Heroes of Uncertainty&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting and somewhat contradictory article.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As the handbook’s [DSM-5] many critics have noted, psychiatrists use terms like &#39;mental disorder&#39; and &#39;normal behavior,&#39; but there is no agreement on what these concepts mean.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;What psychiatrists call a disease is usually just a label for a group of symptoms.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Wellbeing Foundation</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-wellbeing-foundation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 05:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-wellbeing-foundation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tommymorrela&#34;&gt;Tommy Morrela&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, I&amp;rsquo;ve become aware of &lt;a href=&#34;http://wellbeingfoundation.com/&#34;&gt;The Wellbeing Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.  They are located in Ireland.  Here are some quotes from their &lt;a href=&#34;http://wellbeingfoundation.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;About Us&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;To call human suffering a disease, something pathological, is deluded. The biological model of psychological distress has no basis in science; it takes away from the equation between &#39;healer&#39;, sufferer and society the need for understanding, compassion, healing, prevention and social and political change. The medicalisation of problems of living has to stop. We have a collective duty of care to bring about the destruction of psychiatry in its present form.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Caretaker Personality Disorder: Another Fiction</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-caretaker-personality-disorder-another-fiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 05:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-caretaker-personality-disorder-another-fiction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article in the current (May/June) issue of The National Psychologist called &lt;i&gt;Compulsive pleasing is deceptive and dangerous&lt;/i&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Les Barbanell, EdD.  (The National Psychologist is a newspaper-type publication for psychologists.  It&amp;rsquo;s published in Ohio, in the US.  Some of their material is posted online, but this article is not.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is about &amp;ldquo;the Caretaker Personality Disorder (CPD),&amp;rdquo; which apparently Dr. Barbanell invented in 2006 and has been promoting since.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Victim of Psychiatry Speaks Out</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-victim-of-psychiatry-speaks-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 14:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-victim-of-psychiatry-speaks-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an October 2012 article by Ted Chabasinski.  It&amp;rsquo;s on Mad in America and it&amp;rsquo;s called:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/10/our-task-is-to-take-away-the-power-of-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Our Task Is to Take Away the Power of Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ted tells us that &lt;strong&gt;he was was subjected to electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; when he was six years old&lt;/strong&gt;.  You can see a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/author/tchabasinski/&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the October 2012 article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Those who benefit from the way things are now won’t give up their money and power without a huge fight.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood &#39;Mental Disorders&#39; According to the CDC</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 05:23:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 17, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a report titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/pdf/other/su6202.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental Health Surveillance Among Children – United States, 2005-2011&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The CDC is based in Atlanta, Georgia and is a part of the US Department of Health and Human Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CDC&amp;rsquo;s report runs to 40 pages, including tables and references.  It received a fair amount of media coverage, and will likely inform legislation and other government action for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM: The Big Lie</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-the-big-lie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2013 12:14:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-the-big-lie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very interesting article by Kyle Arnold on DxSummit.org.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/456&#34;&gt;DSM: Letting Go of the Big Lie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The lie is that we have succeeded in domesticating emotional suffering, that we have placed it in a grid with clear and familiar boundaries. The lie is that we know the line between mad and normal, and can tell you on which side of the fence you belong. The lie is that it is science, rather than ethics or social norms, that can tell us what kind of behavior is acceptable and what is not. The lie is that psychiatric treatment is objective medical treatment, as clear and direct as your medical doctor treating a broken wrist.  The lie is that by accepting a psychiatric label, you embark on the road to being cured. The lie is the provision of false hope at the price of a stigmatized identity.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Different Perspectives</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/different-perspectives/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 13:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/different-perspectives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 1, 2012, I wrote a post titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2012/06/01/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/&#34;&gt;There Are No Mental Illnesses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday a comment came in on this post.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;When my brother was thirty years old, he started to see objects, which was far away, like hawk. His &#34;mind&#34; wanted to understand it, so he started to think he became a cybrog. Doctor said: you are ill&#34;. When I saw strange things, I said to myself: &#34;Well, I see strange things&#34; that&#39;s all. And I&#39;m healthy...&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with DSM</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 08:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the NY Times Sunday review.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/12/opinion/sunday/why-the-fuss-over-the-dsm-5.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It was written by Sally Satel MD, a psychiatrist, currently a resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is called:  &amp;ldquo;Why the Fuss Over the DSM-5?&amp;rdquo;  Dr. Satel&amp;rsquo;s central point is that psychiatrists only treat &lt;i&gt;symptoms&lt;/i&gt; anyway and pay little attention to the DSM.  She expresses the belief that the manual&amp;rsquo;s diagnoses are &amp;ldquo;…passports to insurance coverage, the keys to special education and behavioral services in school and the tickets to disability benefits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – Embracing a Social Paradigm?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 07:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the May 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;The future of academic psychiatry may be social&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt;by Stefan Priebe, Tom Burns, and Tom K. J. Craig.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NSVo2eU9meHQtOUU/edit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The past 30 years have produced no discoveries leading to major changes in psychiatric practice. The rules regulating research and a dominant neurobiological paradigm may both have stifled creativity. Embracing a social paradigm could generate real progress and, simultaneously, make the profession more attractive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Distress Is Not An Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 06:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uilleannair&#34;&gt;Sam Thompson&lt;/a&gt; (University of Liverpool) posted the following tweet on April 27:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Can anyone point me to a good, succinct summary of the case for equating mental distress with illness?  (serious, non-sarcastic question)&lt;/p&gt;
On the face of it, this looks like a straightforward question, and one might think that a straightforward answer could be found.  But this is not the case, because ultimately it boils down to a matter of definition.  And psychiatry is a field where &lt;strong&gt;definitions are notoriously fuzzy&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;MENTAL DISORDER&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transforming Diagnosis:  The Thomas Insel Article</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 21:06:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 29, Thomas Insel, Director of NIMH, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;Transforming Diagnosis&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/2013/130429NIMHTransformingDiagnosis.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Insel is critical of DSM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;While DSM has been described as a &#39;Bible&#39; for the field, it is, at best, a dictionary, creating a set of labels and defining each.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The weakness is its lack of validity.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This has created quite a stir, in that it appears to support the position of those of us who have been criticizing the DSM on these kinds of grounds for decades.  It also suggests a fundamental rift between the NIMH and the APA, two groups who up till now had appeared to be joined at the hip.
&lt;p&gt;The article has generated a great deal of comment.  So far, there&amp;rsquo;s been nothing from the APA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and the Other Professions</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 09:33:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t have precise figures, but I would guess that psychiatrists constitute less than 5% of the professional staff in the mental health system  The other 95% are psychologists, counselors, social workers, case managers, behavior analysts, case aides, art therapists, occupational therapists, job coaches, etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these other professions have specialized training, both theoretical and practical, and it is reasonable to suppose that they bring to their jobs a &lt;strong&gt;wide range of conceptual orientations&lt;/strong&gt;, and an equally &lt;strong&gt;wide range of practical skills.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Website:  by Mick Bramham</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 09:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across &lt;i&gt;Thinking About Mental Health: Myths, treatment risks &amp;amp; alternatives.&lt;/i&gt;  You can find it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s written by Mick Bramham, from Dorset, England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/chemical-imbalances.html&#34;&gt;Depression: Serotonin Imbalance?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The whole idea of antidepressants supposedly correcting chemical imbalances has more to do with drug company marketing than evidence-based science.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Unfortunately, drug companies are known to exaggerate the benefits of their products and to play down the risks;&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internet Addiction: A Bad Habit, Not An Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 17:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSM-5 drafting committee considered including Internet addiction in the upcoming revision, but eventually backed off, at least for now.  Apparently they decided to put it in the category &amp;ldquo;requiring further study.&amp;rdquo;  So it&amp;rsquo;ll be in DSM-6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, people are being given the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; anyway – and of course, the &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AN ILLUSTRATIVE CASE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt; for sending me a link to a recent article in the UK&amp;rsquo;s MailOnline.  It was written by Rebecca Seales and Eleanor Harding.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2312429/Four-year-old-girl-Britains-youngest-iPad-ADDICT-Shocking-rise-children-hooked-using-smartphones-tablets.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Anxiety Disorder: Now Also for Adults</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of separation anxiety disorder has been around since DSM-III.  In DSM-IV it is defined as &amp;ldquo;…excessive anxiety concerning separation from the home or from those to whom the person is attached.&amp;rdquo;  (DSM-IV-TR p 121).  The APA&amp;rsquo;s prevalence estimate is 4%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is listed under the heading: &amp;ldquo;Other Disorders of Infancy, Childhood, or Adolescence.&amp;rdquo;  One of the criteria is that the problem must begin before age 18, and in practice the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; was generally confined to children under the age of 10 or so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Words to Shape Attitudes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-power-of-words-to-shape-attitudes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2013 14:40:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-power-of-words-to-shape-attitudes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/04/19/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/&#34;&gt;Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?&lt;/a&gt;  The post was based on a study by Drs. Harrow and Jobe in which they speculated that the high relapse rate of &amp;ldquo;schizophrenics&amp;rdquo; who stop taking their drugs may have more to do with drug &lt;i&gt;withdrawal&lt;/i&gt; than the supposed drug efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, at BeyondMeds, pointed out that these drugs should not be called tranquilizers because some of their effects (e.g. akathisia, tardive dyskinesia, etc.) are anything but tranquil.  And this, of course, is a good point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Inter-Rater Reliability is Low</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/the-dsm-5-field-trials-inter-rater-reliability-ratings-take-a-nose-dive/&#34;&gt;article by Jack Carney&lt;/a&gt;, DSW, on this topic on Mad in America.  Jack refers to the DSM-5 field trials published earlier this year in the American Journal of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inter-rater reliability is measured by a statistic called a kappa score.  A score of 1 means perfect inter-rater agreement; a score of 0 indicates zero agreement.  In psychosocial research a kappa score of 0.7 or above is generally considered good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Marketing Ploy: Promoting Mental Health Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 05:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Hersteltalent on Twitter, I came across this newspaper article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/03/12/mental-health-checkups/1981495/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Doctors Urge Mental Health Screenings with Physicals&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It appeared in USA Today, and was written by Jessica Contrera of the Lafayette, Indiana Journal and Courier.  Dateline March 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article, which is written for the general public, is that when you go in to your doctor for a check-up, you should ask for a mental evaluation as well.  The article reminds us that &amp;ldquo;25% of American adults suffer from some form of mental illness each year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Benzodiazepine Withdrawal</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzodiazepine-withdrawal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 09:03:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzodiazepine-withdrawal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/17/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/#.UUknoxyG0eU&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; on this topic, I mentioned that benzo withdrawal can be dangerous, but it&amp;rsquo;s been drawn to my attention, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, that perhaps I didn&amp;rsquo;t adequately stress &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; dangerous it can be in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you click &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/01/21/benzodetoxdangers/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, you can read Monica&amp;rsquo;s own account of her experience in a detox center in Florida.  It&amp;rsquo;s a thought-provoking article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because for many years benzos were dished out so liberally, there is still a &lt;strong&gt;mistaken perception that they are relatively safe and benign&lt;/strong&gt;, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Two Short Stories</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 08:25:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First story&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 70&amp;rsquo;s I worked in Grendon Prison in England.  The facility was run on the lines of a therapeutic community – lots of meetings, groups, etc&amp;hellip;  One of the prisoners – let&amp;rsquo;s call him William – was serving time for burglary.  He was about 24 years old, and during his intake interviews he told us that he was a member of a small quasi-religious sect who believed that doomsday was imminent and that they would be the chosen few.  He talked about these matters openly and with a good measure of passion, and after a few weeks the other prisoners were describing him as &amp;ldquo;crazy&amp;rdquo; and a &amp;ldquo;nutcase.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and the Law</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 14:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this website is that there are no mental illnesses, and that the widespread medicalization of ordinary human problems is spurious and destructive.  These concepts have been around for decades, but in the last four or five years have &amp;ldquo;taken off,&amp;rdquo; and are finding a good deal of acceptance among practitioners, academics, clients, and the general public.  Change is in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A matter that is sometimes overlooked, however, is that the &lt;strong&gt;concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and its &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; by psychiatrists and other professionals is deeply embedded in the legal system of most states and countries&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explanations:  Spurious and Valid</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/explanations-spurious-and-valid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 15:53:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/explanations-spurious-and-valid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the central themes on this website is that &lt;strong&gt;psychiatric diagnoses are spurious&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;have no explanatory value&lt;/strong&gt;.  This contention is central to my entire argument, and for this reason I thought it might be useful to discuss the matter in some detail.  Let&amp;rsquo;s start by examining what is meant by an explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost as soon as a child can talk, he begins to ask questions.  He asks why does it rain; why does grass grow; why is the sun hot; why is iron hard; why does wood float on water; why do cats eat mice; and so on. What the child is doing is trying to find meaning and system in the world which he sees and feels and tastes and hears and smells.  He is looking for explanations.  So, for instance, if a child were to ask:  &amp;ldquo;Why is iron hard?&amp;rdquo; a conscientious parent who had some scientific background might venture an explanation like this:  &amp;ldquo;Because the molecules in the iron are bound together in a way which prevents them from moving around too much.  By contrast, the molecules in soft substances, like water, are not bound as tightly, and so they move apart when you stick your finger in.  The molecules in the iron won&amp;rsquo;t move apart easily – you would have to hit them with a hammer and chisel to get them apart.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muddled Thinking and Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until just a few years ago, the spurious nature of mental illness received little or no attention either in professional circles or in the general media. There were a few of us &amp;ldquo;cranks&amp;rdquo; who poked away at the issue, but peer condemnation was usually swift and outspoken.  On one occasion I was called an &amp;ldquo;anti-science Nazi&amp;rdquo; for daring to suggest that the condition known as ADHD might have more to do with ineffective parental discipline than with brain chemistry.  We were voices in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Thoughts on Dr. Novella&#39;s Articles</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 09:55:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/#.USd7W6WG0eU&#34;&gt;Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;Mental Illness Denial Part I&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Novella makes the point that various parts of the brain enable us to do certain things, and that if we are doing these things dysfunctionally, or not well, or perhaps not at all, then clearly there is something wrong with that part of the brain.  The example he gives is the activity of paying attention – but I think this is provided as an example, and that Dr. Novella intended his comments to apply to the full range of problems embraced by the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – the Pseudoscience</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 15:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As most readers of this website are aware, there is a great deal of resistance to the soon-to-be-released DSM-5.  There is even a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/dsm-5-boycott-launched/&#34;&gt;Boycott DSM-5 Committee &lt;/a&gt;established by Jack Carney, and many people are suggesting that practitioners use the World Health Organization&amp;rsquo;s (WHO&amp;rsquo;s) International Classification of Diseases (ICD) instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the general context of this debate, I have come across an article by Philip Thomas, M.D. – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/pinball-wizards-and-the-doomed-project-of-psychiatric-diagnosis/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pinball Wizards and the Doomed Project of Psychiatric Diagnosis.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  Dr. Thomas points out that &amp;ldquo;…it’s hard to imagine that the criticisms raised about DSM-5 won’t also apply to the ICD.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 16:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Nick Stuart, a regular commenter on this website, drew my attention to Dr. Steven Novella.  Dr. Novella is a strong supporter of the standard psychiatric system, and routinely refers to those of us who challenge these concepts as &amp;ldquo;mental illness deniers.&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;(Mental Illness Denial Part I)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick referred me to some of Dr. Novella&amp;rsquo;s articles, and I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/01/27/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/#.USVHtKWG0eU&#34;&gt;brief response&lt;/a&gt;.  I have been giving these matters some thought, however, and I think the subject matter warrants more attention. This is because Dr. Novella does indeed marshal some compelling arguments in other areas, and also because he routinely condemns us &amp;ldquo;deniers&amp;rdquo; as illogical employers of &amp;ldquo;…semantic misdirection and evasion…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critic of the Illness Concept</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critic-of-the-illness-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 18:53:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critic-of-the-illness-concept/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across another DSM critic – or as Dr. Novella terms us – a mental illness denier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His name is Peter Kinderman, and he is head of the Institute of Psychology, Health and Society at the University of Liverpool.  He has recently written an article called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-20986796&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;i&gt;Grief and anxiety are not mental illnesses.&amp;quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;For a few of us, our experiences of abuse or failure lead us to feel that life is not worth living. We need to recognise these human truths and we need to offer help. But we should not regard these human experiences as symptoms of a mental illness.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Origins of &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-origins-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2013 12:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-origins-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I routinely state that there are no mental illnesses, but I also make it clear that the behaviors, habits, and problems which are &lt;i&gt;labeled&lt;/i&gt; as mental illnesses are very real and can be very disturbing to the individuals involved and to those around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My general position is that &lt;strong&gt;dysfunctional and counterproductive habits are acquired in exactly the same way as productive habits&lt;/strong&gt;.  For this reason, I emphasize the &lt;strong&gt;importance of childhood and adolescence as the time of life when many of our habits, stances, and orientations are being laid down.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Mental Illness&#34; and Genes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-and-genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 11:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-and-genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jay Joseph, PhD has posted an interesting piece: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/five-decades-of-gene-finding-failures-in-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Five Decades of Gene Finding Failures in Psychiatry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; (Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s site).  It is well worth a read.  The general content of the article is clear from the title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Two generations of molecular genetic researchers have attempted, yet failed, to discover the genes that they believe underlie the major psychiatric disorders.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite the sequencing of the human genome and the publication of more than 1,700 schizophrenia molecular genetic studies, we have witnessed over 40 years of gene finding claims, and over 40 years of subsequently non-replicated findings.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism of DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 10:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane, author of &lt;i&gt;Shyness: How Normal Behavior Became a Sickness,&lt;/i&gt; has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201302/dsm-5-has-gone-press-containing-major-scientific-gaffe&#34;&gt;new post&lt;/a&gt;, in which he attacks the APA for including somatic symptom disorder (SSD) in the upcoming DSM-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lane quotes from Allen Francis (former DSM guru who has now seen the light) and Suzy Chapman, a UK health advocate.  Both of these commentators attack the new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; as invalid, unreliable, and potentially over-inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mandatory Mental Health Screenings for Schoolchildren</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 19:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A regular commenter to this website has drawn my attention to a bill that has been proposed in the Connecticut state legislature.  The bill would require public school and homeschooled children to be assessed by mental health practitioners at grades 6, 8, 10, and 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bill, sponsored by Senator Toni Harp and Representative Toni Walker, is in response to the recent Sandy Hook murders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it starts.  Given the built-in vagueness of the DSM, and the inclusiveness bias of the mental health business, the outcome of these screenings (should the bill become law) is predictable: more and more parents disempowered with regards to their parenting responsibilities; more drugged children, and, tragically, more mass murders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Look at Critical Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2013 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.criticalpsychiatry.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Critical Psychiatry Network&lt;/a&gt; is a group of British psychiatrists who are developing and promoting concepts that question and criticize the assumptions that underlie present-day psychiatric practice, not only in Britain, but also in the US and other developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Psychiatry challenges the notion that the various DSM &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are biologically-based illnesses, and adduces a great deal of evidence to the contrary.  They stress the cultural/social aspect of psychiatric diagnosing.  For instance, they point out that a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of ADHD is a cultural construct which provides schools and parents with a socially acceptable method of dealing with difficult children (rather than an identification of an illness).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dangerous People</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dangerous-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 18:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dangerous-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Connecticut mass murders of last month, a great deal of attention, official and otherwise, is being focused on the “mentally ill.”  Politicians of all persuasions are proclaiming that we need more funding for the so-called mental health services, and predictably, the various practitioners and centers are lining up with their hands outstretched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spurious logic, of course, is never identified, or if it is, it gets lost in the rhetoric.  Mental illness is presented (and accepted) as the proximate cause of the violence.  If one were to ask a mental health practitioner why an individual was so crazy and acted so brutally, the reply would be:  Because he has a mental illness.  But if one were to press the matter and ask:  How do you know he has a mental illness? the only possible response is: Because he is so crazy and acted so brutally.  The only evidence for the so-called illness is the very behavior it purports to explain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 18:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late adolescence and early adulthood is arguably the most difficult period of life.  Transitioning from childhood to adulthood entails many challenges.  The young person (male or female) is expected to emancipate successfully from parents; launch a career; and find a partner – all in the space of a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some individuals cope remarkably well.  Others squeak through, and a small minority “crash and burn.”  The latter group usually return home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  More of the Same - Turf Expansion</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 19:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same---turf-expansion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until now, I’ve pretty much steered clear of DSM-5.  My reason for this is that the upcoming revision represents, to my mind, a distraction from the central issue, i.e., that the whole notion of mental illness is spurious, destructive nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position is that the purpose of DSM is to expand psychiatric turf and to legitimize the pushing of mood/behavior-altering pharmaceuticals. In the US (and I believe in most developed countries) you can’t prescribe a drug without a diagnosis.  And the APA has never neglected its primary mission in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviving the Myth of Mental Illness:  Another Interesting Article</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/reviving-the-myth-of-mental-illness-another-interesting-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 11:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/reviving-the-myth-of-mental-illness-another-interesting-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/07/reviving-the-myth-of-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reviving the Myth of Mental Illness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Morgan.  This article appeared in the Personal Stories section of Robert Whitaker’s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mad in America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and is well worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Thus, it is important to note that mental illness in itself – the idea that a mind is ill, is actually a categorical error, like saying the sky is ill or the color green is healthy. &#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Cracks in the Sandcastle: Anti-DSM Sentiment</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle-anti-dsm-sentiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 14:29:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cracks-in-the-sandcastle-anti-dsm-sentiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane recently wrote an article called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201209/anti-dsm-sentiment-rises-in-france&#34;&gt;Anti-DSM Sentiment Rises in France&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; “Anger and concern about the growing influence of the &lt;em&gt;DSM&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in France, as well as over a number of related, prominent pharmaceutical scandals here, has culminated in the creation of &lt;em&gt;Stop&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;DSM,&lt;/em&gt; a professional and political group that is strongly opposed to the manual’s diagnostic power and what it sees as its negative social consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The So-Called Mental Illnesses Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 19:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that mental illness is a spurious and invalid concept, which is promoted and developed by the American Psychiatric Association to legitimize the use of mood-altering drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that people display various problems in their daily lives and particularly in their interpersonal relationships.  The American Psychiatric Association claims that all such problems are caused by mental illness and their list of these so-called illnesses is so long that virtually anybody can be embraced within their coils.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
