<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Pharmaceutical Industry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/pharmaceutical-industry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pharmaceutical Industry on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 10:59:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/pharmaceutical-industry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>GPs Prescribe More Psychotropic Drugs than Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 10:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Psychiatrists, when challenged about the massive increase in psychotropic drug prescriptions, sometimes point out that the bulk of this prescribing is done – not by them – but by primary care doctors (GPs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; claim in this regards may be true, it is also somewhat misleading.  The &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; for which these drugs are being prescribed were &lt;i&gt;invented&lt;/i&gt; by psychiatrists, and &lt;strong&gt;it is these inventions that legitimize the prescribing activity&lt;/strong&gt;.  And, of course, as the psychiatrists invent more illnesses, the prescription rates increase proportionately.  Without the perceived legitimacy of the DSM, GPs simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t dish out antidepressants, anxiolytics, and stimulants on the scale seen today, if for no other reason than the fear of lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now – by Popular Demand – Ritalin for the Elderly!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 10:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the old days, which I well remember, misbehavior in school was considered a disciplinary problem.  This included not paying attention, fidgeting, not applying oneself to one&amp;rsquo;s work, talking, interrupting the teacher, etc., etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the APA decided that these various activities were really symptoms of a mental illness, and thereby created the ever-burgeoning market for Ritalin and other drugs which, we are falsely told, correct the &amp;ldquo;chemical imbalance&amp;rdquo; in these children&amp;rsquo;s brains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Psychotropic Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 10:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytransformation.blogspot.com/2011/04/fishing-lessons-from-my-son.html#.UWBNjZOG0eU&#34;&gt;nice article at Involuntary Transformation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Nathan, poses a very interesting question:  since drugs cause damage to children and there are many better alternatives, &lt;strong&gt;why do so many parents choose the drug option&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan goes on to suggest that the reason lies in the effort that the pharmaceutical industry invests in marketing, and he calls for &amp;ldquo;…complete and total transparency in all Mental Health Services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Conflicts of Interest in Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 11:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come across an article by Lisa Cosgrove et al entitled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jep.12016/abstract&#34;&gt;Conflicts of interest and the quality of recommendations in clinical guidelines.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;It was published in the Journal of &lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Evaluation in Clinical Practice in December of last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone knows, the APA publishes the DSM, but they also publish &amp;ldquo;Clinical Practice Guidelines&amp;rdquo; for various &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the condition known as major depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cosgrove and her colleagues examined the guidelines for major depression to see if the authors had financial or intellectual conflicts of interest.  An example of a financial conflict of interest would be recommending drug treatment when one is on the payroll of a drug company.  An example of an intellectual conflict of interest would be relying on and citing a poor quality study in support of a position in which one had a stake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma&#39;s Subtle but Pernicious Marketing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alice Keys, MD, has recently written a short article for Mad in America.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/he-who-pays-the-piper/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Keys points out that to maintain a medical license, one must accumulate continuing education credits, and that these credits have to be approved by state licensing boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that pharmaceutical companies have largely hijacked this process in recent decades, and that their &amp;ldquo;educational&amp;rdquo; presentations might be better described as infomercials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Marketing Ploy: Promoting Mental Health Evaluations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 05:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Hersteltalent on Twitter, I came across this newspaper article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/03/12/mental-health-checkups/1981495/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Doctors Urge Mental Health Screenings with Physicals&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It appeared in USA Today, and was written by Jessica Contrera of the Lafayette, Indiana Journal and Courier.  Dateline March 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article, which is written for the general public, is that when you go in to your doctor for a check-up, you should ask for a mental evaluation as well.  The article reminds us that &amp;ldquo;25% of American adults suffer from some form of mental illness each year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal from Benzodiazepines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Important updates on this subject can be found at the posts listed at the bottom of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I&#39;ve recently come across an article by Matt Samet called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/social-vacuum/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Social Vacuum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&#39;s dated March 2013, and was published on Robert Whitaker&#39;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Matt had been taking a benzodiazepine for some time, and while on a tapering withdrawal, he experienced some distressing symptoms, including some acute social discomfort.  (For a full account of benzo withdrawal –&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benzodiazepine_withdrawal_syndrome&#34;&gt; click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Pharma, by Ben Goldacre</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 23:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All the awful things you&amp;rsquo;ve heard and read about the pharmaceutical companies are documented on the pages of &lt;i&gt;Bad Pharma&lt;/i&gt; with compelling clarity and abundant references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Goldacre is a British physician.  His primary issue is the safety and efficacy of pharmaceutical products in general medicine, but he has a lot to say about psychiatric drugs also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs are tested by the people who manufacture them, in poorly designed trials, on hopelessly small numbers of weird, unrepresentative patients, and analysed using techniques which are flawed by design, in such a way that they exaggerate the benefits of treatments.&#34;(p. x)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma and Mental Health: Hand-in-Glove</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 19:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another interesting article:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/02/24/academic-integrity-in-ireland-and-the-uk-is-there-any-such-thing/&#34;&gt;Academic Integrity in Ireland and the UK: Is there any such thing?&lt;/a&gt; at Leonie fennells&amp;rsquo; Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about financial ties between pharmaceutical companies and psychiatrists.  Same old story; different location.  It&amp;rsquo;s worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Becky @yobluemama2 on Twitter for drawing my attention to this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fable for Our Times</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-fable-for-our-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 15:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-fable-for-our-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Several of my recent posts have been about fundamental issues. Here&#39;s something a little lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;On the coast of Maine near the Machias Estuary, the Atlantic Ocean pounds the cliffs and beaches.  The scenery is wild and beautiful, and there are lots of seagulls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One spring a seagull was born named Jimmy Brady.  He was a fine little seagull, but his brothers picked on him something terrible, and he grew up feeling nervous and very unsure of himself.  He thought he was ugly, and when it came time to jump off the cliff and fly, Jimmy just couldn’t do it.  He didn&amp;rsquo;t believe that a seagull, as horrible and klutzy as he believed himself to be, could ever soar over the waves as a seagull should.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Big Pharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 22:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have written frequently on this website about the hand-in-glove relationship between psychiatrists and the pharmaceutical companies.  It is my general position that the business-first orientation of the pharmaceutical companies, coupled with their willingness to pay large sums of money to co-operative psychiatrists, has been, and continues to be, a corrupting influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently come across two articles by Carl Elliot, MD, PhD. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/how-to-get-away-with-academic-misconduct-at-the-university-of-minnesota/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;How to Get Away with Academic Misconduct at the University of Minnesota,&amp;rdquo; &lt;/a&gt;and&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/and-thats-the-news-from-the-department-of-psychiatry-where-all-the-nurses-are-supportive-of-research-and-all-the-patients-are-reviewed-for-possible-research-candid/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;And That’s the News from the Department of Psychiatry.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mandatory Mental Health Screenings for Schoolchildren</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 19:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A regular commenter to this website has drawn my attention to a bill that has been proposed in the Connecticut state legislature.  The bill would require public school and homeschooled children to be assessed by mental health practitioners at grades 6, 8, 10, and 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bill, sponsored by Senator Toni Harp and Representative Toni Walker, is in response to the recent Sandy Hook murders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it starts.  Given the built-in vagueness of the DSM, and the inclusiveness bias of the mental health business, the outcome of these screenings (should the bill become law) is predictable: more and more parents disempowered with regards to their parenting responsibilities; more drugged children, and, tragically, more mass murders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold-blooded Killers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 14:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday our local newspaper ran an article called &amp;ldquo;Mental Health Needs Reform.&amp;rdquo;  It was written by a psychologist, and the main thrust of the piece was that if &amp;ldquo;serious mental health care reform&amp;rdquo; is not implemented, we will see more mass murders similar to those at Aurora and Newtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article contained several unwarranted assumptions, and recommended that mental hospitals &amp;ldquo;rebuild facilities for treating those patients.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position, of course, is that there are no mental illnesses, and that cold-blooded killers are not sick in any meaningful sense of the term, but are, rather, individuals who have not internalized an age-appropriate respect for the lives and welfare of other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dangerous People</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dangerous-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 18:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dangerous-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Connecticut mass murders of last month, a great deal of attention, official and otherwise, is being focused on the “mentally ill.”  Politicians of all persuasions are proclaiming that we need more funding for the so-called mental health services, and predictably, the various practitioners and centers are lining up with their hands outstretched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spurious logic, of course, is never identified, or if it is, it gets lost in the rhetoric.  Mental illness is presented (and accepted) as the proximate cause of the violence.  If one were to ask a mental health practitioner why an individual was so crazy and acted so brutally, the reply would be:  Because he has a mental illness.  But if one were to press the matter and ask:  How do you know he has a mental illness? the only possible response is: Because he is so crazy and acted so brutally.  The only evidence for the so-called illness is the very behavior it purports to explain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  More of the Same - Turf Expansion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same-turf-expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 19:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-more-of-the-same-turf-expansion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until now, I’ve pretty much steered clear of DSM-5.  My reason for this is that the upcoming revision represents, to my mind, a distraction from the central issue, i.e., that the whole notion of mental illness is spurious, destructive nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position is that the purpose of DSM is to expand psychiatric turf and to legitimize the pushing of mood/behavior-altering pharmaceuticals. In the US (and I believe in most developed countries) you can’t prescribe a drug without a diagnosis.  And the APA has never neglected its primary mission in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Psychiatrists, the Drug Reps, and the Green, Green, Dollars</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-psychiatrists-the-drug-reps-and-the-green-green-dollars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 10:26:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-psychiatrists-the-drug-reps-and-the-green-green-dollars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve known for years that drug companies give gifts to physicians.  The gifts have taken many forms – pens, vacations, meals, free samples, etc&amp;hellip;  Physicians always insisted that these gifts didn’t influence their prescribing practice – that they always prescribed strictly in the best interests of their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two trends have been exposed in recent years which demonstrate just how depraved this hand-in-glove relationship has become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the “thought leader” ruse.  Here’s how it works.  A drug rep, usually an attractive young, perfectly groomed female, approaches a physician, usually male, and tells the physician that he has been identified as a thought leader in his area, and that they would like to recruit him to give presentations to groups of physicians and other healthcare workers.  The physician, of course, will be paid generously for his time.  He says “sure,” and the dance begins.  The drug rep arranges the “training” sessions.  The drug company provides the script and the refreshments.  The mark – I mean the physician – delivers the script, in which the merits of the drug company’s product are lauded to the detriment of competitors.  At the end of the session, the physician receives a check and goes away contented.  Over the next few months more such sessions will be organized and the physician begins to think of his “speech” checks as regular income.  He will also receive “coaching” from the drug rep if his presentation seems to lack the kind of conviction that the drug company feels warranted.  (After all, they are paying the piper).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
