<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Anxiety on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/anxiety/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Anxiety on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/anxiety/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal from Benzodiazepines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Important updates on this subject can be found at the posts listed at the bottom of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I&#39;ve recently come across an article by Matt Samet called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/social-vacuum/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Social Vacuum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&#39;s dated March 2013, and was published on Robert Whitaker&#39;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Matt had been taking a benzodiazepine for some time, and while on a tapering withdrawal, he experienced some distressing symptoms, including some acute social discomfort.  (For a full account of benzo withdrawal –&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benzodiazepine_withdrawal_syndrome&#34;&gt; click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder Is Not An Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/obsessive-compulsive-disorder-is-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 13:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/obsessive-compulsive-disorder-is-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I was listening to NPR on the car radio.  The program was about so-called obsessive compulsive disorder, and a woman was describing her difficulty in this area.  I didn’t record her actual words, but it went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;I have all these checks and rituals that I have to do each day.  And it’s beginning to put a strain on my marriage.  Sometimes my husband wants to go somewhere but I can’t go until I finish my checks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Business As Usual</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/business-as-usual/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2011 15:44:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/business-as-usual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane, author of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2010/04/15/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/&#34;&gt;Shyness&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;has written an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201011/pharmaceutical-scandal-in-britain-sheds-disturbing-new-light-benzodiazepine&#34;&gt;interesting post&lt;/a&gt;.  The gist of the matter is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a class of drugs known as benzodiazepines (benzos for short) that are promoted by Pharma and prescribed by psychiatrists to “treat” anxiety.  (As if anxiety were an illness!)  See my post on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2009/05/07/anxiety-disorders/&#34;&gt;So-called Anxiety Disorders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benzos include such household names as Valium, Librium, Ativan, Xanax, etc..  When introduced in the 1960’s, these drugs were widely touted as “safe” tranquilizers.  Readers may remember Valium as “mother’s little helper,” so called because it was marketed to millions of harried housewives as they struggled to adapt to an increasingly complex and multi-faceted lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anxiety Disorders</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/anxiety-disorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2009 12:28:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/anxiety-disorders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fear is the &lt;em&gt;normal &lt;/em&gt;human response to imminent danger.  It is an adaptive response, in that it is helpful to survival, and it occurs in almost all animal species.  When our cave-dwelling ancestors were attacked by mountain lions, they probably experienced acute fear.  This fear gave them an extra burst of energy to flee the danger, or, if flight were impossible, to turn and fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today in most parts of the world, there is little danger of attack from wild animals.  As areas develop economically and culturally, these kinds of acute dangers are systematically eliminated or at least drastically reduced.  Close encounters with tornadoes, hurricanes, rattlesnakes, car accidents, etc., can still arouse full-blown fear responses, but most people in developed countries can go months – even years – without experiencing these kinds of situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
