<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Stimulants on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/stimulants/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stimulants on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 05:58:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/stimulants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Driving Under the Influence of Stimulants</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 05:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 22, I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/04/22/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on this general topic.  In that article I pointed out that the notion of stimulant prescription drugs improving the driving of people who &amp;ldquo;have ADHD&amp;rdquo; was gaining traction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since than I have come across two articles on this subject from Australia.  (Thanks to Nanu Grewal for the links.)  Both articles appeared in the Sunshine Coast Daily, and you can see them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/hospital-launches-complaints-probe/1122551/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/crackdowntoo-late-for-twins-slow-action-way-too-la/1960148/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2009, four people, including five-year-old twin girls, died in a two-car accident.  The driver of one of the cars had been prescribed dexamphetamine for the treatment of ADHD by a local psychiatrist, and was found to have had six times the prescribed dosage of dexamphetamine in his system at the time of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sandcastle Continues to Crumble:  ADHD Does Not Exist</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 05:48:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;BOOK PREVIEW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Richard C. Saul, MD
&lt;em&gt;ADHD Does Not Exist:  The Truth About Attention Deficit and Hyperactivity Disorder&lt;/em&gt;
Publication date:  February 18, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;************************&lt;/p&gt;
Those of us on this side of the psychiatry debate have been saying for decades that the condition known as ADHD is not an illness, but is rather an arbitrarily delineated cluster of vaguely defined problems that children have acquired in various ways.  We have also pointed out that psychiatry&#39;s labeling of this condition as an illness is simply another instance of their inexorable turf expansion, and that their widespread drugging of the individuals so labeled is destructive and disempowering.
&lt;p&gt;And, also for decades, psychiatry has been marginalizing us as unscientific mental illness deniers, who seek to put the clock back and deprive people suffering from this &amp;ldquo;illness&amp;rdquo; of the vital &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; that they so desperately need.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
