<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ECT on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/ect/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ECT on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/ect/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Shock &#34;Treatment&#34; Is Not Safe and Provides Little If Any Benefit</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DELICATE THINGS REQUIRE DELICATE HANDLING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, one of my hobbies was making small transistor radios.  It sounds complicated, but is well within the reach of an average 15-year-old.  You get some magazine articles, learn how to read a circuit, and learn how to use a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transistor is a small device – about half the size of a pencil eraser – with three wires coming out of it.  In building a radio receiver, the transistors have to be soldered to other devices which are in turn soldered to other devices, etc…  The soldering iron is plugged into a wall outlet, but no mains electricity reaches the tip of the iron.  However, tiny eddy currents can circulate in the tip, and although they are only of the order of &lt;i&gt;milliamps&lt;/i&gt;, they can burn a transistor in seconds.  What you have to do is unplug the iron from the socket, make the joint with the tip&amp;rsquo;s retained heat, and then replug the iron to have it ready for the next joint.  The point being that &lt;i&gt;delicate things require delicate handling&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;strong&gt;electricity can be very destructive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
