<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Books Worth Reading on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/books-worth-reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books Worth Reading on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 09:47:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/books-worth-reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Survivor&#39;s Story:  The Dark Threads</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 09:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just read &lt;em&gt;The Dark Threads,&lt;/em&gt; by Jean Davison (Accent Press Ltd, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s autobiographical, and describes with great detail and insight how a young woman of 18 years, whose only problem was acute shyness coupled with a yearning for some meaning in life, made the mistake of visiting a psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jean describes how she was &lt;strong&gt;bullied into accepting psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; She was &lt;strong&gt;drugged into a zombie-like stupor and given electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;  &lt;/strong&gt;She describes graphically the disempowering and humiliating aspects of &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; and the endless patronizing condescension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock &#34;Treatment&#34; Is Not Safe and Provides Little If Any Benefit</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DELICATE THINGS REQUIRE DELICATE HANDLING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, one of my hobbies was making small transistor radios.  It sounds complicated, but is well within the reach of an average 15-year-old.  You get some magazine articles, learn how to read a circuit, and learn how to use a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transistor is a small device – about half the size of a pencil eraser – with three wires coming out of it.  In building a radio receiver, the transistors have to be soldered to other devices which are in turn soldered to other devices, etc…  The soldering iron is plugged into a wall outlet, but no mains electricity reaches the tip of the iron.  However, tiny eddy currents can circulate in the tip, and although they are only of the order of &lt;i&gt;milliamps&lt;/i&gt;, they can burn a transistor in seconds.  What you have to do is unplug the iron from the socket, make the joint with the tip&amp;rsquo;s retained heat, and then replug the iron to have it ready for the next joint.  The point being that &lt;i&gt;delicate things require delicate handling&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;strong&gt;electricity can be very destructive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Prescription Drugs Associated with Reports of Violence Towards Others&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 12:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the title of a 2010 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0015337&#34;&gt;research report &lt;/a&gt;by Thomas J. Moore, Joseph Glenmullen, and Curt D. Furberg, published in PLOS One, an online peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of the study searched the FDA&amp;rsquo;s Adverse Event Reporting System from 2004 to September 2009, and flagged reports indicating violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They concluded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Acts of violence towards others are a genuine and serious adverse drug event associated with a relatively small group of drugs.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Pharma, by Ben Goldacre</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 23:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All the awful things you&amp;rsquo;ve heard and read about the pharmaceutical companies are documented on the pages of &lt;i&gt;Bad Pharma&lt;/i&gt; with compelling clarity and abundant references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Goldacre is a British physician.  His primary issue is the safety and efficacy of pharmaceutical products in general medicine, but he has a lot to say about psychiatric drugs also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs are tested by the people who manufacture them, in poorly designed trials, on hopelessly small numbers of weird, unrepresentative patients, and analysed using techniques which are flawed by design, in such a way that they exaggerate the benefits of treatments.&#34;(p. x)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Important Book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-important-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 09:44:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-important-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/De-medicalizing-Misery.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4326&#34; alt=&#34;De-medicalizing-Misery&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/De-medicalizing-Misery-300x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De-Medicalizing Misery&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a collection of papers by various authors, most of whom have experience working with clients and are also associated with prestigious British universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“The architects of modern biological psychiatry have constructed a system that does little justice to the myriad problems it claims to address, while creating multiple iatrogenic problems for those to whom it is applied.” (p 1)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Book by Stephen Ray Flora</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-book-by-stephen-ray-flora/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 23:21:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-book-by-stephen-ray-flora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I recommended &lt;em&gt;Taking America Off Drugs&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen Ray Flora.  Well, he has also written &lt;em&gt;The Power of Reinforcement&lt;/em&gt; (State University of New York Press, 2004), and this also is well worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement is a crucial concept in psychology, and in this book Dr. Flora clarifies the matter and dispels the misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it; read it; keep it close.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2012 22:09:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-good-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taking America Off Drugs&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen Ray Flora&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago,&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2011/12/28/forensic-psychiatry/#.Txzc-W8V3a8&#34;&gt; in a comment&lt;/a&gt;, A Behaviorist Fan recommended the above book to me.  It came out in 2007, and I don’t know how I missed it at the time.  But I’ve read it now and it’s a superb piece of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely a &lt;em&gt;must buy&lt;/em&gt; and must keep close at hand.  Stephen analyses the various “diagnoses” listed in DSM.  He points out their behavioral nature, and describes how they can be ameliorated with relatively simple behavioral techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Interesting Book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-interesting-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 10:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-interesting-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unhinged, by Daniel Carlat, MD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Carlat is a psychiatrist who has written something of an exposé of the abuses that reside within the psychiatric profession.  Many of his chapters echo topics that have been addressed frequently on this blog.  Dr. Carlat still clings to the notion that problem behaviors can be accurately conceptualized as illnesses, but he does criticize the proliferation of “diagnoses” and the application of these “diagnoses” to increasing numbers of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugs, Placebos, and Life</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugs-placebos-and-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2010 18:53:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugs-placebos-and-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read a very interesting book by Irving Kirsch, PhD.  It’s called &lt;i&gt;The Emperor’s New Drugs&lt;/i&gt;, and the central theme of the work is that antidepressants are only very slightly more effective than placebos (i.e. sugar pills), and that the difference is not clinically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic is cogent and the research is rigorous.  Read the book and decide for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kirsch argues in favor of psychotherapy as a substitute for pills.  And certainly talking is usually helpful.  However, as long as depression is conceptualized as an illness, I don’t believe we will see real progress in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The So-Called Mental Illnesses Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 19:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that mental illness is a spurious and invalid concept, which is promoted and developed by the American Psychiatric Association to legitimize the use of mood-altering drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that people display various problems in their daily lives and particularly in their interpersonal relationships.  The American Psychiatric Association claims that all such problems are caused by mental illness and their list of these so-called illnesses is so long that virtually anybody can be embraced within their coils.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
