<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Myth of Chemical Imbalance on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/myth-of-chemical-imbalance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Myth of Chemical Imbalance on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2013 22:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/myth-of-chemical-imbalance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Look at Critical Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2013 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-critical-look-at-critical-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.criticalpsychiatry.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Critical Psychiatry Network&lt;/a&gt; is a group of British psychiatrists who are developing and promoting concepts that question and criticize the assumptions that underlie present-day psychiatric practice, not only in Britain, but also in the US and other developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Psychiatry challenges the notion that the various DSM &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are biologically-based illnesses, and adduces a great deal of evidence to the contrary.  They stress the cultural/social aspect of psychiatric diagnosing.  For instance, they point out that a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of ADHD is a cultural construct which provides schools and parents with a socially acceptable method of dealing with difficult children (rather than an identification of an illness).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression is Not a Brain Defect</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-is-not-a-brain-defect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 14:15:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/depression-is-not-a-brain-defect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve come across an article by psychologist Bruce Levine, PhD, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/04/how-the-brain-defect-theory-of-depression-stigmatizes-depression-sufferers/&#34;&gt;How the “Brain Defect” Theory of Depression Stigmatizes Depression Sufferers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Levine convincingly debunks the brain defect theory, and also the notion that the illness theory destigmatizes depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; “Americans have been increasingly socialized to be terrified of the overwhelming pain that can fuel depression, and they have been taught to distrust their own and other’s ability to overcome it. This terror, like any terror, inhibits critical thinking. Without critical thinking, it is difficult to accurately assess the legitimacy of authorities. And Americans have become easy prey for mental health authorities’ proclamation that depression is a result of a brain defect.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
