<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>IF THEY&#39;RE NOT ILLNESSES WHAT ARE THEY? on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/if-theyre-not-illnesses-what-are-they/</link>
    <description>Recent content in IF THEY&#39;RE NOT ILLNESSES WHAT ARE THEY? on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 09:43:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/if-theyre-not-illnesses-what-are-they/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>There are No Mental Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 09:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been writing this blog for the past three years.  The primary concepts are scattered throughout the blog, and I thought it might be helpful to draw together the essential underlying concepts in one post.  Some of this repeats material covered under the individual “diagnoses,” and for this I apologize to my regular readers, but the notion that there are no mental illnesses (which I repeat regularly) is unorthodox and warrants clarification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Illness:  The History of a Mistake</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-the-history-of-a-mistake/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2010 11:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-illness-the-history-of-a-mistake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The human brain is a pattern-seeking machine.  Because of his brain, man strives to understand the world around him and uses this understanding to improve his lot.  The brain looks for patterns and explanations.  Our ancestors, for instance, discovered that certain rocks, through processing in certain ways, could be shaped to make sharp tools which they used to great advantage.  Later it was discovered that other rocks when heated in certain ways produced iron. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The So-Called Mental Illnesses Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 19:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that mental illness is a spurious and invalid concept, which is promoted and developed by the American Psychiatric Association to legitimize the use of mood-altering drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that people display various problems in their daily lives and particularly in their interpersonal relationships.  The American Psychiatric Association claims that all such problems are caused by mental illness and their list of these so-called illnesses is so long that virtually anybody can be embraced within their coils.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
