<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>NIMH on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/nimh/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NIMH on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 14:33:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/nimh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Insel Changes His Mind</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-insel-changes-his-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 14:33:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-insel-changes-his-mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, as I guess everybody knows by now, Dr. Insel has changed his mind.  On April 29, he stated that the weakness of DSM &amp;ldquo;…is its lack of validity.&amp;rdquo;  He went on to express the view that his agency, NIMH, (the US government&amp;rsquo;s mental health research arm) &amp;ldquo;…cannot succeed if we use DSM categories…&amp;rdquo;  You can see his full statement &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/director/2013/transforming-diagnosis.shtml&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement was widely interpreted as a significant rift between NIMH and the APA.  But apparently they&amp;rsquo;ve made up their differences and are pals again.  On May 13, just two weeks after his divorce statement, Dr. Insel and Dr. Lieberman, APA president elect, have issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2013/dsm-5-and-rdoc-shared-interests.shtml?utm_source=rss_readers&amp;amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;amp;utm_campaign=rss_summary&#34;&gt;joint statement&lt;/a&gt; in which they express the belief that the DSM &amp;ldquo;…represents the best information currently available for clinical diagnosis of mental disorders.&amp;rdquo;  Patients, families and insurers, we are told, &amp;ldquo;…can be confident that effective treatments are available and that the DSM is the key resource for delivering the best available care.&amp;rdquo;  It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe that this is the same DSM that he earlier criticized as &lt;i&gt;lacking validity!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Strikes Back:  APA Responds to NIMH</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-apa-responds-to-nimh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 09:16:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-apa-responds-to-nimh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 3, 2013, David Kupfer MD (DSM-5 Task Force Chair) responded to Thomas Insel&amp;rsquo;s April 29&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; unequivocal attack on the validity and usefulness of DSM.  You can see Dr. Kupfer&amp;rsquo;s response &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Statement-from-dsm-chair-david-kupfer-md.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Essentially Dr. Insel said that the categories set out in the DSM did not correspond to anything in the real world, and that NIMH would no longer be using these categories as the basis for their research program.  This statement did not, however, represent any significant movement away from the biomedical model on the part of NIMH.  In fact, if anything, it was a movement towards an even &lt;i&gt;more&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;deeply entrenched&lt;/i&gt; medical model.  But it was a huge hit on DSM and on the APA, who tout the catalog as the basis to their claim to scientific credibility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
