<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ADHD on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/adhd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ADHD on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 05:30:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/adhd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances and the &#34;Overdiagnosing&#34; of Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-overdiagnosing-of-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 05:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-overdiagnosing-of-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 31, 2016, the very eminent psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, architect of DSM-IV, published an article on his Psychology Today blog, Saving Normal.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201610/dsm-5-diagnoses-in-kids-should-always-be-written-in-pencil&#34;&gt;DSM-5 Diagnoses In Kids Should Always Be Written In Pencil&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  (The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/dsm5-diagnoses-in-kids-sh_b_12732918.html&#34;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; also appeared on the Huffington Post Blog on the same date.)  The subheading is &amp;ldquo;Mislabelling children and adolescents is frequent and can haunt them for life&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in many of Dr. Frances&amp;rsquo;s recent articles, the bulk of the text is written by someone else, and Dr. Frances provides an introduction and a summary/conclusion.  In this case, the core of the article is written. by Juan Vasen and Gisela Untoiglich of Forum Infancias, an Argentine organization of mental health workers dedicated to the &amp;ldquo;proper diagnosis and treatment of children and adolescents&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  A Destructive Psychiatric Hoax</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-psychiatric-hoax/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-psychiatric-hoax/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, Alan Schwarz, an investigative reporter for the New York Times, published his latest book:  &lt;em&gt;ADHD Nation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blurb on the jacket states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;More than 1 in 7 American children get diagnosed with ADHD—three times what experts have said is appropriate—meaning that millions of kids are misdiagnosed and taking medications such as Adderall or Concerta for a psychiatric condition they probably do not have.  The numbers rise every year.  And still, many experts and drug companies deny any cause for concern.  In fact, they say that adults and the rest of the world should embrace ADHD and that its medications will transform their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Overdiagnosis of ADHD&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-overdiagnosis-of-adhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 04:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-overdiagnosis-of-adhd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 23, the very eminent psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, published on the HuffPost blog an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/conclusive-proof-adhd-is-overdiagnosed_b_10107214.html&#34;&gt;Conclusive Proof ADHD is Overdiagnosed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general theme, that various &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses&amp;rdquo; are being &amp;ldquo;overdiagnosed&amp;rdquo; is gaining popularity in recent years among some psychiatrists, presumably in an effort to distance themselves from the trend of psychiatric-drugs-on-demand-for-every-conceivable-human-problem that has become an escalating and undeniable feature of American psychiatric practice.  The assertion in Dr. Frances&amp;rsquo;s title – that the label &amp;ldquo;ADHD&amp;rdquo; is being applied to too many people – is obviously true. But the implicit assumptions – that there is a &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; level of such labeling, and that the label has some valid ontological significance – are emphatically false.  But Dr. Frances affords no recognition to this aspect of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  The Hoax Unravels</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of stating the obvious, ADHD is not an illness.  Rather, it is an unreliable and disempowering label for a loose collection of arbitrarily chosen and vaguely defined behaviors.  ADHD has been avidly promoted as an illness by pharma-psychiatry for the purpose of selling stimulant drugs.  In which endeavor, they have been phenomenally successful, but, as in other areas of psychiatry, the hoax is unraveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Still Trying to Excuse Psychiatry&#39;s (and his own) Role in the ADHD &#39;Epidemic&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-trying-to-excuse-psychiatry-s-and-his-own-role-in-the-adhd-epidemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-trying-to-excuse-psychiatry-s-and-his-own-role-in-the-adhd-epidemic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 9, 2015, Allen Frances, MD, posted an interesting article on the Huffington Post&amp;rsquo;s Blog.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/why-are-so-many-college-a_b_8331958.html&#34;&gt;Why Are So Many College and High School Kids Abusing Adderall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that the &amp;ldquo;excessive use of ADHD medication&amp;rdquo; is a more legitimate target for a war on drugs than the ongoing war with the drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Huffington Post article is unusual, in that most of it is written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD.  Dr. Frances wrote the introduction, ending with  &amp;ldquo;I have invited Dr Gretchen LeFever Watson, a clinical psychologist and public health researcher, to describe this growing problem.&amp;rdquo;  Dr. Watson wrote the main body of the piece; and Dr. Frances finished up with some brief concluding remarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Inherent Unreliability of the ADHD Label</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-inherent-unreliability-of-the-adhd-label/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 05:30:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-inherent-unreliability-of-the-adhd-label/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I imagine that everybody on this side of the issue knows by now that the eminent psychiatrist Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, Chief Psychiatrist at Columbia, and past President of the APA, called Robert Whitaker &amp;ldquo;a menace to society.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This outburst of petulance – the latest in a string of similar deprecations – occurred on April 26, 2015 during an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cbc.ca/radio/thesundayedition/upper-v-lower-jihadi-town-listener-mail-the-untold-story-of-psychiatry-reciting-poetry-1.3045391/the-art-and-science-of-psychiatry-1.3045627&#34;&gt;interview with Michael Enright&lt;/a&gt; on CBC (Canadian Broadcasting Corporation) radio&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Sunday Edition.&amp;rdquo;  The grounds for Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s vituperation were that Robert had dared to challenge some of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s most sacred tenets!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  A Destructive and Disempowering Label; Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-and-disempowering-label-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 05:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-a-destructive-and-disempowering-label-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen an increasing number of articles and papers from psychiatrists in which they seem to be accepting at least some of the antipsychiatry criticisms, and appear interested in reforms.  It is tempting to see this development as an indication of progress, but as in many aspects of life, things aren&amp;rsquo;t always what they seem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month (June 2015), The Lancet Psychiatry published a paper online in their Personal View series.  The paper is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Childhood-a-suitable-case-for-treatment.pdf&#34;&gt;Childhood: a suitable case for treatment?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and the authors are Ilina Singh and Simon Wessely.  Dr. Singh is Professor of Science, Ethics &amp;amp; Society at King&amp;rsquo;s College London, and is cross-appointed to the Institute of Psychiatry.  Dr. Wessely is professor of psychological medicine at the Institute of Psychiatry, King&amp;rsquo;s College London, and President of the Royal College of Psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  &lt;b&gt;Parenting Your Child with ADHD: A No-Nonsense Guide for Nurturing Self-Reliance and Cooperation&lt;/b&gt;, by Craig Wiener, EdD</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-parenting-your-child-with-adhd-a-no-nonsense-guide-for-nurturing-self-reliance-and-coo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 05:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-parenting-your-child-with-adhd-a-no-nonsense-guide-for-nurturing-self-reliance-and-coo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read this book, and I think it would be extremely helpful for parents, teachers, and counselors who work with children in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…ADHD [is] something that your child does rather than something that she &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt;.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The first thing to realize is that while you and other adults see your child’s ADHD behavior as a problem to overcome, for your child, ADHD behavior holds &lt;em&gt;solutions&lt;/em&gt; to the difficulties that he faces on a daily basis. When your child encounters adversity, ADHD behavior somehow mitigates the situation. When you identify what gives his ADHD behavior its staying power, you will have gained valuable insight into why such behavior repeats so frequently. You will also be taking a giant step forward in knowing how to eliminate it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ADHD Label and Mortality</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-adhd-label-and-mortality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 05:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-adhd-label-and-mortality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 26, 2015, The Lancet published online an article by Soren Dalsgaard et al titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thelancet.com/pdfs/journals/lancet/PIIS0140-6736(14)61684-6.pdf&#34;&gt;Mortality in children, adolescents, and adults with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a nationwide cohort study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article describes a Danish study that was designed to assess &amp;ldquo;ADHD-related mortality in a large cohort of Danish individuals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers describe their methods as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;By use of the Danish national registers, we followed up 1·92 million individuals, including 32 061 with ADHD, from their first birthday through to 2013. We estimated mortality rate ratios (MRRs), adjusted for calendar year, age, sex, family history of psychiatric disorders, maternal and paternal age, and parental educational and employment status, by Poisson regression, to compare individuals with and without ADHD.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  A Disease Called Childhood, by Marilyn Wedge</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-a-disease-called-childhood-by-marilyn-wedge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-a-disease-called-childhood-by-marilyn-wedge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Avery, a member of Penguin Group USA, has recently published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Disease Called Childhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Marilyn Wedge.  Marilyn has a PhD in psychology and works as a family therapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, fully 11% of American children had received a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).  It is widely believed by these children, their parents, the press, the public, and government agencies, that this loose collection of vaguely defined behaviors constitutes an illness – specifically a chemical imbalance in the brain, which is corrected by stimulant drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Insel:  &#34;Are Children Overmedicated?&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-insel-are-children-overmedicated/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 05:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-insel-are-children-overmedicated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, is the Director of the National Institute of Mental Health.  In June of last year, he published, on the Director&amp;rsquo;s Blog, an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/director/2014/are-children-overmedicated.shtml&#34;&gt;Are Children Overmedicated?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  The gist of the article is that children are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being overmedicated, but rather that there is an increase in &amp;ldquo;severe psychiatric problems&amp;rdquo; in this population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The latest estimate from the National Center for Health Statistics reports that 7.5 percent of U.S. children between ages 6 and 17 were taking medication for &#39;emotional or behavioral difficulties&#39; in 2011-2012. The CDC reports a five-fold increase in the number of children under 18 on psychostimulants from 1988-1994 to 2007–2010, with the most recent rate of 4.2 percent. The same report estimates that 1.3 percent of children are on antidepressants. The rate of antipsychotic prescriptions for children has increased six-fold over this same period, according to a study of office visits within the National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey. In children under age 5, psychotropic prescription rates peaked at 1.45 percent in 2002-2005 and declined to 1.00 percent from 2006-2009.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression/ ADHD</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-adhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 06:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-adhd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;I was searching Google for effects of propaganda on the human psych, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;and stumbled upon this site. After reading a few stories, I felt I had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to share my own. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I was in high school I was depressed. To the point where I was a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;walking text book definition. Failing grades, poor hygiene, isolation. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;All the signs were obvious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I had to go to rehab for drinking too much cough syrup.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I went to the doctor he diagnosed me with ADHD. I have never been &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;a hyper person. always rather slow and calm.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Than he tells me that he is going to just experiment with multiple &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;drugs to see what works, and than diagnose me with whatever that drug &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;treats.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;First drug was Vyvanse (lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Its a new &amp;ldquo;abuse-free&amp;rdquo; amphetamine. Due to a coating of protein, the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;chemical can only dissolve in your stomach acid. Injecting, Smoking, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;or Snorting would not activate it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;However the prescribed dose taken once a day was enough to make me a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;full effect of amphetamines, and I began losing alot of sleep. After &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;having multiple panic attacks on this medication, I demanded the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;doctor take me off of it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;He than gave me Focalin (Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Another new &amp;ldquo;abuse-free&amp;rdquo; drug. During my younger years I experimented &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;with MDMA, and I would compare the feeling of Focalin with that of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Extacy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;When I got into college my doctor pulled me off of it saying that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;college kids are more likely to sell it, and that he must change my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;prescription.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Next drug was Strattera (atomoxetine). I threw up every time I took &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;it. It gave me intense piriods of happiness followed by extreme bursts &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;of anger for no reason at all.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I stopped going to the doctor, I stopped taking medications. I no &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;longer trust the medical system, the pharm companies, or even the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;government. I&amp;rsquo;d rather suffer the depression untreated than go through &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;what I went through in high school.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;On a side note, The experience made me drop out of school, and get my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;GED. That year, my school experienced a higher drop out rate than ever &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;before.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Toddlers for Inattention, Impulsivity, and Hyperactivity</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-toddlers-for-inattention-impulsivity-and-hyperactivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 05:58:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-toddlers-for-inattention-impulsivity-and-hyperactivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, the New York Times ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/17/us/among-experts-scrutiny-of-attention-disorder-diagnoses-in-2-and-3-year-olds.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thousands of Toddlers Are Medicated for A.D.H.D., Report Finds, Raising Worries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;by Alan Schwarz.  Here is the opening sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;More than 10,000 American toddlers 2 or 3 years old are being medicated for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder outside established pediatric guidelines, according to data presented on Friday by an official at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The CDC official is Susanna Visser, MS, DrPh, Acting Associate Director of Science for the Division of Human Development and Disability, and she was speaking at the annual Rosalyn Carter Georgia Mental Health Forum.  I have not been able to find the text of Ms. Visser&#39;s speech.  (It will probably be published later.)  Meanwhile, there is a good deal of information in Alan Schwarz&#39;s article.  Here are some more quotes:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The report, which found that toddlers covered by Medicaid are particularly prone to be put on medication such as Ritalin and Adderall, is among the first efforts to gauge the diagnosis of A.D.H.D. in children below age 4. Doctors at the Georgia Mental Health Forum at the Carter Center in Atlanta, where the data was presented, as well as several outside experts strongly criticized the use of medication in so many children that young.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driving Under the Influence of Stimulants</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 05:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 22, I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/04/22/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on this general topic.  In that article I pointed out that the notion of stimulant prescription drugs improving the driving of people who &amp;ldquo;have ADHD&amp;rdquo; was gaining traction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since than I have come across two articles on this subject from Australia.  (Thanks to Nanu Grewal for the links.)  Both articles appeared in the Sunshine Coast Daily, and you can see them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/hospital-launches-complaints-probe/1122551/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/crackdowntoo-late-for-twins-slow-action-way-too-la/1960148/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2009, four people, including five-year-old twin girls, died in a two-car accident.  The driver of one of the cars had been prescribed dexamphetamine for the treatment of ADHD by a local psychiatrist, and was found to have had six times the prescribed dosage of dexamphetamine in his system at the time of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;ADHD&#39; and Dangerous Driving</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 05:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Laurence Jerome, a Canadian psychiatrist, and two colleagues wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/ADHD-and-Driving-Jerome-et-al-ccap15_3p105.pdf&#34;&gt;What We Know About ADHD and Driving Risk: A Literature Review, Meta-Analysis and Critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It was published in the Journal of the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry in August, 2006. The primary result of the meta-analysis was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Current data support the utility of stimulant medication in improving driving performance in younger ADHD drivers.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The study is lengthy and well-referenced, but in keeping with standard psychiatric practice, it conceptualizes and presents ADHD as a &#34;…common psychiatric disorder…&#34; with symptoms of &#34;…inattention, impulsiveness and hyperactivity…&#34;  In other words, they present ADHD as something that a person &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; rather than as something that a person &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; The problem with this approach is that it creates the impression that meaningful or significant correlations/effects have been found, where in fact all that has happened is an elucidation of the terms used.
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the authors refer to a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Fried%2C+R.%2C+Petty%2C+C.R.%2C+Surman%2C+C.B.%2C+Reimer%2C+B.%2C+Aleardi%2C+M.%2C+Martin%2C+J.M.+2006&#34;&gt;Fried et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2006) and state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  Are We Helping Or Harming?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 06:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In November 2013, the British Medical Journal published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://charlesmarsan.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Overdiagnosis-ADHD.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: are we helping or harming?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Rae Thomas, PhD, Psychologist, Australia; Geoffrey K. Mitchell, MB BS, FRACGP, PhD, Professor of General Practice, Australia; and Laura Batstra, PhD, Psychologist, Netherlands.  The article is part of a series on the dangers of overdiagnosis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Prevalence and prescribing rates for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) have risen steeply over the past decade, partly in response to concerns about underdiagnosis and undertreatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Still Passing the Buck: Psychiatry Is Blameless</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 05:47:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has expressed concern about the rise in the number of people being assigned a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of ADHD.  He has put up a video on Medscape, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/819298&#34;&gt;Explaining the Rise in ADHD&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There is a transcript with the video.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is responding to a December 14, 2013, New York Times article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/15/health/the-selling-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;The Selling of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;by Alan Schwarz, and a December 18 editorial in the same paper titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/19/opinion/an-epidemic-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html&#34;&gt;An Epidemic of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sandcastle Continues to Crumble:  ADHD Does Not Exist</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 05:48:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;BOOK PREVIEW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Richard C. Saul, MD
&lt;em&gt;ADHD Does Not Exist:  The Truth About Attention Deficit and Hyperactivity Disorder&lt;/em&gt;
Publication date:  February 18, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;************************&lt;/p&gt;
Those of us on this side of the psychiatry debate have been saying for decades that the condition known as ADHD is not an illness, but is rather an arbitrarily delineated cluster of vaguely defined problems that children have acquired in various ways.  We have also pointed out that psychiatry&#39;s labeling of this condition as an illness is simply another instance of their inexorable turf expansion, and that their widespread drugging of the individuals so labeled is destructive and disempowering.
&lt;p&gt;And, also for decades, psychiatry has been marginalizing us as unscientific mental illness deniers, who seek to put the clock back and deprive people suffering from this &amp;ldquo;illness&amp;rdquo; of the vital &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; that they so desperately need.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Never Mind The Facts; Just Sell More Pills</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 05:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article, recently published in Journal of Contemporary Psychotherapy, on Springer Link.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10879-013-9244-x/fulltext.html&#34;&gt;Shooting the Messenger: The Case of ADHD&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and it was written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently some of the authors had noted in 1995 a marked increase in the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of the condition known as ADHD in southeastern Virginia.  This is a large urban conglomeration of six different cities, including Norfolk, Portsmouth, and Virginia Beach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood &#39;Mental Disorders&#39; According to the CDC</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 05:23:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-mental-disorders-according-to-the-cdc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 17, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a report titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/pdf/other/su6202.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental Health Surveillance Among Children – United States, 2005-2011&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The CDC is based in Atlanta, Georgia and is a part of the US Department of Health and Human Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CDC&amp;rsquo;s report runs to 40 pages, including tables and references.  It received a fair amount of media coverage, and will likely inform legislation and other government action for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Children Gives Them the Wrong Message</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 10:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The routine drugging of children for the ordinary problems of childhood is destructive for two reasons:  firstly because of the toxic effects of the pharmaceutical products, and secondly because it &lt;strong&gt;conveys to the child the message that drugs are an acceptable way to deal with life&amp;rsquo;s problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This latter kind of damage is graphically illustrated in a tragic NY Times article by Ted Gup.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/03/opinion/diagnosis-human.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Ted is a fellow of the Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Under Scrutiny</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-under-scrutiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 12:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-under-scrutiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Duncan Double is a British psychiatrist who has a website called &lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Critical Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 12 he published a post under the heading:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/2012/10/the-majority-of-psychiatrists-think.html&#34;&gt;“The majority of psychiatrists think adult ADHD is an example of the over-medicalisation of everyday life.” &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“When I trained, adult ADHD was never mentioned - it&#39;s a relatively new concept, gaining popularity in the 1990s. Many psychiatrists don&#39;t feel happy diagnosing a condition in adults that they were taught children generally grow out of.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parenting and Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/parenting-and-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 14:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/parenting-and-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About a week ago an article appeared on the ‘net concerning an attempt by parents to ban ice cream vendors from a playground in Brooklyn, New York.  The piece was reprinted in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/slopers_creamy_river_lcaxb1lj4D0SHqo4f2K3GO&#34;&gt;New York Post&lt;/a&gt;.  Apparently some of the parents are upset because the arrival of the vendors stimulates requests for ice cream from the children, which results in confrontation and bitterness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsible parents everywhere will recognize the dilemma.  Ice cream has little or no nutritional value, but children like it.  So do we stand our ground or do we give in?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on ADHD</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-adhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2012 21:46:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-adhd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week Reuters ran an article by Toni Clarke:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/01/01/us-adhd-adderall-shortage-idUSTRE80009E20120101&#34;&gt;“Insight: Shortage of ADHD Drug Adderall seen persisting.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the first five paragraphs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“A shortage of Adderall, which is used to treat attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, shows little sign of easing as manufacturers struggle to get enough active ingredient to make the drug and demand climbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Adderall, a stimulant, is a controlled substance, meaning it is addictive and has the potential to be abused. The Drug Enforcement Administration tightly regulates how much of the drug&#39;s active pharmaceutical ingredient (API) can be distributed to manufacturers each year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 00:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing this post as a response to a comment posted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://drpullen.com/&#34;&gt;medical blog&lt;/a&gt; in my previous post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2011/02/24/more-on-so-called-bipolar-disorder/#comments&#34;&gt;More on So-called Bipolar Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2001 I became very ill.  The symptoms were exhaustion and mild nosebleeds. I went to three different practitioners, but they all were dismissive of my concerns, assured me that I was in good health, and sent me on my way.   On August 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of that year I was admitted to the hospital in Greeley, Colorado with complete kidney failure.  The nephrologist at the hospital gave me the &lt;em&gt;diagnosis&lt;/em&gt; that had eluded the earlier doctors:  Wegener’s Granulomatosis - a rare autoimmune disease that attacks lungs, kidneys, and airways. I have been on dialysis every since.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conduct Disorder and Oppositional Defiant Disorder</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/conduct-disorder-and-oppositional-defiant-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2009 14:12:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/conduct-disorder-and-oppositional-defiant-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONDUCT DISORDER
&lt;/strong&gt;
The essential feature of Conduct Disorder, according to the APA, is a “repetitive and persistent pattern” of rule breaking or activity which violates other people’s basic rights.  The manual identifies four broad categories of behavior under this heading:  aggression; destruction of property; theft or deceitfulness; and serious violation of rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSM goes on to state that individuals with this disorder display little concern for the feelings or welfare of others, are frequently callous and indifferent to other people’s pain and loss, and show little in the way of feelings of guilt or remorse.  Poor frustration tolerance, irritability, temper tantrums, and recklessness are cited as frequently associated features.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2009 11:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder is defined as “a persistent pattern of inattention and/or hyperimpulsivity that is more frequent and severe than is typically observed in individuals at a comparable level of development.” There is a requirement that the problem existed before age seven and that some of the problems are present in at least two settings. There also must be clear evidence that the inappropriate activity interferes with the individual’s social, academic, or occupational functioning. With regards to the actual diagnostic procedure, the APA lists eighteen behavioral indicators, nine under the heading “inattention,” six under “hyperactivity,” and three under “impulsivity.” For the diagnosis to be considered positive, the child must exhibit at least six problems from either the inattention list or the hyperimpulsivity lists. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
