<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Schizophrenia on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/schizophrenia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Schizophrenia on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 05:30:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/schizophrenia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Robert Whitaker Refutes Jeffrey Lieberman; But Is Psychiatry Reformable?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 05:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 5, 2017, Donald Goff, MD and seven other psychiatrists, including the very eminent Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, published an article in the American Journal of Psychiatry.  The title is: &lt;span style=&#34;color: #000080;&#34;&gt;&lt;span lang=&#34;zxx&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.16091016&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Long-Term Effects of Antipsychotic Medication on Clinical Course in Schizophrenia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Concerns have been raised that treatment with antipsychotic medication might adversely affect long-term outcomes for people with schizophrenia. The evidence cited for these concerns includes the association of antipsychotic treatment with brain volume reduction and with dopamine receptor sensitization, which might make patients vulnerable to relapse and illness progression. An international group of experts was convened to examine findings from clinical and basic research relevant to these concerns. Little evidence was found to support a negative long-term effect of initial or maintenance antipsychotic treatment on outcomes, compared with withholding treatment. Randomized controlled trials strongly support the efficacy of antipsychotics for the acute treatment of psychosis and prevention of relapse; correlational evidence suggests that early intervention and reduced duration of untreated psychosis might improve longer-term outcomes. Strategies for treatment discontinuation or alternative nonpharmacologic treatment approaches may benefit a subgroup of patients but may be associated with incremental risk of relapse and require further study, including the development of biomarkers that will enable a precision medicine approach to individualized treatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on the Biological Evidence for &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 10, 2017, I put up a post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/http:/behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;The Biological Evidence for &amp;ldquo;Mental Illness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  It was published simultaneously on Mad in America.  The post was a response to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.madinamerica.com/comment-history/?user_id=11436&#34;&gt;earlier comment&lt;/a&gt; from Carolina Partners in Mental Healthcare PLLC, which included the assertion &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses have a long history of biological evidence.&amp;rdquo;  In my January 10 article, I challenged this assertion and pointed out that no such evidence existed.  The article generated some comments, most of which were favorable.  There was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/10/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/#comment-3097355796&#34;&gt;one comment&lt;/a&gt;, however, from Michael, who asserted:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Biological Evidence for &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 05:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 2, 2017, I published a short post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/02/carrie-fisher-dead-at-age-60/&#34;&gt;Carrie Fisher Dead at Age 60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on Behaviorism and Mental Health.  The article was published simultaneously on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.madinamerica.com/2017/01/carrie-fisher-dead-age-60/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On January 4, a response from Carolina Partners was entered into the comments string on both sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carolina Partners in Mental Healthcare, PLLC, is a large psychiatric group practice based in North Carolina.  According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.carolinapartners.com/&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;, they comprise 14 psychiatrists, 7 psychologists, 34 Advanced Practice Nurse Practitioners/Physicians Assistants, and 43 Therapists and Counselors.  They have 27 North Carolina locations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances on the Benefits of &#34;Antipsychotics&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-on-the-benefits-of-antipsychotics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 05:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-on-the-benefits-of-antipsychotics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 1, Allen Frances, MD, published an interesting article on the Huffington Post blog.  The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/do-antipsychotics-help-or_b_9131376.html&#34;&gt;Do Antipsychotics Help or Harm Psychotic Symptoms?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and is a response to Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s post of January 27:  &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2016/01/me-allen-frances-and-climbing-out-of-a-pigeonhole/&#34;&gt;Me, Allen Frances, and Climbing Out of a Pigeonhole&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  This post, in turn, was a response to Dr. Frances&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/psychiatric-medicines-are_b_8990770.html&#34;&gt;Psychiatric Medicines Are Not All Good or All Bad&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which was published in the Huffington Post on January 15.  Readers may remember that I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2016/02/09/allen-frances-seeks-the-middle-way/&#34;&gt;critique&lt;/a&gt; of this latter article on February 9.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are &#39;Psychiatric Disorders&#39; Brain Diseases?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-disorders-brain-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 05:30:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-disorders-brain-diseases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steven Reidbord MD is a board-certified psychiatrist who practices in San Francisco.  He writes a blog called Reidbord&amp;rsquo;s Reflections.  On December 12, 2015, he posted an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.stevenreidbordmd.com/?p=1107&#34;&gt;Are psychiatric disorders brain diseases?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting and thought-provoking piece, with many twists and turns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments and reflections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Of the conditions deemed inherently psychiatric, some seem rooted in biological brain dysfunction.  Schizophrenia, autism, bipolar disorder, and severe forms of obsessive compulsive disorder and melancholic depression are often cited.  It’s important to note that their apparently biological nature derives from natural history and clinical presentation, not from diagnostic tests, and not because we know their root causes.  Schizophrenia, for example, runs in families, usually appears at a characteristic age, severely affects a diverse array of mental functions, looks very similar across cultures, and brings with it reliable if non-specific neuroanatomical changes.  Even though schizophrenia cannot be diagnosed under the microscope or on brain imaging, it is plausible that a biological mechanism eventually will be found.  (The same type of reasoning applied to AIDS before the discovery of HIV, and to many other medical diseases.)  A similar argument can be made for other putatively biological psychiatric disorders.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delusions</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/delusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 05:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/delusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 defines delusions as &amp;ldquo;…fixed beliefs that are not amenable to change in the light of conflicting evidence.&amp;rdquo;  (p 87).  The manual lists six kinds of delusions:  persecutory; referential; grandiose; erotomanic; nihilistic; and somatic.  The APA provides another definition of delusions on p 819.  It&amp;rsquo;s substantially the same as the one above, but offers the additional varieties:  bizarre; delusional jealousy; mixed type; mood-congruent; mood-incongruent; of being controlled; thought broadcasting; and thought insertion.  Interestingly, nihilistic delusions are omitted from the second list.  These, we are told on page 87,  &amp;ldquo;…involve the conviction that a major catastrophe will occur.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances &#39;Replies&#39;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-replies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 05:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-replies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 19, 2015, I published a post titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/06/19/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-and-johnson/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allen Frances&amp;rsquo; Ties to Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that post, I set out some very serious allegations against Dr. Frances.  I drew these allegations from a document titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Rothman.pdf&#34;&gt;Special Witness Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; dated October 15, 2010.  The report was written by David Rothman, PhD, Professor of Social Medicine at Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rothman&amp;rsquo;s report was produced in the context of a lawsuit filed by the State of Texas against Janssen Pharmaceutica, a subsidiary of Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances&#39; Ties to Johnson &amp; Johnson</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 05:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uottawa.scholarsportal.info/ottawa/index.php/aporia/article/view/3486/3195&#34;&gt;Diagnosisgate: Conflict of Interest at the Top of the Psychiatric Apparatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Paula Caplan, PhD.  The article was published in Aporia, the University of Ottawa nursing journal, in January 2015.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oa.uottawa.ca/journals/aporia/about_aporia.jsp?lang=&#34;&gt;Aporia&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;a peer-reviewed, bilingual, and open access journal dedicated to scholarly debates in nursing and the health sciences.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr, Caplan is a clinical and research psychologist, and an Associate at Harvard&amp;rsquo;s DuBois Institute.  She worked as a consultant to the DSM-IV task force in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s, but resigned from this position after two years.    Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from her February 2014 post on Mad in America &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/02/great-crazy-cover-harm-results-rewriting-history-dsm/&#34;&gt;The Great “Crazy” Cover-up: Harm Results from Rewriting the History of DSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptic Drugs And Mortality</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-mortality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-mortality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November of last year, the Schizophrenia Bulletin published online a research study:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25422511&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antipsychotic Treatment and Mortality in Schizophrenia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Minna Torniainen et al.  The research was conducted in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors offer the following background for the study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;It is generally believed that long-term use of antipsychotics increases mortality and, especially, the risk of cardiovascular death. However, there are no solid data to substantiate this view.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
and the following conclusions:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Among patients with schizophrenia, the cumulative antipsychotic exposure displays a U-shaped curve for overall mortality, revealing the highest risk of death among those patients with no antipsychotic use. These results indicate that both excess overall and cardiovascular mortality in schizophrenia is attributable to other factors than antipsychotic treatment when used in adequate dosages.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric Diagnoses:  Labels, Not Explanations</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-labels-not-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-labels-not-explanations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 16, Ronald Pies, MD, published an article in the Psychiatric Times.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/couch-crisis/war-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt;The War on Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; and the sub-title synopsis on the pdf version reads:  &amp;ldquo;A recent report that argues against descriptive diagnosis in medicine is historically ill-informed and medically naive, in the opinion of this psychiatrist.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pies is a very prestigious and eminent psychiatrist.  He is a professor of psychiatry at both Syracuse and Tufts.  He was the first editor of Psychiatric Times, which, by its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/contribute-site&#34;&gt;own account&lt;/a&gt;, provides &amp;ldquo;News, Special Reports, and clinical content related to psychiatry&amp;rdquo; for &amp;ldquo;…psychiatrists and allied mental health professionals who treat mental disorders…Circulation of the monthly print publication is approximately 40,000.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dopamine Hypothesis of Schizophrenia – Version III</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-dopamine-hypothesis-of-schizophrenia-version-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2015 05:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-dopamine-hypothesis-of-schizophrenia-version-iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 27, 2014, the Division of Clinical Psychology of the British Psychological Society published a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bps.org.uk/system/files/user-files/Division%20of%20Clinical%20Psychology/public/understanding_psychosis_-_final_19th_nov_2014.pdf&#34;&gt;Understanding Psychosis and Schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;The paper was edited by Anne Cooke of Canterbury Christ Church University.  The central theme of the paper is that the condition known as psychosis is better understood as a response to adverse life events rather than as a symptom of neurological pathology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper was wide ranging and insightful, and, predictably, drew support from most of us on this side of the issue and criticism from psychiatry.  Section 12 of the paper is headed &amp;ldquo;Medication&amp;rdquo; and under the subheading &amp;ldquo;Key Points&amp;rdquo;, you&amp;rsquo;ll find this quote:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Macabre Celebration:  80 Years of Convulsive &#39;Therapy&#39;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-macabre-celebration-80-years-of-convulsive-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 05:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-macabre-celebration-80-years-of-convulsive-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the June 2014 issue of the Journal of ECT.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Max Fink, MD, and is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/ectjournal/citation/2014/06000/celebrating_80_years_of_inducing_brain_seizures_as.3.aspx&#34;&gt;Celebrating 80 Years of Inducing Brain Seizures as Psychiatric Treatment.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/em&gt;Dr. Fink is a psychiatrist and neurologist, and professor emeritus of psychiatry and neurology at the State University of New York, Stony Brook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is short (approximately 400 words), and is essentially a tribute to Ladislas Meduna for his discovery  &amp;ldquo;…that induced seizures alleviated severe psychiatric disorders…&amp;rdquo;, which Dr. Fink describes as  &amp;ldquo;…a remarkable medical advance…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Social Functioning Predicts Adult Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorder.  Or Does It?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-social-functioning-predicts-adult-schizophrenia-spectrum-disorder-or-does-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 05:58:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-social-functioning-predicts-adult-schizophrenia-spectrum-disorder-or-does-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2013, the journal Schizophrenia Research published a paper by Tsuji, T. et al. titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Tsuji%2C+Schiffman%2C+Kline+2013&#34;&gt;Premorbid teacher-rated social functioning predicts adult schizophrenia-spectrum disorder: A high-risk prospective investigation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Here’s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Social functioning deficits are a core component of schizophrenia spectrum disorders, and may emerge years prior to the onset of diagnosable illness. The current study prospectively examines the relation between teacher-rated childhood social dysfunction and later mental illness among participants who were at genetic high-risk for schizophrenia and controls (n=244). The teacher-rated social functioning scale significantly predicted psychiatric outcomes (schizophrenia-spectrum vs. other psychiatric disorder vs. no mental illness). Poor premorbid social functioning appears to constitute a marker of illness vulnerability and may also function as a chronic stressor potentially exacerbating risk for illness.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critique of the Schizophrenia Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-the-schizophrenia-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 05:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-the-schizophrenia-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In January 2014, the journal Research on Social Work Practice ran a special issue called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rsw.sagepub.com/content/24/1.toc&#34;&gt;A Critical Appraisal of the DSM-5: Social Work Perspectives&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt; There are fifteen articles on this general theme, and together they present a wide range of arguments against the DSM system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social workers represent the numerically biggest group of mental health practitioners in the US, and it is particularly gratifying to see a major social work journal addressing this topic so forthrightly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Blood Test for Schizophrenia with 83% Accuracy?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-blood-test-for-schizophrenia-with-83-accuracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 05:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-blood-test-for-schizophrenia-with-83-accuracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An NBC online News article dated October 15, 2010, carried the noteworthy title &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nbcnews.com/id/39686973/ns/health-mental_health/t/new-blood-test-may-help-detect-schizophrenia/#.UxVbXvldXwl&#34;&gt;New blood test may help detect schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Thanks to Francesca for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article was written by Natasha Allen, a freelance medical journalist.  The gist of the article is that there is a new blood test called VeriPsych which &amp;ldquo;researchers say&amp;rdquo; is 83% accurate in discriminating people who are &amp;ldquo;schizophrenic&amp;rdquo; from people who are not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genetic Protection Against Schizophrenia?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/genetic-protection-against-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 05:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/genetic-protection-against-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On November 12, 2013, Molecular Psychiatry published online &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/mp/journal/v19/n1/pdf/mp2013156a.pdf&#34;&gt;Evidence that duplications of 22q11.2 protect against schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Rees et al.  The print version was published last month – January 2014.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the authors&amp;rsquo; summary:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;A number of large, rare copy number variants (CNVs) are deleterious for neurodevelopmental disorders, but large, rare, protective CNVs have not been reported for such phenotypes. Here we show in a CNV analysis of 47 005 individuals, the largest CNV analysis of schizophrenia to date, that large duplications (1.5–3.0 Mb) at 22q11.2—the reciprocal of the well-known, risk-inducing deletion of this locus—are substantially less common in schizophrenia cases than in the general population (0.014% vs. 0.085%, OR=0.17, P=0.00086). 22q11.2 duplications represent the first putative protective mutation for schizophrenia.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Research</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 05:57:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Psychiatric News is the APA&amp;rsquo;s online bulletin.  On Jan 15, it ran an article by Vabren Watts (an APA staff writer).  The article is called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1814750&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;APA Gives Schizophrenia Research Capitol Hill Spotlight&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;It is reported in the article that on December 12, 2013, the APA, together with the Congressional Neuroscience Caucus and the American Brain Coalition, made a joint presentation to legislators and their staffs on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Childhood Abuse in Development of &#34;Schizophrenia&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/role-of-childhood-abuse-in-development-of-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2013 05:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/role-of-childhood-abuse-in-development-of-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been some discussion in recent weeks concerning the role of childhood abuse in the etiology of the condition known as schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is particularly difficult to address this problem because the condition known as schizophrenia is not a unified phenomenon.  Rather, it is an assortment of loosely clustered behaviors which has been falsely and illogically labeled by the APA as an illness, existing in an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question &amp;ldquo;Is schizophrenia caused by childhood abuse?&amp;rdquo; is a meaningless question. In other words, it cannot be answered either as &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;false.&amp;rdquo;  In fact, it can&amp;rsquo;t even be answered &amp;ldquo;maybe.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talk Therapy for Schizophrenia</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 21:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Vermont&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Seven Days&lt;/i&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Burlington&amp;rsquo;s HowardCenter Tries a New Approach to Treating Mental Illness: More Talk, Fewer Meds.&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.7dvt.com/2013burlingtons-howardcenter-tries-new-approach-treating-mental-illness-more-talking-fewer-meds&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Steven_Coles_&#34;&gt;Steven Coles&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently Vermont&amp;rsquo;s Department of Mental Health is promoting a &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; kind of treatment for psychosis:  talk therapy.  The project leader is Dr. Sandra Steingard, who for most of her career accepted the orthodox view of schizophrenia and the need for neuroleptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;You must take these pills for life.&#34;  Or is it for death?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/you-must-take-these-pills-for-life-or-is-it-for-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 09:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/you-must-take-these-pills-for-life-or-is-it-for-death/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an important article (&lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2013/05/07/interview-john-nash/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) on Monica Cassani&amp;rsquo;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/&#34;&gt;BeyondMeds&lt;/a&gt; in which she tackles the myth that once a person has been assigned a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of schizophrenia, he/she must take neuroleptics for life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Unfortunately, at this juncture in history many people who get labeled with psychiatric illness these days do not have the opportunity for recovery because they are encouraged to stay ill by a system that all too often impedes psychological growth by use of excessive psychotropic drugs. This over-use of medication also kills people. The average life-span of people taking these medications is 25 years shorter than people who do not take these drugs. The drugs cause a long laundry list of problems only some of which are diabetes, obesity, heart conditions and a shrinking brain.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics Increase the Risk of Osteoporosis</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-increase-the-risk-of-osteoporosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2013 09:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-increase-the-risk-of-osteoporosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all known for a long time that neuroleptic drugs damage brain cells.  But now it seems clear that they also &lt;strong&gt;increase the risk of osteoporosis and consequently bone fractures&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an article about this in the International Journal of Endocrinology, dated March 2013.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Osteoporosis-Associated-with-Antipsychotic-Treatment-in-Schizophrenia.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Osteoporosis Associated with Antipsychotic Treatment in Schizophrenia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was written by Haishan Wu et al, from the Central South University in Changsha, China.  I came upon the article through Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s site &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Two Short Stories</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 08:25:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First story&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 70&amp;rsquo;s I worked in Grendon Prison in England.  The facility was run on the lines of a therapeutic community – lots of meetings, groups, etc&amp;hellip;  One of the prisoners – let&amp;rsquo;s call him William – was serving time for burglary.  He was about 24 years old, and during his intake interviews he told us that he was a member of a small quasi-religious sect who believed that doomsday was imminent and that they would be the chosen few.  He talked about these matters openly and with a good measure of passion, and after a few weeks the other prisoners were describing him as &amp;ldquo;crazy&amp;rdquo; and a &amp;ldquo;nutcase.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Involuntary Commitment – A Case Study</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/involuntary-commitment-a-case-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 15:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/involuntary-commitment-a-case-study/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Years ago I was director of a county mental health center in an Eastern state.  Shortly after taking the position, I became concerned that &lt;strong&gt;clients were being involuntarily committed too readily&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;without exploration of other options&lt;/strong&gt;.  I issued an instruction that all such activity had to be approved by a middle manager before it could proceed.  This measure aroused enormous resistance from the front-line staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one client – let&amp;rsquo;s call him Charlie – who was committed to the State Hospital every year, usually in July.  Every July, he would become &amp;ldquo;agitated,&amp;rdquo; would scream profanities at his elderly mother, and break things around the house.  He carried a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muddled Thinking and Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until just a few years ago, the spurious nature of mental illness received little or no attention either in professional circles or in the general media. There were a few of us &amp;ldquo;cranks&amp;rdquo; who poked away at the issue, but peer condemnation was usually swift and outspoken.  On one occasion I was called an &amp;ldquo;anti-science Nazi&amp;rdquo; for daring to suggest that the condition known as ADHD might have more to do with ineffective parental discipline than with brain chemistry.  We were voices in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – the Pseudoscience</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 15:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-pseudoscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As most readers of this website are aware, there is a great deal of resistance to the soon-to-be-released DSM-5.  There is even a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/dsm-5-boycott-launched/&#34;&gt;Boycott DSM-5 Committee &lt;/a&gt;established by Jack Carney, and many people are suggesting that practitioners use the World Health Organization&amp;rsquo;s (WHO&amp;rsquo;s) International Classification of Diseases (ICD) instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the general context of this debate, I have come across an article by Philip Thomas, M.D. – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/pinball-wizards-and-the-doomed-project-of-psychiatric-diagnosis/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pinball Wizards and the Doomed Project of Psychiatric Diagnosis.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  Dr. Thomas points out that &amp;ldquo;…it’s hard to imagine that the criticisms raised about DSM-5 won’t also apply to the ICD.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Mental Illness&#34; and Genes</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-and-genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 11:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-and-genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jay Joseph, PhD has posted an interesting piece: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/02/five-decades-of-gene-finding-failures-in-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Five Decades of Gene Finding Failures in Psychiatry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; (Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s site).  It is well worth a read.  The general content of the article is clear from the title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Two generations of molecular genetic researchers have attempted, yet failed, to discover the genes that they believe underlie the major psychiatric disorders.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite the sequencing of the human genome and the publication of more than 1,700 schizophrenia molecular genetic studies, we have witnessed over 40 years of gene finding claims, and over 40 years of subsequently non-replicated findings.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 18:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late adolescence and early adulthood is arguably the most difficult period of life.  Transitioning from childhood to adulthood entails many challenges.  The young person (male or female) is expected to emancipate successfully from parents; launch a career; and find a partner – all in the space of a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some individuals cope remarkably well.  Others squeak through, and a small minority “crash and burn.”  The latter group usually return home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Label - Damaging and Dangerous</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-label---damaging-and-dangerous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2012 11:03:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-label---damaging-and-dangerous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s an interesting article&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2012/12/22844/&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Inquiry into the Schizophrenia Label (ISL) &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;on Robert Whitaker’s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently Philip Thomas, M.D. and other researchers have been asking mental health clients how they perceived the &lt;strong&gt;schizophrenia label.&lt;/strong&gt;  They received nearly 500 responses, and found that &lt;em&gt;more than 80%&lt;/em&gt; of responders described the label as &lt;strong&gt;damaging and dangerous.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They question the validity and usefulness of the “diagnosis” and tentatively suggest that it may need to be discarded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cinema Shooting – Psychiatric Defense</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cinema-shooting-psychiatric-defense/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2012 08:33:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cinema-shooting-psychiatric-defense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was widely reported last week that James Holmes, the alleged cinema shooter, will be pursuing a “mental illness” defense.  Details are scarce because the judge has issued a gag order, but it is likely, given the available information, that the lawyers will argue that because of his psychiatric history he is incompetent to stand trial.  It is also likely that they will bring in some eminent psychiatrist(s) who will confirm his “diagnosis” and claim that at the time of the offense he didn’t know what he was doing, or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM and Disability</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-and-disability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every society in every generation makes errors.  Some of the errors are minor.  Some are major.  One of the great errors of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century was this:  we accepted the spurious notion that a wide range of life’s problems were in fact &lt;em&gt;illnesses&lt;/em&gt;.  This spurious notion was initiated with good intentions – to provide shelter and humanitarian care for a relatively small number of individuals whose plight was truly dreadful.  But then the concept of mental illness took off, fuelled largely by the efforts of psychiatrists to legitimize their status as “real” doctors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Is Not An Illness (Part 3)</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2010 18:41:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Hallucinations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Schizophrenia Part 1, we noted that the APA lists hallucinations as one of the primary “symptoms” of schizophrenia.  The APA defines an hallucination as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“A sensory perception that has the compelling sense of reality of a true perception but that occurs without external stimulation of the relevant sensory organ.” (DSM-IV-TR, p 823)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In other words: seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, or feeling something that isn’t really there.  Typically the individual who has been “diagnosed” with schizophrenia reports that he hears voices that accuse him of some wrong or exhort him to some action, and sometimes threaten him with punishment or retribution.
&lt;p&gt;A number of points need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Is Not an Illness (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2010 09:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Delusions, contd.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last post I pointed out that schizophrenia as defined by DSM is a confusing collection of human problems with no evidence of a common etiology or indeed any valid justification for including them under a common heading.  I discussed delusions and made the point that cognitive distortions of this kind are a normal response to failure.  When the experience of failure is profound and pervasive, the delusional speech tends to be commensurately extreme.  Delusions are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; symptomatic of an underlying illness, but rather are a normal human reaction to severe stress or profound failure, particularly in the late teens/early adulthood phase of life.  This is the time of life in which our general coping skills are subjected to their first serious tests, and when people experience profound failure at this time, there is a risk that they will drift towards delusional speech.  Onset of delusional speech is typically &lt;a href=&#34;http://bjp.rcpsych.org/cgi/content/abstract/162/1/80&#34;&gt;later for women&lt;/a&gt; than men, and probably corresponds with the process of giving birth and caring for small children.  The potential for strong feelings of failure is high at this point of life also.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Is Not An Illness (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2010 19:35:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-is-not-an-illness-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: normal; font-size: 13px;&#34;&gt;The APA defines schizophrenia by the presence of two or more of the following, each present for a significant portion of time during a one-month period:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1)   delusions
(2)   hallucinations
(3)   disorganized speech
(4)   grossly disorganized or catatonic behavior
(5)   negative symptoms i.e. affective flattening, alogia or avolition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signs of the disturbance must have been present for at least six months and there must be significant deficits in one or more areas of functioning such as work, interpersonal relations or self-care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
