<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Books Worth Reading on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/books-worth-reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books Worth Reading on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 05:30:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/books-worth-reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry Interrogated&lt;/em&gt;, (ed. Bonnie Burstow), Palgrave Macmillan:  A Book Review</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/em-psychiatry-interrogated-em-ed-bonnie-burstow-palgrave-macmillan-a-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 05:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/em-psychiatry-interrogated-em-ed-bonnie-burstow-palgrave-macmillan-a-book-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read &lt;em&gt;Psychiatry Interrogated&lt;/em&gt;, subtitled &amp;ldquo;An Institutional Ethnography Anthology&amp;rdquo;&lt;em&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;Ethnography is the branch of anthropology that deals with the systematic study of individual cultures.&lt;em&gt;  Institutional&lt;/em&gt; ethnography (IE), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institutional_ethnography&#34;&gt;according to Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, is  &amp;ldquo;a method of social research [that]… explores the social relations that structure people&amp;rsquo;s everyday lives, specifically by looking at the ways that people interact with one another in the context of social institutions (school, marriage, work, for example) and understanding how those interactions are institutionalized…For the institutional ethnographer, ordinary daily activity becomes the site for an investigation of social organization.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Power of the Double Circle</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-the-power-of-the-double-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-the-power-of-the-double-circle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read &lt;em&gt;The Power of the Double Circle&lt;/em&gt; by Philip Springer, MD, and Shelby Havens, DNP.  It&amp;rsquo;s a small book (91 pages), but it sets out an idea that might have some value in support/self-help and other kinds of groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Springer is a retired psychiatrist, and Dr. Havens is a psychiatric nurse practitioner, but their position as set out in the book is something close to anti-psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  &lt;b&gt;Depression Delusion&lt;/b&gt;, by Terry Lynch, MD, MA</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-depression-delusion-b-by-terry-lynch-md-ma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 05:30:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-depression-delusion-b-by-terry-lynch-md-ma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this truly remarkable, and meticulously researched, volume, Dr. Lynch annihilates psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s cherished chemical imbalance theory of depression.  Every facet of this theory, which the author correctly calls a delusion, is critically analyzed and found wanting.  Example after example is provided of psychiatrists promoting this fiction, the factual and logical errors of which are clearly exposed in Dr. Lynch&amp;rsquo;s lucid, seamless, and highly readable prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book runs to 343 pages, and is laden with factual details, case studies, alternative perspectives, and hard-hitting commentary.  Dr. Lynch does not sit on the sidelines, nor does he seek any kind of collegial compromise with the chemical imbalance theory, which he unambiguously denounces as a groundless and destructive falsehood.  Here are some quotes that I think will convey something of the content, style, and cogency of this vitally important work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  &lt;b&gt;Parenting Your Child with ADHD: A No-Nonsense Guide for Nurturing Self-Reliance and Cooperation&lt;/b&gt;, by Craig Wiener, EdD</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-parenting-your-child-with-adhd-a-no-nonsense-guide-for-nurturing-self-reliance-and-coo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 05:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-b-parenting-your-child-with-adhd-a-no-nonsense-guide-for-nurturing-self-reliance-and-coo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read this book, and I think it would be extremely helpful for parents, teachers, and counselors who work with children in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…ADHD [is] something that your child does rather than something that she &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt;.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The first thing to realize is that while you and other adults see your child’s ADHD behavior as a problem to overcome, for your child, ADHD behavior holds &lt;em&gt;solutions&lt;/em&gt; to the difficulties that he faces on a daily basis. When your child encounters adversity, ADHD behavior somehow mitigates the situation. When you identify what gives his ADHD behavior its staying power, you will have gained valuable insight into why such behavior repeats so frequently. You will also be taking a giant step forward in knowing how to eliminate it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  &lt;strong&gt;Tales From The Madhouse&lt;/strong&gt;, by Gary Sidley</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-strong-tales-from-the-madhouse-strong-by-gary-sidley/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 05:30:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-strong-tales-from-the-madhouse-strong-by-gary-sidley/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year the British publisher PCCS Books published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales From The Madhouse&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;An insider critique of psychiatric services&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Gary Sidley.  Gary worked for thirty-three years in the British NHS mental health service.  He has held positions as a psychiatric nurse, a manager, and a clinical psychologist.  He is currently a freelance writer and trainer.  His present focus is the promotion of alternatives to biological psychiatry in the alleviation of human suffering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  &lt;strong&gt;Psychiatry and the Business of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;An Ethical and Epistemological Accounting&lt;/em&gt;, by Bonnie Burstow</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-strong-psychiatry-and-the-business-of-madness-strong-em-an-ethical-and-epistemological-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-strong-psychiatry-and-the-business-of-madness-strong-em-an-ethical-and-epistemological-a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This latest book by Bonnie Burstow, PhD, critiques psychiatry, and effectively annihilates any claims that the profession might have had to legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonnie gives us a scholarly, but very readable, account of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the history of psychiatry, ancient and modern;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the significance and shortcomings of the DSM;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the legal, ethical, and personal ramifications of involuntary &#34;treatment&#34;;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the training of psychiatrists and the dynamics underlying their uncritical acceptance of their profession&#39;s spurious concepts and destructive treatments;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the ways in which non-psychiatrist mental health workers are co-opted into the system, and become, often despite good intentions, supporters and active participants in the psychiatric travesty;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the role and tactics of the psycho-pharma industry;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the stark, destructive, degrading realities of electric shock &#34;treatment&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
In the final chapter, Bonnie offers us a glimpse of what an alternative approach might look like.
&lt;p&gt;Normally when I write a book review, I include some quotes from the work to enable readers to judge for themselves the quality and content of the material.  With &lt;em&gt;Psychiatry and the Business of Madness,&lt;/em&gt; however, this presented a problem, in that virtually every one of the 264 pages of text contains eminently quotable material.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a short sample:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  A Disease Called Childhood, by Marilyn Wedge</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-a-disease-called-childhood-by-marilyn-wedge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-a-disease-called-childhood-by-marilyn-wedge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Avery, a member of Penguin Group USA, has recently published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Disease Called Childhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Marilyn Wedge.  Marilyn has a PhD in psychology and works as a family therapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, fully 11% of American children had received a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).  It is widely believed by these children, their parents, the press, the public, and government agencies, that this loose collection of vaguely defined behaviors constitutes an illness – specifically a chemical imbalance in the brain, which is corrected by stimulant drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review:  Body Dysmorphic Disorder:  The Illusion,  by Zoe Wybrant</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-body-dysmorphic-disorder-the-illusion-by-zoe-wybrant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/book-review-body-dysmorphic-disorder-the-illusion-by-zoe-wybrant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Body Dysmorphic Disorder is one of the so-called mental disorders listed in the DSM-5.  The manual lists the following  diagnostic criteria, (p 242):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;A.  Preoccupation with one or more perceived defects or flaws in physical appearance that are not observable or appear slight to others.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;B.  At some point during the course of the disorder, the individual has performed repetitive behaviors (e.g., mirror checking, excessive grooming, skin picking, reassurance seeking) or mental acts (e.g., comparing his or her appearance with that of others ) in response to the appearance concerns.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;C.  The preoccupation causes clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;D.  The appearance preoccupation is not better explained by concerns with body fat or weight in an individual whose symptoms meet diagnostic criteria for an eating disorder.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Body Dysmorphic Disorder:  The Illusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, discusses this &#34;disorder&#34; from the perspective of someone who has struggled with these issues herself.  Zoe challenges the usefulness of diagnosis and standard psychiatric treatment – and provides an abundance of clearly-stated contributory factors, together with suggestions for self-help.
&lt;p&gt;The book reads nicely, and would be helpful for anyone who is troubled with these kinds of concerns, or for therapists/counselors who encounter these kinds of issues in their work.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Straight Talk from Lucy Johnstone</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/straight-talk-from-lucy-johnstone/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 05:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/straight-talk-from-lucy-johnstone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PCCS Books Ltd has recently published &lt;em&gt;A Straight Talking Introduction to Psychiatric Diagnosis,&lt;/em&gt; by Lucy Johnstone, PhD.  Lucy is a consultant psychologist working in Wales, and has been an outspoken critic of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s medical model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…my own conclusion, based on extensive reading and clinical work and many enlightening discussions with service users, is that psychiatric diagnosis is not a valid or evidence-based way of understanding the difficulties and distress that people experience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Disrupted</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-disrupted/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-disrupted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On August 15, 2014, McGill-Queens University Press published &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry Disrupted: Theorizing Resistance and Crafting the (R)evolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  The work is a collection of papers by various authors, edited by Bonnie Burstow, Brenda A. LeFrançois, and Shaindl Diamond.  There is a Foreword by Paula Caplan, and a Preface by Kate Millett.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that there is growing opposition to psychiatry.  No longer marginalized and ignored, as in former decades, anti-psychiatry writers are proclaiming psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s spurious and destructive nature in a wide range of venues.  Even the mainstream media is taking tentative steps in our direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Prescription for Psychiatry, by Peter Kinderman, PhD</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-prescription-for-psychiatry-by-peter-kinderman-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 05:30:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-prescription-for-psychiatry-by-peter-kinderman-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently read Peter Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s new book, &lt;em&gt;A Prescription for Psychiatry, &lt;/em&gt;which was published on September 3 by Palgrave Macmillan.  The overall message of the work is captured nicely in the subtitle:  Why We Need a Whole New Approach to Mental Health and Wellbeing.  Dr. Kinderman is Professor of Clinical Psychology, Head of the Institute of Psychology, Health and Society at the University of Liverpool, and an honorary Consultant Clinical Psychologist with Mersey Care NHS Trust in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Our Children:  A Book Review</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-our-children-a-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 05:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-our-children-a-book-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Drugging-Our-Children-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4320&#34; alt=&#34;Drugging Our Children &#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Drugging-Our-Children-2-233x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;163&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The 2012 book &lt;em&gt;Drugging Our Children: How Profiteers Are Pushing Antipsychotics on Our Youngest, and What We Can Do to Stop It&lt;/em&gt;, is edited by Sharna Olfman PhD, and Brent Dean Robbins, PhD.  It is a collection of ten articles, plus an Introduction and an Afterword by Sharna Olfman.  Here are the chapter titles, with a quote from each:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Introduction&lt;/i&gt;, by Sharna Olfman, PhD&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sandcastle Continues to Crumble:  ADHD Does Not Exist</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 05:48:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;BOOK PREVIEW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Richard C. Saul, MD
&lt;em&gt;ADHD Does Not Exist:  The Truth About Attention Deficit and Hyperactivity Disorder&lt;/em&gt;
Publication date:  February 18, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;************************&lt;/p&gt;
Those of us on this side of the psychiatry debate have been saying for decades that the condition known as ADHD is not an illness, but is rather an arbitrarily delineated cluster of vaguely defined problems that children have acquired in various ways.  We have also pointed out that psychiatry&#39;s labeling of this condition as an illness is simply another instance of their inexorable turf expansion, and that their widespread drugging of the individuals so labeled is destructive and disempowering.
&lt;p&gt;And, also for decades, psychiatry has been marginalizing us as unscientific mental illness deniers, who seek to put the clock back and deprive people suffering from this &amp;ldquo;illness&amp;rdquo; of the vital &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; that they so desperately need.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bitterest Pills, by Joanna Moncrieff: Another Book Worth Reading</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bitterest-pills-by-joanna-moncrieff-another-book-worth-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 05:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bitterest-pills-by-joanna-moncrieff-another-book-worth-reading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Joanna Moncrieff is a UK psychiatrist and a founding member of the Critical Psychiatry Network.  In 2009 she wrote &lt;em&gt;The Myth of the Chemical Cure: A Critique of Psychiatric Drug Treatment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/The-Bitterest-Pills-joanna-moncrieff.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-4323 aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;The Bitterest Pills-joanna-moncrieff&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/The-Bitterest-Pills-joanna-moncrieff-191x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;115&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Her latest book,&lt;em&gt; The Bitterest Pills,&lt;/em&gt; was published earlier this year, and is about neuroleptic drugs (the so-called anti-psychotics).  You can get an idea of the tenor and scope of the work from the table of contents:
&lt;ol start=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Curse or Cure:  What Are Antipsychotics?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chlorpromazine:  The First Wonder Drug&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Magic Bullets:  The Development of Ideas on Drug Action&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Building a House of Cards:  The Dopamine Theory of Schizophrenia and Drug Action&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Phoenix Rises:  From Tardive Dyskinesia to the Introduction of &#39;Atypicals&#39;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Looking Where the Light Is:  Randomised Controlled Trials of Antipsychotics&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Patient&#39;s Dilemma:  Other Evidence on the Effects of Antipsychotics&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chemical Cosh:  Antipsychotics and Chemical Restraint&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Old and New Drug-induced Problems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The First Tentacles:  The &#39;Early Intervention in Psychosis&#39; Movement&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Antipsychotic Epidemic:  Prescribing in the Twenty-first Century&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;All is not as it Seems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
There are 39 pages of references at the back.
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Critique of Psychiatry&#39;s Medical Model</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 06:15:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-critique-of-psychiatry-s-medical-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read &lt;i&gt;De-Medicalizing Misery&lt;/i&gt; [palgrave macmillan, 2011].  It&amp;rsquo;s a comprehensive collection of articles, edited by Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon.  The table of contents provides a sense of the book&amp;rsquo;s scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Carving Nature at its Joints?  DSM and the Medicalization of Everyday Life&lt;/i&gt;, Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dualisms and the Myth of Mental Illness&lt;/i&gt;, Philip Thomas and Patrick Bracken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Making the World Go Away, and How Psychology and Psychiatry Benefit&lt;/i&gt;, Mary Boyle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cultural Diversity and Racism: An Historical Perspective&lt;/i&gt;, Suman Fernando&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Social Context of Paranoia&lt;/i&gt;, David J. Harper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;From Bad Character to BPD: The Medicalization of &#39;Personality Disorder&#39;&lt;/i&gt;, James Bourne&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Medicalizing Masculinity&lt;/i&gt;, Sami Timimi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Can Traumatic Events Traumatize People?  Trauma, Madness, and Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Lucy Johnstone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children Who Witness Violence at Home&lt;/i&gt;, Arlene Vetere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Discourses of Acceptance and Resistance:  Speaking Out about Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, Ewen Speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Personal &lt;/i&gt;is&lt;i&gt; The Political&lt;/i&gt;, Jacqui Dillon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;&#39;I&#39;m Just, You Know, Joe Bloggs&#39;:  The Management of Parental Responsibility for First-episode Psychosis&lt;/i&gt;, Carlton Coulter and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Myth of the Antidepressant:  An Historical Analysis&lt;/i&gt;, Joanna Moncrieff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Antidepressants and the Placebo Response&lt;/i&gt;, Irving Kirsch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Why Were Doctors So Slow to Recognize Antidepressant Discontinuation Problems?&lt;/i&gt; Duncan Double&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Toxic Psychology&lt;/i&gt;, Craig Newnes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychotherapy:  Illusion with No Future?&lt;/i&gt; David Smail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Psychologization of Torture&lt;/i&gt;, Nimisha Patel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;What Is to Be Done? &lt;/i&gt;Joanna Moncrieff, Jacqui Dillon, and Mark Rapley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Each author brings to the general topic his or her unique perspectives, and the result is persuasive and inspiring.
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from the final chapter:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Corruption of Healthcare</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-corruption-of-healthcare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 09:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-corruption-of-healthcare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading another great book:  &lt;i&gt;Deadly Medicines and Organised Crime: How big pharma has corrupted healthcare&lt;/i&gt;, by Peter C. Gotzsche [Radcliffe Publishing, 2013].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is an exposé of pharma&amp;rsquo;s fraudulent research and marketing.  The author is a Danish physician who has been involved in clinical trials of drugs, and in drug regulatory matters.  He is a professor at the University of Copenhagen.  He has published more than 50 papers, including papers in the BMJ, Lancet, JAMA, Annals of Internal Medicine, and the New England Journal of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cracked: The Unhappy Truth About Psychiatry, by James Davies, PhD: Book Review</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cracked-the-unhappy-truth-about-psychiatry-by-james-davies-phd-book-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 05:55:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cracked-the-unhappy-truth-about-psychiatry-by-james-davies-phd-book-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an excellent book, published by Pegasus Books earlier this year.  The cover blurb says that it is &amp;ldquo;…scathing about every aspect of psychiatry.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Davies, who is a practicing therapist in the UK, brings to the subject enormous energy and enthusiasm.  He has interviewed Robert Spitzer, Allen Frances, Irving Kirsch, Joanna Moncrieff, Sami Tamimi, Peter Breggin, and many, many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the points he makes will be familiar to those of us on this side of the debate, but there is an enormous amount of fresh material and insights.  The book careens, almost literally, from one psychiatric outrage to the next, and the arguments are supported by appropriate citations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Madness Contested: An Outstanding Book</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 06:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested &lt;/i&gt;has recently been published by PCCS Books.  It&amp;rsquo;s a collection of articles, edited by Steven Coles, Sarah Keenan, and Bob Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a remarkable piece of work.  It covers just about every contentious concept in the present &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; debate, and brings to bear an abundance of new insights and up-to-date research findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 21 articles plus an introduction by the editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the name of each article with a brief quotation from each:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survivor&#39;s Story:  The Dark Threads</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 09:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just read &lt;em&gt;The Dark Threads,&lt;/em&gt; by Jean Davison (Accent Press Ltd, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s autobiographical, and describes with great detail and insight how a young woman of 18 years, whose only problem was acute shyness coupled with a yearning for some meaning in life, made the mistake of visiting a psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jean describes how she was &lt;strong&gt;bullied into accepting psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; She was &lt;strong&gt;drugged into a zombie-like stupor and given electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;  &lt;/strong&gt;She describes graphically the disempowering and humiliating aspects of &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; and the endless patronizing condescension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock &#34;Treatment&#34; Is Not Safe and Provides Little If Any Benefit</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 09:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/shock-treatment-is-not-safe-and-provides-little-if-any-benefit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DELICATE THINGS REQUIRE DELICATE HANDLING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, one of my hobbies was making small transistor radios.  It sounds complicated, but is well within the reach of an average 15-year-old.  You get some magazine articles, learn how to read a circuit, and learn how to use a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transistor is a small device – about half the size of a pencil eraser – with three wires coming out of it.  In building a radio receiver, the transistors have to be soldered to other devices which are in turn soldered to other devices, etc…  The soldering iron is plugged into a wall outlet, but no mains electricity reaches the tip of the iron.  However, tiny eddy currents can circulate in the tip, and although they are only of the order of &lt;i&gt;milliamps&lt;/i&gt;, they can burn a transistor in seconds.  What you have to do is unplug the iron from the socket, make the joint with the tip&amp;rsquo;s retained heat, and then replug the iron to have it ready for the next joint.  The point being that &lt;i&gt;delicate things require delicate handling&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;strong&gt;electricity can be very destructive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Prescription Drugs Associated with Reports of Violence Towards Others&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 12:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/prescription-drugs-associated-with-reports-of-violence-towards-others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the title of a 2010 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0015337&#34;&gt;research report &lt;/a&gt;by Thomas J. Moore, Joseph Glenmullen, and Curt D. Furberg, published in PLOS One, an online peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of the study searched the FDA&amp;rsquo;s Adverse Event Reporting System from 2004 to September 2009, and flagged reports indicating violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They concluded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Acts of violence towards others are a genuine and serious adverse drug event associated with a relatively small group of drugs.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Pharma, by Ben Goldacre</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 23:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bad-pharma-by-ben-goldacre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All the awful things you&amp;rsquo;ve heard and read about the pharmaceutical companies are documented on the pages of &lt;i&gt;Bad Pharma&lt;/i&gt; with compelling clarity and abundant references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Goldacre is a British physician.  His primary issue is the safety and efficacy of pharmaceutical products in general medicine, but he has a lot to say about psychiatric drugs also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drugs are tested by the people who manufacture them, in poorly designed trials, on hopelessly small numbers of weird, unrepresentative patients, and analysed using techniques which are flawed by design, in such a way that they exaggerate the benefits of treatments.&#34;(p. x)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Important Book</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-important-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 09:44:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-important-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/De-medicalizing-Misery.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4326&#34; alt=&#34;De-medicalizing-Misery&#34; src=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/De-medicalizing-Misery-300x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De-Medicalizing Misery&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Mark Rapley, Joanna Moncrieff, and Jacqui Dillon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a collection of papers by various authors, most of whom have experience working with clients and are also associated with prestigious British universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“The architects of modern biological psychiatry have constructed a system that does little justice to the myriad problems it claims to address, while creating multiple iatrogenic problems for those to whom it is applied.” (p 1)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Book by Stephen Ray Flora</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-book-by-stephen-ray-flora/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 23:21:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-book-by-stephen-ray-flora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I recommended &lt;em&gt;Taking America Off Drugs&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen Ray Flora.  Well, he has also written &lt;em&gt;The Power of Reinforcement&lt;/em&gt; (State University of New York Press, 2004), and this also is well worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement is a crucial concept in psychology, and in this book Dr. Flora clarifies the matter and dispels the misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy it; read it; keep it close.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Book</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2012 22:09:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taking America Off Drugs&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen Ray Flora&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago,&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2011/12/28/forensic-psychiatry/#.Txzc-W8V3a8&#34;&gt; in a comment&lt;/a&gt;, A Behaviorist Fan recommended the above book to me.  It came out in 2007, and I don’t know how I missed it at the time.  But I’ve read it now and it’s a superb piece of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely a &lt;em&gt;must buy&lt;/em&gt; and must keep close at hand.  Stephen analyses the various “diagnoses” listed in DSM.  He points out their behavioral nature, and describes how they can be ameliorated with relatively simple behavioral techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Interesting Book</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-interesting-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 10:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-interesting-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unhinged, by Daniel Carlat, MD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Carlat is a psychiatrist who has written something of an exposé of the abuses that reside within the psychiatric profession.  Many of his chapters echo topics that have been addressed frequently on this blog.  Dr. Carlat still clings to the notion that problem behaviors can be accurately conceptualized as illnesses, but he does criticize the proliferation of “diagnoses” and the application of these “diagnoses” to increasing numbers of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugs, Placebos, and Life</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugs-placebos-and-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2010 18:53:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugs-placebos-and-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently read a very interesting book by Irving Kirsch, PhD.  It’s called &lt;i&gt;The Emperor’s New Drugs&lt;/i&gt;, and the central theme of the work is that antidepressants are only very slightly more effective than placebos (i.e. sugar pills), and that the difference is not clinically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic is cogent and the research is rigorous.  Read the book and decide for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kirsch argues in favor of psychotherapy as a substitute for pills.  And certainly talking is usually helpful.  However, as long as depression is conceptualized as an illness, I don’t believe we will see real progress in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The So-Called Mental Illnesses Are Not Illnesses</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 19:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this blog is that mental illness is a spurious and invalid concept, which is promoted and developed by the American Psychiatric Association to legitimize the use of mood-altering drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that people display various problems in their daily lives and particularly in their interpersonal relationships.  The American Psychiatric Association claims that all such problems are caused by mental illness and their list of these so-called illnesses is so long that virtually anybody can be embraced within their coils.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
