<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Major Tranquilizers on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/major-tranquilizers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Major Tranquilizers on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/major-tranquilizers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tardive Dyskinesia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tardive-dyskinesia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 09:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tardive-dyskinesia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the late 80&amp;rsquo;s, I worked for a while in an addictions unit that was located on the grounds of a State Hospital in West Virginia.  Clients would arrive on 72-hour holding committals from the counties, and if the psychiatrist felt that the client needed to stay longer than that (which was almost always the case), then either the client had to convert to voluntary status, which is what happened in most cases, or the hospital had to arrange for a hearing in front of a judge.  For convenience, a local judge would come in and the hearing would be held in the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
