<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Trichotillomania on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/trichotillomania/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trichotillomania on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2009 12:09:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/trichotillomania/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Can They Just Invent Illnesses?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-they-just-invent-illnesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2009 12:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-they-just-invent-illnesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The notion of a professional group such as the APA sitting in their councils and committees inventing illnesses for themselves to treat seems so preposterous that a measure of disbelief on the part of the reader is understandable.  In its historical context, however, the development is not so surprising.  The original 1952 DSM was very simple and unpretentious, and whilst part of the APA’s motivation in drafting the document was undoubtedly to draw some credibility and respectability to their profession, there is at the same time nothing to suggest any great drive at that time towards aggrandizement or service expansion.  However, having agreed in 1952 that neurosis was a form of mental disorder, it was inevitable that subsequent revisions of the manual would attempt to define this feature further and look for subdivisions of the general category.  This, of course, is exactly what has happened, and the current version of DSM lists literally dozens of disorders of this sort, although the general term neurosis is no longer used.  (For an interesting discussion of this matter, see Karen Franklin’s post at &lt;a href=&#34;http://forensicpsychologist.blogspot.com/2008/10/dsm-makeover-what-will-they-come-up.html&#34;&gt;In The News&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
