<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Delusions on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/delusions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Delusions on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 05:01:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/delusions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Delusions</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/delusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 05:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/delusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 defines delusions as &amp;ldquo;…fixed beliefs that are not amenable to change in the light of conflicting evidence.&amp;rdquo;  (p 87).  The manual lists six kinds of delusions:  persecutory; referential; grandiose; erotomanic; nihilistic; and somatic.  The APA provides another definition of delusions on p 819.  It&amp;rsquo;s substantially the same as the one above, but offers the additional varieties:  bizarre; delusional jealousy; mixed type; mood-congruent; mood-incongruent; of being controlled; thought broadcasting; and thought insertion.  Interestingly, nihilistic delusions are omitted from the second list.  These, we are told on page 87,  &amp;ldquo;…involve the conviction that a major catastrophe will occur.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Childhood Abuse in Development of &#34;Schizophrenia&#34;</title>
      <link>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/role-of-childhood-abuse-in-development-of-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2013 05:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/role-of-childhood-abuse-in-development-of-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been some discussion in recent weeks concerning the role of childhood abuse in the etiology of the condition known as schizophrenia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is particularly difficult to address this problem because the condition known as schizophrenia is not a unified phenomenon.  Rather, it is an assortment of loosely clustered behaviors which has been falsely and illogically labeled by the APA as an illness, existing in an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question &amp;ldquo;Is schizophrenia caused by childhood abuse?&amp;rdquo; is a meaningless question. In other words, it cannot be answered either as &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;false.&amp;rdquo;  In fact, it can&amp;rsquo;t even be answered &amp;ldquo;maybe.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
