<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Dealing With Problems of Daily Living on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/dealing-with-problems-of-daily-living/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dealing With Problems of Daily Living on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/dealing-with-problems-of-daily-living/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Blood Test for Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 07:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-blood-test-for-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of Talla Trialogue on Twitter, I have read an article by Shari Roan called &lt;i&gt;Blood Test for Depression Proves It&amp;rsquo;s Not All In Your Head&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.takepart.com/article/2013/01/25/major-depression-can-be-diagnosed-blood-test&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article appears to be an interview with Lonna Williams, the CEO of Ridge Diagnostics.  This company is reportedly introducing a blood test for depression.  The test is called MDDScore and is expected to cost $745.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article tells us that:  &amp;ldquo;You get a numerical score that suggests how likely it is that you have depression. Studies show that MDD Score is about as accurate at making a diagnosis as the most rigorous evaluations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative to the Medical Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-the-medical-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 13:41:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/an-alternative-to-the-medical-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Lucy Johnstone on twitter, I came across a chapter from Steven Coles&amp;rsquo; book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested&lt;/i&gt;.  The book was published in the UK in February 2013, but won&amp;rsquo;t be available in the US until September of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapter is called&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychminded.co.uk/news/news2013/april2013/proven-alternative-to-the-medical-model-in-mental-health-care.htm&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;A proven alternative to the medical model in mental health care?&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;  and describes the Leeds Survivor Led Crisis Service, which for twelve years has provided a &lt;strong&gt;genuine alternative to mainstream mental health services. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People Helping People</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/people-helping-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 21:51:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/people-helping-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things are changing in the mental health business.  People of various persuasions are attacking the medicalization of human problems on the grounds of spuriousness and destructiveness.  Others are drawing attention to the ineffectiveness of the drugs, the dangerous side-effects, and the corrupting links between psychiatrists and big pharma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the change that ultimately is going to have the greatest effect is the fact that more and more service users are shucking off the archaic legacy of silence and shame, and are telling their stories.  They are telling us that the &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; in many cases hurt them rather than helped, but more importantly, that they are now finding their way not through psychiatry, but through something much more powerful and effective:  &lt;i&gt;people &lt;/i&gt;helping &lt;i&gt;people!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Psychotropic Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 10:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytransformation.blogspot.com/2011/04/fishing-lessons-from-my-son.html#.UWBNjZOG0eU&#34;&gt;nice article at Involuntary Transformation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Nathan, poses a very interesting question:  since drugs cause damage to children and there are many better alternatives, &lt;strong&gt;why do so many parents choose the drug option&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan goes on to suggest that the reason lies in the effort that the pharmaceutical industry invests in marketing, and he calls for &amp;ldquo;…complete and total transparency in all Mental Health Services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Children Gives Them the Wrong Message</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 10:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The routine drugging of children for the ordinary problems of childhood is destructive for two reasons:  firstly because of the toxic effects of the pharmaceutical products, and secondly because it &lt;strong&gt;conveys to the child the message that drugs are an acceptable way to deal with life&amp;rsquo;s problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This latter kind of damage is graphically illustrated in a tragic NY Times article by Ted Gup.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/03/opinion/diagnosis-human.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Ted is a fellow of the Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freudian Psychoanalysis is Better than Drugs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 10:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I received a short comment from Ruth Elliot on my post&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/26/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/#.UVt4fZOG0eU&#34;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psychiatric &amp;ldquo;Diagnoses&amp;rdquo; for Children&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Ruth linked to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://claudiamgoldmd.blogspot.com/2013/01/towards-new-or-return-to-old-paradigm.html#comment-form&#34;&gt;article by Claudia Gold, MD&lt;/a&gt;.  Claudia is a Freudian psychoanalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ideological orientation is behavioral, and if you were to ask people in this business:  what is the opposite of a behaviorist? you would probably get the answer:  a Freudian psychoanalyst.  And vice versa.  They are two very different ways of conceptualizing human activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petition on Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting new article by Paula Caplan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/comedy-history-and-the-future-mental-disorder-labels&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It discusses the harmful effects of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the fact that because of these labels, people have lost their &amp;ldquo;… jobs, custody of children, health insurance, and the right to make decisions about their medical and legal affairs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paula also mentions a petition she created in December 2011 calling for &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Congressional Hearings about Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  The petition is still up. You can find it&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.change.org/petitions/everyone-who-cares-about-the-harm-done-by-psychiatric-diagnosis-endorse-the-call-for-congressional-hearings-about-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Withdrawal from Benzodiazepines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Important updates on this subject can be found at the posts listed at the bottom of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I&#39;ve recently come across an article by Matt Samet called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/social-vacuum/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Social Vacuum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It&#39;s dated March 2013, and was published on Robert Whitaker&#39;s website &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Matt had been taking a benzodiazepine for some time, and while on a tapering withdrawal, he experienced some distressing symptoms, including some acute social discomfort.  (For a full account of benzo withdrawal –&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benzodiazepine_withdrawal_syndrome&#34;&gt; click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and the Law</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 14:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this website is that there are no mental illnesses, and that the widespread medicalization of ordinary human problems is spurious and destructive.  These concepts have been around for decades, but in the last four or five years have &amp;ldquo;taken off,&amp;rdquo; and are finding a good deal of acceptance among practitioners, academics, clients, and the general public.  Change is in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A matter that is sometimes overlooked, however, is that the &lt;strong&gt;concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and its &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; by psychiatrists and other professionals is deeply embedded in the legal system of most states and countries&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Involuntary Commitment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 11:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent times a good deal of criticism has been directed towards the practice of involuntarily committing individuals to state and private mental hospitals.  Most of this criticism focuses on the lack of effective due process; conflicts of interest in the case of private facilities; and failure to adequately explore alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my view, all of these criticisms are valid, and warrant attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is another side to the story that is seldom aired outside the mental health centers.  A great many clients &lt;i&gt;like&lt;/i&gt; going to the mental hospital; they plan their trips in advance and &amp;ldquo;freak out&amp;rdquo; at the appointed time, knowing that the knee-jerk response of the mental health center will be a court-ordered admission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Call Yourself That:  The Harmful Effects of Negative Self-labeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/don-t-call-yourself-that-the-harmful-effects-of-negative-self-labeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 11:25:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/don-t-call-yourself-that-the-harmful-effects-of-negative-self-labeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we were young, most of us devoted a good deal of time and energy to squabbling with other children.  To the dismay of our parents, we because adept in the use of impolite language, and kept our stock of insulting words and phrases up-to-date.  As adults we are more socially sophisticated.  We no longer call one another rude names – at least not openly.  Tragically, however, many people go through their entire adult lives calling &lt;i&gt;themselves&lt;/i&gt; names, which although not as vulgar as the insults of childhood, are considerably more destructive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
