<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychiatric &#34;Spin&#34; on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/psychiatric-spin/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Psychiatric &#34;Spin&#34; on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 05:30:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/psychiatric-spin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Is Anti-Psychiatry Harmful?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/is-anti-psychiatry-harmful/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/is-anti-psychiatry-harmful/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On September 9, 2020, Jonathan Stea, PhD, Tyler Black, MD, and Joseph Pierre, MD, published a piece on MedPage Today.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medpagetoday.com/psychiatry/generalpsychiatry/88526&#34;&gt;Why Anti-Psychiatry Now Fails and Harms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Stea is a clinical psychologist and adjunct assistant professor at the University of Calgary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Black is the psychiatric medical director of British Columbia Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital.  He is also a clinical instructor in psychiatry at the University of British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drs. Pies and Ruffalo Still Rattling Their Wooden Swords</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drs-pies-and-ruffalo-still-rattling-their-wooden-swords/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 11:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drs-pies-and-ruffalo-still-rattling-their-wooden-swords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ronald Pies, MD, and Mark Ruffalo, D Psa, were busy in June.  They published &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; papers in defense of psychiatry:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/freud-fluoxetine/202006/what-is-meant-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt;What Is Meant by a Psychiatric Diagnosis?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;Psychiatric diagnoses are not merely descriptive; they reflect genuine illness&amp;rdquo;); and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/freud-fluoxetine/202006/psychiatric-diagnosis-20-the-myth-the-symptom-checklist&#34;&gt;Psychiatric Diagnosis 2.0: The Myth of the Symptom Checklist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(&amp;ldquo;More on the meaning of psychiatric diagnosis&amp;rdquo;).  Both were published by Psychology Today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s their opening to the first paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 40px;&#34;&gt;&#34;It has become fashionable for some in the social sciences to assert that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/psychiatry&#34;&gt;psychiatric&lt;/a&gt; diagnoses represent &#39;constructs&#39; and not genuine disorders or diseases. During a recent Twitter exchange, one of us (Mark Ruffalo) was pointed to an article published &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychologically-minded/201907/psychiatric-diagnosis-is-not-disease&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Psychology Today &lt;/em&gt;in 2019 by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/psychoanalysis&#34;&gt;psychoanalytic&lt;/a&gt; psychologist Jonathan Shedler, Ph.D., titled, &#39;A Psychiatric Diagnosis Is Not a Disease.&#39;&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances: Still Spinning the Story</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-spinning-the-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 05:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-spinning-the-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 4, 2020, the very eminent Allen Frances, MD, published an article in Aeon, which according to its &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/about&#34;&gt;About page&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;a digital magazine, publishing some of the most profound and provocative thinking on the web. We ask the big questions and find the freshest, most original answers, provided by leading thinkers on science, philosophy, society and the arts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/ideas/the-lure-of-cool-brain-research-is-stifling-psychotherapy&#34;&gt;The lure of ‘cool’ brain research is stifling psychotherapy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  The central theme is that prior to 1990, the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) &amp;ldquo;appreciated the need for a well-rounded approach [to mental health] and maintained a balanced research budget that covered an extraordinarily wide range of topics and techniques.&amp;rdquo;  However, since 1990, the opening year of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decade_of_the_Brain&#34;&gt;Decade of the Brain&lt;/a&gt;, the NIMH has &amp;ldquo;increasingly narrowed its focus almost exclusively to brain biology – leaving out everything else that makes us human, both in sickness and in health.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances and the Increasing Use of Antidepressants</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 05:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, 2018, the prestigious and venerable psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, gave an interview to Christiane Amanpour on CNN.  You can see the video &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/videos/tv/2018/05/17/amanpour-allen-frances-antidepressants-interview.cnn&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;em&gt;How Antidepressant Withdrawal &amp;ldquo;Can Trap People&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how the interview opened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;CA:  &#34;So you know, I just wanted to start by saying that who knew that antidepressants were addictive.  It&#39;s not what you associate with things like antidepressants.  You think of pain-killers, obviously, and drugs and alcohol, and cigarettes.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The &#34;Essential Principles&#34; of Psychiatric Practice: More Psychiatric Cheerleading</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-essential-principles-of-psychiatric-practice-more-psychiatric-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 05:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-essential-principles-of-psychiatric-practice-more-psychiatric-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the May 2018 issue of Current Psychiatry, there&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/The-DNA-of-Psychiatric-Practice.pdf&#34;&gt;editoria&lt;/a&gt;l by Henry Nasrallah, MD.  Dr. Nasrallah is a highly renowned psychiatrist, and is Editor-in-Chief of the journal.  He is also chair of the St. Louis University Department of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the opening paragraph of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As the end of the academic year approaches, I always think of one last message to send to the freshly minted psychiatrists who will complete their 4 years of post-MD training. This year, I thought of emphasizing the principles of psychiatric practice, which the graduates will deliver for the next 4 to 5 decades of their professional lives. Those essential principles are coded in the DNA of psychiatric practice, just as the construction of all organs in the human body is coded within the DNA of the 22,000 genes that comprise our 23 chromosomes.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Pies Defending Psychiatry&#39;s Position on Auditory Hallucinations</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-defending-psychiatry-s-position-on-auditory-hallucinations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 05:30:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-defending-psychiatry-s-position-on-auditory-hallucinations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 4, 2017, the very eminent and prestigious psychiatrist Ronald Pies, MD, published an article on Psychiatric Times.  The piece is titled: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Psychiatric_Times_-_Hearing_Voices_and_Psychiatrys_Real_Medical_Model_-_2017-09-15.pdf&#34;&gt;Hearing Voices and Psychiatry’s (Real) Medical Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Dr. Pies is Editor-in-Chief Emeritus of Psychiatric Times and a professor of psychiatry at SUNY and Tufts.  He has written extensively on psychiatric and other matters, and has acquired a reputation for scholarship and erudition.  His credibility, however, took a considerable knock in 2014 when, in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/823368&#34;&gt;Medscape article&lt;/a&gt; he asserted that the chemical imbalance theory of depression was just a kind of urban legend that was never seriously promoted by psychiatry. This assertion, which was widely disputed, added a whole new dimension to the concept of the ivory tower.  But it also provided an important insight into Dr. Pies&amp;rsquo; primary position:  that psychiatry is inherently benign, scientifically founded, and helpful, and that all suggestions to the contrary are logically flawed, factually mistaken, or both.  The present &amp;ldquo;Hearing Voices…&amp;rdquo; piece is in this same vein.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rebranding Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/rebranding-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/rebranding-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Or, how to make a silk purse from a sow&amp;rsquo;s ear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2017, the British Journal of Psychiatry published a guest editorial titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Shrink+rethink%3A+rebranding+psychiatry&#34;&gt;Shrink rethink: rebranding psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The authors are Scottish psychiatrists Jim Crabb, MD and Neil Masson, MD, and Lee Barber, an advertising and marketing strategist.  Both Drs. Crabb and Masson practice general adult psychiatry and also lecture in psychiatry at the University of Glasgow.  They are both members of the Scottish Teaching and Recruitment Group (STARG), which &amp;ldquo;looks at ways of improving recruitment into psychiatry.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robert Whitaker Refutes Jeffrey Lieberman; But Is Psychiatry Reformable?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 05:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 5, 2017, Donald Goff, MD and seven other psychiatrists, including the very eminent Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, published an article in the American Journal of Psychiatry.  The title is: &lt;span style=&#34;color: #000080;&#34;&gt;&lt;span lang=&#34;zxx&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.16091016&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Long-Term Effects of Antipsychotic Medication on Clinical Course in Schizophrenia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Concerns have been raised that treatment with antipsychotic medication might adversely affect long-term outcomes for people with schizophrenia. The evidence cited for these concerns includes the association of antipsychotic treatment with brain volume reduction and with dopamine receptor sensitization, which might make patients vulnerable to relapse and illness progression. An international group of experts was convened to examine findings from clinical and basic research relevant to these concerns. Little evidence was found to support a negative long-term effect of initial or maintenance antipsychotic treatment on outcomes, compared with withholding treatment. Randomized controlled trials strongly support the efficacy of antipsychotics for the acute treatment of psychosis and prevention of relapse; correlational evidence suggests that early intervention and reduced duration of untreated psychosis might improve longer-term outcomes. Strategies for treatment discontinuation or alternative nonpharmacologic treatment approaches may benefit a subgroup of patients but may be associated with incremental risk of relapse and require further study, including the development of biomarkers that will enable a precision medicine approach to individualized treatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nassir Ghaemi and The Psychological Fallacy</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/nassir-ghaemi-and-the-psychological-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 05:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/nassir-ghaemi-and-the-psychological-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 8, 2013, the eminent psychiatrist Nassir Ghaemi, MD, MPH, published an article on Medscape. The title of the piece is &lt;a href=&#34;http://boards.medscape.com/forums/?128@@.2a590e54!comment=1&amp;amp;cat=All&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000080;&#34;&gt;&lt;span lang=&#34;zxx&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Psychological Fallacy in Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The article is almost four years old. Ordinarily I don&amp;rsquo;t discuss material this dated, but the content of this article is particularly important, and worthy of discussion, belated as it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASSIR GHAEMI&amp;rsquo;S BIO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to his bio, Dr. Ghaemi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…is an academic psychiatrist specializing in mood illnesses, depression and bipolar illness, and Editor of a monthly newsletter, The Psychiatry Letter (www.psychiatryletter.org).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health First Aid: Another Psychiatric Expansionist Tool</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On December 25, 2016, the Baltimore Sun published an excellent article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/oped/bs-ed-youth-overmedication-20161225-story.html&#34;&gt;Drug companies prey on children&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Patrick D. Hahn, PhD.  Dr. Hahn is an affiliate professor of biology at Loyola University, Maryland.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I recently attended Youth Mental Health First Aid Training at a local public school. It was an eye-opening experience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Youth Mental Health First Aid Training, sponsored by the National Council for Behavioral Health, is intended to enable teachers, parents and others in contact with young people to identify potential &#39;mental illnesses&#39; in order to facilitate early detection and treatment by our mental health care system. My fellow attendees were surprisingly open about their own experiences with that system. One mentioned that her son became manic after being diagnosed for ADHD. Another said that both she and her roommate became bipolar after being diagnosed for depression. Neither our facilitators nor anyone else present pointed out that mania and bipolar disorder are toxic effects of medications commonly prescribed for ADHD and depression.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Biological Evidence for &#34;Mental Illness&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 05:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-biological-evidence-for-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 2, 2017, I published a short post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2017/01/02/carrie-fisher-dead-at-age-60/&#34;&gt;Carrie Fisher Dead at Age 60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on Behaviorism and Mental Health.  The article was published simultaneously on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.madinamerica.com/2017/01/carrie-fisher-dead-age-60/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On January 4, a response from Carolina Partners was entered into the comments string on both sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carolina Partners in Mental Healthcare, PLLC, is a large psychiatric group practice based in North Carolina.  According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.carolinapartners.com/&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;, they comprise 14 psychiatrists, 7 psychologists, 34 Advanced Practice Nurse Practitioners/Physicians Assistants, and 43 Therapists and Counselors.  They have 27 North Carolina locations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Response to a Defender of Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-response-to-a-defender-of-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 05:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/my-response-to-a-defender-of-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 13, an interesting article was published on the Huffington Post Blog.  The author is Jessica Gold, MD, a psychiatry resident at Stanford University; the post is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/inpatient-psychiatry-not-all-needles-drugs-and-locks_us_57fd5a2ae4b0dccfa3908cc3?timestamp=1476371560599&#34;&gt;Inpatient Psychiatry: Not all Needles, Drugs And Locks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a personal experience/opinion piece, the gist of which is that people who criticize or condemn psychiatry simply don&amp;rsquo;t understand the complexities and needs of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;patients&amp;rdquo;, particularly the need for locked wards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances:  Still Blaming Everyone But Himself</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-blaming-everyone-but-himself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-blaming-everyone-but-himself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 7, Allen Frances, MD, posted an article on the HuffPost site.  The piece was titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/antidepressants-work-but-_b_9849478.html&#34;&gt;Antidepressants Work, But Only For Really Depressed People&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superficially, the article presents itself as a call to limit the prescribing of the so-called antidepressant drugs to severe cases; but the piece can, I suggest, be more accurately characterized as Dr. Frances&amp;rsquo;s latest attempt to distance himself, and psychiatry in general, from the pill-peddling frenzy that has characterized the profession for the past thirty or forty years&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  The Hoax Unravels</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 05:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-the-hoax-unravels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the risk of stating the obvious, ADHD is not an illness.  Rather, it is an unreliable and disempowering label for a loose collection of arbitrarily chosen and vaguely defined behaviors.  ADHD has been avidly promoted as an illness by pharma-psychiatry for the purpose of selling stimulant drugs.  In which endeavor, they have been phenomenally successful, but, as in other areas of psychiatry, the hoax is unraveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances on Anti-Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-on-anti-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 06:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-on-anti-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 22, Allen Frances, MD, published an article titled:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/psychiatry-and-antipsychi_b_9243944.html&#34;&gt;Psychiatry and Anti-Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on the HuffPost Blog.  The general theme of the article is that psychiatry may have some problems, but it is basically sound, wholesome, and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatry used to be a biopsychosocial profession that allowed time to get to know the person, not just treat the symptom. But drastic cuts in the funding of mental health services have dramatically reduced the quality of the service they can provide. Psychiatrists are now forced to follow very large panels of patients. Most of the limited time they are allowed with each is spent discussing symptoms, adjusting the meds, and determining side effects. Little time is left to forge a healing relationship, provide support, and teach skills through psychotherapy. And patients usually get to a psychiatrist- if at all- as a last resort, only after other things have failed- and with the expectation by the patient and referral source that the main purpose of the visit is just to prescribe medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Bashing</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-bashing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 05:30:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-bashing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month (February 2016), the British Journal of Psychiatry published an online bulletin titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/BASH-article-BJP.pdf&#34;&gt;BASH: badmouthing, attitudes and stigmatisation in healthcare as experienced by medical students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Ali Ajaz et al.  Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&#34;Aims and method&lt;/strong&gt; We used an online questionnaire to investigate medical students&#39; perceptions of the apparent hierarchy between specialties, whether they have witnessed disparaging comments (‘badmouthing’ or ‘bashing’) against other specialists and whether this has had an effect on their career choice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Still Trying to Excuse Psychiatry&#39;s (and his own) Role in the ADHD &#39;Epidemic&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-trying-to-excuse-psychiatry-s-and-his-own-role-in-the-adhd-epidemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-still-trying-to-excuse-psychiatry-s-and-his-own-role-in-the-adhd-epidemic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 9, 2015, Allen Frances, MD, posted an interesting article on the Huffington Post&amp;rsquo;s Blog.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/why-are-so-many-college-a_b_8331958.html&#34;&gt;Why Are So Many College and High School Kids Abusing Adderall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that the &amp;ldquo;excessive use of ADHD medication&amp;rdquo; is a more legitimate target for a war on drugs than the ongoing war with the drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Huffington Post article is unusual, in that most of it is written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD.  Dr. Frances wrote the introduction, ending with  &amp;ldquo;I have invited Dr Gretchen LeFever Watson, a clinical psychologist and public health researcher, to describe this growing problem.&amp;rdquo;  Dr. Watson wrote the main body of the piece; and Dr. Frances finished up with some brief concluding remarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Names and Shames the Power Players, but Not Himself</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-names-and-shames-the-power-players-but-not-himself/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-names-and-shames-the-power-players-but-not-himself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 13, 2015, Allen Frances, MD, published a post on his Psychology Today blog Saving Normal.  The post is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201510/what-drives-our-dumb-and-disorganized-mental-health-policies&#34;&gt;What Drives Our Dumb and Disorganized Mental Health Policies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and the subtitle is &amp;ldquo;Naming and shaming the power players.&amp;rdquo;  The article has also been published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/Allen-Frances-Psychiatric_Times_-_What_Drives_Our_Disorganized_Mental_Health_Policies_-_2015-10-09-1.pdf&#34;&gt;Psychiatric Times&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/dumb-and-disorganized-mental-health-policy_b_8209056.html&#34;&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/a&gt;.  Dr. Frances is a professor emeritus of psychiatry at Duke University, and was chairman of the DSM-IV Task Force.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Pies and Psychiatry&#39;s &#39;Solid Center&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-and-psychiatry-s-solid-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 05:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-and-psychiatry-s-solid-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ronald Pies, MD, is one of American&amp;rsquo;s most eminent and prestigious psychiatrists.  He is the Editor-in-Chief Emeritus of Psychiatric Times, and he is a Professor of Psychiatry at both Syracuse and Tufts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree with many of Dr. Pies&amp;rsquo; contentions, and I have expressed these disagreements in detail in various posts (for instance, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/06/06/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/04/02/453-psychiatric-diagnoses-labels-not-explanations/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/09/08/dr-pies-still-spinning/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  But there is one area where I have to acknowledge Dr. Pies&amp;rsquo; efforts:  he never gives up in his defense of his beloved psychiatry, even in the face of the most damaging counter-evidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The APA&#39;s New Image</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-apa-s-new-image/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 05:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-apa-s-new-image/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 25, 2014, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, then President of the APA, &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/doi/full/10.1176%2Fappi.pn.2014.5a21&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that the association had engaged the services of Porter Novelli, a prestigious PR company based in Washington DC and currently operating in 60 different countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Mindful of the continuing stigma associated with mental illness and psychiatric treatment, we retained an outside consultant agency (Porter Novelli) to review APA’s communications capabilities, needs, and opportunities. Based on its report, we are now moving forward with an initiative to enact a sophisticated and proactive communications plan that will be directed both internally to APA members and externally to the media, mental health stakeholder groups, and the general public.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stigmatization of Psychiatry and Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/stigmatization-of-psychiatry-and-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 05:30:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/stigmatization-of-psychiatry-and-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 27, 2015, European Psychiatry published a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/EPA-guidance-on-image-of-psychiatrists-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;EPA guidance on how to improve the image of psychiatry and of the psychiatrist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The paper was authored by D. Bhugra et al.  EPA is the European Psychiatric Association.  Dr. Bhugra is a psychiatrist who works at the Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology, and Neuroscience, King&amp;rsquo;s College, London, and is also President of the World Psychiatric Association.  There are thirteen co-authors, most of whom are also psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Saving Psychiatry From Itself?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 12, 2014, the eminent psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, participated in a panel discussion at the Mad In America film festival in Gothenburg, Sweden.  After the festival, he wrote an article – &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/finding-a-middle-ground-between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry_b_6010890.html&#34;&gt;Finding a Middle Ground Between Psychiatry and Anti-Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;– for the Huffington Post Blog, summarizing the positions he had discussed at the festival. The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/10/between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry-mad-in-america-opens-a-dialogue/&#34;&gt;re-published on MIA&lt;/a&gt; on October 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is ostensibly an attempt to find common ground between psychiatry and its critics, but the piece contains numerous distortions and omissions which I think need to be identified and discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spurious Chemical Imbalance Theory is Still Alive and Well</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-spurious-chemical-imbalance-theory-is-still-alive-and-well/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 05:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-spurious-chemical-imbalance-theory-is-still-alive-and-well/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 5, 2015, Scott Alexander, MD, a trainee psychiatrist, posted an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://slatestarcodex.com/2015/04/05/chemical-imbalance/&#34;&gt;Chemical Imbalance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on his website Slate Star Codex.  (The writer tells us that Scott Alexander is a blog handle and not his real name, but for convenience, I will refer to him as Dr. Alexander.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Alexander begins by noting that there have been a number of articles recently that have criticized psychiatry for &amp;ldquo;botching the &amp;lsquo;chemical imbalance&amp;rsquo; theory.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric Diagnoses:  Labels, Not Explanations</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-labels-not-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 05:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-labels-not-explanations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 16, Ronald Pies, MD, published an article in the Psychiatric Times.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/couch-crisis/war-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt;The War on Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; and the sub-title synopsis on the pdf version reads:  &amp;ldquo;A recent report that argues against descriptive diagnosis in medicine is historically ill-informed and medically naive, in the opinion of this psychiatrist.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pies is a very prestigious and eminent psychiatrist.  He is a professor of psychiatry at both Syracuse and Tufts.  He was the first editor of Psychiatric Times, which, by its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/contribute-site&#34;&gt;own account&lt;/a&gt;, provides &amp;ldquo;News, Special Reports, and clinical content related to psychiatry&amp;rdquo; for &amp;ldquo;…psychiatrists and allied mental health professionals who treat mental disorders…Circulation of the monthly print publication is approximately 40,000.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Insel:  &#34;Are Children Overmedicated?&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-insel-are-children-overmedicated/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 05:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-insel-are-children-overmedicated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, is the Director of the National Institute of Mental Health.  In June of last year, he published, on the Director&amp;rsquo;s Blog, an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/director/2014/are-children-overmedicated.shtml&#34;&gt;Are Children Overmedicated?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  The gist of the article is that children are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being overmedicated, but rather that there is an increase in &amp;ldquo;severe psychiatric problems&amp;rdquo; in this population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The latest estimate from the National Center for Health Statistics reports that 7.5 percent of U.S. children between ages 6 and 17 were taking medication for &#39;emotional or behavioral difficulties&#39; in 2011-2012. The CDC reports a five-fold increase in the number of children under 18 on psychostimulants from 1988-1994 to 2007–2010, with the most recent rate of 4.2 percent. The same report estimates that 1.3 percent of children are on antidepressants. The rate of antipsychotic prescriptions for children has increased six-fold over this same period, according to a study of office visits within the National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey. In children under age 5, psychotropic prescription rates peaked at 1.45 percent in 2002-2005 and declined to 1.00 percent from 2006-2009.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cures For Brain Disorders</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cures-for-brain-disorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 05:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cures-for-brain-disorders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 18, Thomas Insel, MD, published an article on The World Economic Forum Blog.  The article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://agenda.weforum.org/2015/01/four-things-leaders-need-to-know-about-mental-health/&#34;&gt;4 things leaders need to know about mental health&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;Dr. Insel is the Director of the National Institute of Mental Health.  The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weforum.org/world-economic-forum&#34;&gt;World Economic Forum&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;is an International Institution committed to improving the state of the world through public-private cooperation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Insel&amp;rsquo;s paper makes a number of assertions, some of which are misleading.  Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antipsychiatry Stigma</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antipsychiatry-stigma/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 05:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antipsychiatry-stigma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acps.2014.131.issue-1/issuetoc&#34;&gt;current issue&lt;/a&gt; of Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica is devoted to the topic of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s poor image, and what steps might be taken to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to the discussion is a study &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acps.12368/pdf&#34;&gt;Images of psychiatry and psychiatrists&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by H. Stuart et al, - and seven commentaries on this study by various authors.  The Stuart et al paper describes a survey of 1057 teaching medical faculty members from 15 sites in Europe and Asia.  The overall response rate was 65%, and the results indicate clearly that general medical teaching staff have a poor opinion of psychiatry and psychiatrists.  For instance, 90% of respondents endorsed the item &amp;ldquo;Most psychiatrists are not good role models for medical students.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry: Still Trying To Rewrite History</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-trying-to-rewrite-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 05:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-trying-to-rewrite-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 15, psychiatrist Allan Tasman, MD, published an article in Psychiatric Times.  The title of the article is &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/history-psychiatry/most-exciting-time-history-psychiatry?GUID=&amp;amp;rememberme=1&amp;amp;ts=16102014&#34;&gt;The Most Exciting Time in the History of Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychiatric Times &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/contribute-site&#34;&gt;describes itself&lt;/a&gt;:  &amp;ldquo;Our Focus:  News, special Reports, and clinical content related to psychiatry. Our Audience:  Psychiatrists and allied mental health professionals who treat mental disorders.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychiatric_Times&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:  &amp;ldquo;Psychiatric Times is a medical trade publication written for an audience involved in the profession of psychiatry.&amp;rdquo;  It is published by UBM Medica and is distributed to about 50,000 psychiatrists monthly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Cheerleading from the Royal College of Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cheerleading-from-the-royal-college-of-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 05:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cheerleading-from-the-royal-college-of-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 23, Simon Wessely, MD, a British psychiatrist, published an article, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/the-real-crisis-in-psychiatry-is-that-there-isnt-enough-of-it-32076&#34;&gt;The real crisis in psychiatry is that there isn&amp;rsquo;t enough of it&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; at the online site &lt;em&gt;The Conversation&lt;/em&gt;.  Dr. Wessely is the Professor of Psychological Medicine at King&amp;rsquo;s College, London, and is also the President of the Royal College of Psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/us/who-we-are&#34;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is an independent non-profit online media outlet that delivers &amp;ldquo;…news and views from the academic and research community…&amp;rdquo; directly to the public.  Their aim is &amp;ldquo;…to promote better understanding of current affairs and complex issues.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Benzos and Cognitive Damage</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzos-and-cognitive-damage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 05:30:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzos-and-cognitive-damage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 9, 2014, the BMJ published an article by Sophie Billioti de Gage et al.  The article was titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/bmj.g5205-billioti-ALZ.pdf&#34;&gt;Benzodiazepine use and risk of Alzheimer’s disease: case-control study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and concluded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“Benzodiazepine use is associated with an increased risk of Alzheimer’s disease. &lt;em&gt;The stronger association observed for long term exposures reinforces the suspicion of a possible direct association,&lt;/em&gt; even if benzodiazepine use might also be an early marker of a condition associated with an increased risk of dementia. Unwarranted long term use of these drugs should be considered as a public health concern.” [Emphasis added]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma-funded Research</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-funded-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-funded-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On August 20, 2014, P&lt;em&gt;sychiatry Advisor&lt;/em&gt; published an article on its website.  The article was written by Leslie Citrome, MD, a professor of psychiatry at New York Medical College in Valhalla, NY, and a member of the Board of Directors of the American Society of Clinical Psychopharmacology.  The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatryadvisor.com/is-bias-against-pharma-funded-research-fair/article/367248/&#34;&gt;Is Bias Against Pharma-Funded Research Fair?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  This is an interesting title, because bias, by its very definition, is unfair.  So the very wording of the question begs the question – which strikes me as unfair.  But let&amp;rsquo;s put that aside.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murderers and Psychiatric Drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murderers-and-psychiatric-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 05:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murderers-and-psychiatric-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the current issue of the National Psychologist written by David Kirschner, PhD, a New York psychologist.  The National Psychologist is a newspaper-type magazine that publishes articles of general interest to psychologists and others working in this field.  Most issues contain a mix of opinion pieces, news, changes in government regulations, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kirschner&amp;rsquo;s article is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nationalpsychologist.com/2014/09/mass-shooters-received-only-limited-treatment/102638.html&#34;&gt;Mass shooters received only limited treatment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Pies Still Spinning</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-still-spinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 05:28:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-pies-still-spinning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 1, the very eminent psychiatrist Ronald Pies, MD, wrote an article for Psychiatric Times titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/positivism-humanism-and-case-psychiatric-diagnosis/page/0/3&#34;&gt;Positivism, Humanism and the Case for Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article also appeared in Medscape on August 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pies begins by discussing websites &amp;ldquo;…that critically examine psychiatry.&amp;rdquo;  These websites, he tells us,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…vary from the viscerally enraged, to the politely skeptical, to the constructively critical, and everything in between. The worst antipsychiatry Web sites, in my view, are veritable bastions of bigotry, in which psychiatrists are subjected to invective and abuse that would never be tolerated if directed, say, at some ethnic or racial minority.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simon Says:  Happiness Won&#39;t Cure Mental Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/simon-says-happiness-won-t-cure-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 05:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/simon-says-happiness-won-t-cure-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professor Simon Wessely, who was recently installed as President of Britain&amp;rsquo;s Royal College of Psychiatrists, has just written his second post in that capacity.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/discoverpsychiatry/thepresidentsblog/happinessthegreatestgift.aspx&#34;&gt;Happiness: The greatest gift that I possess?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The background to Dr. Wessely&amp;rsquo;s article is the recent launching of the UK&amp;rsquo;s Centre Forum&amp;rsquo;s Mental Health Commission&amp;rsquo;s report:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.centreforum.org/assets/pubs/the-pursuit-of-happiness.pdf&#34;&gt;The pursuit of happiness:  a new ambition for our mental health&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  This is a very interesting report, the gist of which can perhaps be gained from these quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Debunks the &#39;Myths&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-debunks-the-myths/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-debunks-the-myths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;Psychiatry has always had its share of critics, but in the past two decades these criticisms have increased in frequency and intensity.  Psychiatry&#39;s underlying concepts are being denounced as spurious to the point of inanity, and its practices are being accurately and forcefully exposed as destructive, disempowering, and stigmatizing.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychiatry has no rational or logical response to these criticisms.  Its leadership and its rank and file remain stubbornly blind to the arbitrariness and invalidity of its so-called diagnoses, the unquestioning adoption of which distorts their perceptions of people and their problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suicidal Behavior After FDA Warnings</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/suicidal-behavior-after-fda-warnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 05:45:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/suicidal-behavior-after-fda-warnings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 18, the British Medical Journal published an article by Christine Lu et al, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmj.com/content/348/bmj.g3596&#34;&gt;Changes in antidepressant use by young people and suicidal behavior after FDA warnings and media coverage: quasi-experimental study&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the conclusion paragraph from the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Safety warnings about antidepressants and widespread media coverage decreased antidepressant use, and there were simultaneous increases in suicide attempts among young people. It is essential to monitor and reduce possible unintended consequences of FDA warnings and media reporting.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lingering Doubts About Psychiatry&#39;s Scientific Status</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lingering-doubts-about-psychiatry-s-scientific-status/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 05:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lingering-doubts-about-psychiatry-s-scientific-status/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professor Sir Simon Wessely is a British psychiatrist who works at the Institute of Psychiatry, King&amp;rsquo;s College, London.  He is also the new President of the Royal College of Psychiatrists, and in that capacity, he recently wrote his first blog, titled, appropriately enough, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/discoverpsychiatry/blogfromthepresidentelect.aspx&#34;&gt;My First Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (May 24, 2014)&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article is essentially a perusal of, and commentary on, the program for the RCP&amp;rsquo;s Annual Congress, about which Sir Simon expresses considerable enthusiasm.  He also engages in a little cheerleading.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New APA President: Same Old Cheerleading</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-apa-president-same-old-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 05:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-apa-president-same-old-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my readers know, I am a great fan of former APA President Jeffrey Lieberman, MD.  His regular articles on Psychiatric News were always helpful to the anti-psychiatry cause, and he will be greatly missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his successor, Paul Summergrad, MD, has recently posted his first presidential message, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=1882424&#34;&gt;APA Poised to Take Advantage of Unique Time in History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and it is already clear that not much has changed.  Cheerleading and unabashed self-congratulations are still the order of the day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Final APA Address</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-final-apa-address/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2014 10:49:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-final-apa-address/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 29, Psychiatric News ran an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=1877665&#34;&gt;Lieberman Sees Promising Future for Psychiatrists, Patients&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;The author is Mark Moran, a senior reporter for the American Psychiatric Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post is an account of Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s outgoing presidential address to the APA conference in New York, and contains many quotes from this most eminent and memorable psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Our future is now. We have been waiting, many of us our whole lives, for the chance to change the way the world thinks of psychiatry and the way we think of ourselves as psychiatrists. Let’s use the momentum we have to plunge ahead into the next year with our confidence brimming, our energy renewed, and our sights set high.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Response:  Attack and PR</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-response-attack-and-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2014 05:58:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-response-attack-and-pr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last decade or so psychiatry has received a great deal of criticism.  The fundamental point of contention is psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s insistence that an ever increasing range of problems of thinking, feeling, and/or behaving are in fact illnesses that need to be aggressively treated with drugs, intracranial electric shocks, and other somatic interventions.  It is further contended, by those of us on this side of the debate, that this spurious medicalization of non-medical problems was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an innocent error, but rather was, and is, a self-serving and deliberate policy designed to expand psychiatric turf and to create an impression of psychiatry as a legitimate medical specialty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry DID Promote the Chemical Imbalance Theory</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2014 05:58:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 15, Ronald Pies, MD, an eminent and widely published psychiatrist, wrote an article for Medscape.com.  The piece is titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/823368&#34;&gt;Nuances, Narratives, and the &amp;lsquo;Chemical Imbalance&amp;rsquo; Debate in Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thrust of the article is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…the &#39;chemical imbalance theory&#39; was never a real theory, nor was it widely propounded by responsible practitioners in the field of psychiatry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This is not the first time that Dr. Pies has made this claim,  On July 11, 2011, he wrote an article for Psychiatric Times titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/blogs/couch-crisis/psychiatry-new-brain-mind-and-legend-chemical-imbalance&#34;&gt;Psychiatry’s New Brain-Mind and the Legend of the “Chemical Imbalance.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  In that article he wrote:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;In truth, the ‘chemical imbalance’ notion was always a kind of urban legend- – never a theory seriously propounded by well-informed psychiatrists.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Underestimate the Benefits of Antidepressants?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 05:58:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 19, 2014, The Lancet published an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Do-we-underestimate-the-benefits-of-antidepressants.pdf&#34;&gt;Do we underestimate the benefits of antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by German psychiatrists Mazda Adli and Ulrich Hegerl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lancet, founded in 1823, is a weekly, general medical journal which since 1991 has been owned by Elsevier, a private, Amsterdam-based, publishing house with offices in the UK, USA, and other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article can be gathered from the opening paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Swansong</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-swansong/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 05:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-swansong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my readers know, I am a great fan of Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA.  In his capacity as president, Dr. Lieberman writes a regular bulletin in Psychiatric News.  These literary and intellectual gems have been a wonderful source of inspiration to me in my efforts to draw attention to psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s flaws, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think it would be an exaggeration to say that in many respects, Dr. Lieberman has been one of our greatest allies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depression vs. Normal Unhappiness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-vs-normal-unhappiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 05:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/depression-vs-normal-unhappiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alex Langford is a British trainee psychiatrist.  He blogs at The Psychiatric SHO, and on April 21, he posted an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychiatrysho.wordpress.com/2014/04/21/antidepressants-are-not-happy-pills/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antidepressants are not &amp;lsquo;happy pills.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeandavisonwriter.wordpress.com/2014/04/26/more-support-and-understanding-needed-for-people-wanting-to-try-a-no-meds-approach/&#34;&gt;Jean Davison&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is an impassioned attack on psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s critics.  Here are some quotes, with my responses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I am sick and tired of the way the press portrays depression as unhappiness and antidepressants as ‘happy pills’.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This is interesting, though my general impression is that the mainstream media lean a good deal more towards psychiatry than towards our side of the debate.  In addition, the words &#34;depression&#34; and unhappiness are pretty much synonymous.  So it&#39;s difficult to see why that, or the characterization of antidepressants as &#34;happy pills,&#34; should be so upsetting to Dr. Langford.  We all, of course, have our linguistic likes and dislikes.  I personally don&#39;t care much for the growing trend to pronounce the indefinite article as &#34;ay,&#34; or for psychiatry&#39;s insistence on calling neuroleptic drugs &#34;anti-psychotics.&#34;  But what can you do?  I just Googled the phrase &#34;antidepressants are happy pills&#34; and got 204,000 hits!  So the notion has some traction and is probably here to stay.  One can&#39;t legislate for the way people use words.  Or perhaps psychiatrists imagine that they can.
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;For problems in other areas of health we’d only trust the experts to comment, but when it comes to mental health it seems like anyone can cast judgement.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Fights Back – With More PR</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-fights-back-with-more-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 05:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-fights-back-with-more-pr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;About six months ago, I wrote a post called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/10/14/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Health Care Reform and Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.  In that article, I gave a brief account of the APA&amp;rsquo;s Council on Communications, and I expressed the belief that the council seemed more concerned with PR (in the most tawdry sense of the term) than with any serious examination or reform of psychiatric practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Lately, I was browsing the APA blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://apahealthyminds.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Healthy Minds, Healthy Lives&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, and it seemed that a good deal of what I was reading seemed to have a fairly heavy PR component.  So I opened the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatry.org/advocacy--newsroom/council-on-communications&#34;&gt;Council on Communications&lt;/a&gt; tab and found that their lead page is pretty much as it was six months ago.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perfect Psychiatrist</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 05:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On March 19, a new article was posted on Aeon Magazine.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/magazine/being-human/have-psychiatrists-lost-perspective-on-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;A Mad World&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and was written by Joseph Pierre, MD, who works in Log Angeles as a psychiatric practitioner and professor.  Dr. Pierre has authored more than fifty papers, and has received several awards.  He has lectured nationally and internationally, and would, I think, be considered an eminent psychiatrist.  I am grateful to several readers for the link to the article.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Szasz Refuted:  I Don&#39;t Think So!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-szasz-refuted-i-don-t-think-so/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 05:58:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/thomas-szasz-refuted-i-don-t-think-so/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On February 28, Awais Aftab, MD, a psychiatrist working in Qatar, published an interesting article on Psychiatric Times.  The article, which is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/dsm-5-0/mental-illness-vs-brain-disorders-szasz-dsm-5&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Mental Illness vs Brain Disorders: From Szasz to DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, is an attempt to validate the concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and, in particular, claims to refute the position of the late Thomas Szasz, MD, that mental illness is a spurious concept.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The validity or otherwise of the concept of mental illness is fundamental to psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s claim to legitimacy, and for this reason, Dr. Aftab&amp;rsquo;s article deserves close scrutiny.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Cheerleading from Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cheerleading-from-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2014 05:57:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-cheerleading-from-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On February 28, our good friend, the eminent Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1839382&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Politics of Psychiatry and Mental Health Care &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;on Psychiatric News, the APA&amp;rsquo;s online bulletin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His co-author on this occasion is Patrick Kennedy, former Congressman from Rhode Island and co-sponsor of the Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece is fluff and cheerleading, which have become Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s areas of specialty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Trying to Reinvent Itself</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-trying-to-reinvent-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2014 05:58:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-trying-to-reinvent-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a truly delightful little piece in February&amp;rsquo;s Current Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Henry Nasrallah, MD, and is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/uploads/media/010_0214CP_FromTheEditor_FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;Psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s future shock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;  Dr. Nasrallah is Editor-in-Chief of Current Psychiatry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The gist of the article is that &amp;ldquo;transformative&amp;rdquo; changes are occurring in the psychiatric field, and psychiatrists had better get on board, or they will be left behind.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;The &#39;neuroscientification&#39; of psychiatry, ongoing for more than 3 decades, is now approaching a tipping point: The specialty is on the verge of an unprecedented denouement of the old tenets and assumptions.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Embraces Patient-Centered Care:  Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embraces-patient-centered-care-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 05:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embraces-patient-centered-care-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 29, the APA&amp;rsquo;s online bulletin Psychiatric News, published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1827633&#34;&gt;Psychiatry Embraces Patient-Centered Care&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, and Lisa Dixon, MD.  Dr. Lieberman is President of the APA, and chair of psychiatry at Columbia University.  Dr. Dixon is a professor of psychiatry at Columbia.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the opening statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatry has long been considered the medical specialty most attuned to listening to the patient.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This is a little difficult to reconcile with the fifteen minute med-check that has been pretty much the standard of care in most psychiatric offices for the past 25 years.  It is also difficult to reconcile with reports from psychiatric survivors.
&lt;p&gt;The authors are willing to concede, however, that &amp;ldquo;…the nature of the doctor-patient relationship was traditionally one-sided.&amp;rdquo;  What they mean by this is:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 05:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/revitalizing-psychiatric-therapeutics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In January of this year, Steven Hyman MD, former Director of NIMH and currently a leading psychiatric researcher at MIT and Harvard, published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/npp/journal/v39/n1/full/npp2013181a.html&#34;&gt;Revitalizing Psychiatric Therapeutics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; in Neuropsychopharmacology.  The article is in the journal&amp;rsquo;s commentary section and is essentially an opinion piece.  Here&amp;rsquo;s Dr. Hyman&amp;rsquo;s summary:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Despite high prevalence and enormous unmet medical need, the pharmaceutical industry has recently de-emphasized neuropsychiatric disorders as &#39;too difficult&#39; a challenge to warrant major investment.  Here I describe major obstacles to drug discovery and development including a lack of new molecular targets, shortcomings of current animal models, and the lack of biomarkers for clinical trials.  My major focus, however, is on new technologies and scientific approaches to neuropsychiatric disorders that give promise for revitalizing therapeutics and may thus answer industry&#39;s concerns.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia Research</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 05:57:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Psychiatric News is the APA&amp;rsquo;s online bulletin.  On Jan 15, it ran an article by Vabren Watts (an APA staff writer).  The article is called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1814750&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;APA Gives Schizophrenia Research Capitol Hill Spotlight&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;It is reported in the article that on December 12, 2013, the APA, together with the Congressional Neuroscience Caucus and the American Brain Coalition, made a joint presentation to legislators and their staffs on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Still Passing the Buck: Psychiatry Is Blameless</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 05:47:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has expressed concern about the rise in the number of people being assigned a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of ADHD.  He has put up a video on Medscape, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/819298&#34;&gt;Explaining the Rise in ADHD&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There is a transcript with the video.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is responding to a December 14, 2013, New York Times article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/15/health/the-selling-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;The Selling of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;by Alan Schwarz, and a December 18 editorial in the same paper titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/19/opinion/an-epidemic-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html&#34;&gt;An Epidemic of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New President of Royal College of Psychiatrists: Priorities</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-president-of-royal-college-of-psychiatrists-priorities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 06:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-president-of-royal-college-of-psychiatrists-priorities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The Royal College of Psychiatry is the UK equivalent of the American Psychiatric Association.  On January 14, they announced that Professor Simon Wessely has been elected as their next president, and that he will take office on June 26, 2014.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wessely is an eminent psychiatrist who has been knighted by the Queen for his services to psychiatric medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/mediacentre/pressreleases2014/presidentelections2014result.aspx&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;, the Royal College reported that Dr. Wessely&amp;rsquo;s priorities as President will be:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Of Psychiatrists: What The Future Holds</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-of-psychiatrists-what-the-future-holds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 06:06:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-of-psychiatrists-what-the-future-holds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Joel Yager, MD, is a Professor of Psychiatry, University of Colorado at Denver School of Medicine.  He started his career as a US Army psychiatrist in 1969, and has held a wide range of clinical and teaching positions in the intervening years.  He has received numerous awards, including lifetime achievement awards from the National Eating Disorders Association (2008) and from the Association for Academic Psychiatry (2009).  He has published more than 200 peer-reviewed papers, many of which are concerned with the training of psychiatrists.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Valid Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 05:58:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 23, I wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/23/dsm-5-dimensional-diagnoses-more-conflicts-of-interest/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  In the article I sketched out the role of David Kupfer, MD, in promoting the concept of dimensional assessment in DSM-5, and I speculated that at least part of his motivation in this regard might have stemmed from the fact that he is a major shareholder in a company that is developing a computerized assessment instrument.  I ended the piece with a general criticism of psychiatry:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Person-first Terminology Doesn&#39;t Validate Psychiatric Diagnoses</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/person-first-terminology-doesn-t-validate-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 05:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/person-first-terminology-doesn-t-validate-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 3, on CommonHealth I saw the following headline:  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commonhealth.wbur.org/2014/01/renounce-term-the-mentally-ill&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A Phrase To Renounce For 2014:  &amp;lsquo;The Mentally Ill&amp;rsquo;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, written by Carey Goldberg.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first impression was that the author was debunking the concept of mental illness, but I was sadly mistaken.  The theme of the article was the so-called person-first terminology that has been promoted by various bodies and agencies since about the mid-eighties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that one shouldn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;a developmentally disabled child.&amp;rdquo;  Instead, one should say &amp;ldquo;a child with a developmental disability.&amp;rdquo;  Similarly, a person should not be referred to as an &amp;ldquo;alcoholic,&amp;rdquo; but rather as a &amp;ldquo;person with alcoholism.&amp;rdquo;  And so on.  The idea is to avoid giving the impression that the individual is to be &lt;i&gt;defined by &lt;/i&gt; the presence of a disabling condition.  The individual is first and foremost a &lt;i&gt;person,&lt;/i&gt; and the problem or disability is semantically tacked on to indicate that it is a &lt;i&gt;quality&lt;/i&gt; of the person rather than the defining feature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman on Value and Price: Psychiatry Continues to Side-step Criticism</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-on-value-and-price-psychiatry-continues-to-side-step-criticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2013 05:46:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-on-value-and-price-psychiatry-continues-to-side-step-criticism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, is the President of the APA, and every two weeks or so he writes psychiatric propaganda articles on Psychiatric News (the APA&amp;rsquo;s online bulletin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 26, his piece was titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1809756&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;APA Successful in Attaining Higher Work Values for Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Here&amp;rsquo;s the first paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;In an ideal world, value and price would be closely aligned. This alignment doesn’t occur, however, when the value of a service or good isn’t understood. One only has to look at the huge disparity between the salaries of teachers compared with entertainers and sports figures to appreciate this incongruity; or between compensation in the financial-services industry and medicine. For too long, this has especially been the case for psychiatric services. Mental illness is a health care disparity, and mental health care has been stigmatized and undervalued, as have been the physicians who provide it. The result has been inappropriately low reimbursement rates for psychiatric treatment and a corresponding lack of access to mental health care for too many patients.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training the Psychiatrists of the Future (According to Dr. Lieberman): More Cheerleading</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 05:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA and Chair of Psychiatry at Columbia University, published a post on November 26 on Psychiatric News.  The article is called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1787247&#34;&gt;Training the Psychiatrists of the Future&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and is co-authored by Richard Summers, MD.  Dr. Summers is a Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Lieberman and Summers open by telling us that psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; roles &amp;ldquo;…are changing and will continue to change.&amp;rdquo;  That sounds great, but don&amp;rsquo;t expect too much.  There will still, they tell us, be a need for:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causes of High Mortality in People Labeled &#39;Mentally Ill&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 06:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ANOTHER VIDEO FROM DR. LIEBERMAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, made another video.  This one is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/813056&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;An Important Look at Mortality in Mental Illness: A Decade of Data on Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was made for Medscape.  You can see the transcript at the same site.  Medscape is a web resource for medical practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s commentary on an article that appeared in JAMA Psychiatry online on August 28:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1733743&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Comparative Mortality Risk in Adult Patients With Schizophrenia, Depression, Bipolar Disorder, Anxiety Disorders, and Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Participating in Psychopharmacology Clinical Trials&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Arif Khan, MD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Pursues JFK&#39;s Vision</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-pursues-jfk-s-vision/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 05:55:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-pursues-jfk-s-vision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 1, Psychiatric News published &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1765560&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;50 Years After: Will We Realize JFK’s Vision for Mental Health Care?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  Psychiatric News is an APA publication, and the piece was written by APA&amp;rsquo;s President, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman begins by reminding us that in 1963, President Kennedy signed the Community Mental Health Act (CMHA) into law.  Dr. Lieberman points out that the CMHA:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…was intended to set the foundation for contemporary mental health policy, one premised on the establishment of community-based care as an alternative to institutionalization.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman and &#39;60 Minutes&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 23, Psychiatric News (the APA&amp;rsquo;s media outlet) ran an article titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=1762017&#34;&gt;‘60 Minutes’ Interviews APA President on Schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The article was written by Mark Moran, a Psychiatric News reporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece opens with a quote from Jeffrey Lieberman, MD (President of the APA):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;&#39;60 Minutes&#39; showed a genuine interest beyond simply producing what was expected to be a popular segment and indicated a desire to do follow-up reporting on psychosis and violence.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/protecting-the-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/protecting-the-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/1636&#34;&gt;Safeguarding a Generation of Children from Over-diagnosis and Prescription of Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Dave Traxson, who works as an Educational Psychologist in the UK, and is posted on the  DxSummit website, an online platform for rethinking mental health, a forum in which the concepts underlying pharma-psychiatry are questioned and challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I view the trend towards mass medication of children with mind altering and potentially toxic drugs and ‘drug cocktails’ as a form of psycho-economic imperialism. By that I mean that young peoples’ developing minds are being colonized, using biochemicals, for huge commercial profit and in effect, increased social control. This has resulted from carefully constructed ‘business plans’ in boardrooms which some years ago saw the population of children in the western world as a great market expansion opportunity. The pharmaceutical companies have reaped the huge financial rewards of this rich and very bitter harvest ever since.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The New Holy Grail: Dysfunctional Neural Circuits</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 06:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org//newsArticle.aspx?articleid=1758579&#34;&gt;Change, Challenge, and Opportunity: Psychiatry Through the Looking Glass of Research&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s dated October 17, and was authored  by Steven Hyman, MD, and Jeffrey Lieberman, MD.  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;Mental Health Law on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is President of the APA.  Dr. Hyman was Director of NIMH from 1996 to 2001, and is now the Director of the Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research at the Broad Institute.  The Broad Institute is affiliated with Harvard University, and Dr. Hyman is a Harvard Distinguished Service Professor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Health Care Reform and Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 05:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an APA article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1748304&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Change, Challenge, and Opportunity: Psychiatry in the Age of Health Care Reform&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It was co-authored by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, and Howard Goldman, MD, PhD, and dated October 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article discusses the implications of the Affordable Care Act (Obamacare) for psychiatry, and also reviews progress of the 2008 Mental Health Parity Act.  The latter mandated that insurance coverage for &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses&amp;rdquo; be essentially on a par with coverage for general medical problems, but the act has not yet been implemented in its entirety.  The authors also point out that there are provisions in the ACA that focus on reform of the actual health care services, as well as the reform of health care insurance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Proposed Mental Health School Program</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-proposed-mental-health-school-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 06:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-proposed-mental-health-school-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 30, the Wisconsin State Journal posted an article online.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://host.madison.com/news/local/govt-and-politics/county-executive-joe-parisi-proposes-new-mental-health-program-for/article_7dc57b3e-4940-56ac-8b83-9f5a9be9617e.html&#34;&gt;County Executive Joe Parisi proposes new mental health program for county school district&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and was written by Andrea Anderson.  [Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;S. Randolph Kretchmar on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that Joe Parisi, the County Executive of Dane County, Wisconsin, is proposing to allocate $90,000 each to two school districts &amp;ldquo;…to treat student mental health…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Spin on the Navy Yard Murders</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 05:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has written a guest post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.everydayhealth.com/columns/health-answers/in-the-wake-of-the-navy-yard-shooting-a-way-forward/&#34;&gt;In the Wake of the Navy Yard Shooting: A Way Forward&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;on EverydayHealth.  Everyday Health Inc. is a media company which operates for-profit websites on health and related matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been confirmed that the Navy Yard shooter had been taking trazadone, an antidepressant of the serotonin antagonist and reuptake inhibitor (SARI) class, and the House Committee on Veterans&amp;rsquo; Affairs has indicated that it &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenewamerican.com/usnews/crime/item/16595-did-psychiatric-meds-cause-navy-yard-tragedy&#34;&gt;plans to investigate&lt;/a&gt; to what extent the drug might have been a causative factor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Latest</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 07:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 12, Jeffry Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, posted an article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1738168&#34;&gt;IPS to Feature Patrick Kennedy, Celebrate Community Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a preview of an APA conference scheduled for October 10-13 in Philadelphia: &amp;ldquo;Transforming Psychiatric Practice, Reforming Health Care Delivery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman tells us that he is very excited about the conference, and that the theme is particularly relevant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…given the changes we are experiencing in the profession and some of the exciting program events that I hope will support APA’s goal of being in the forefront of changes in the profession under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Lame Excuses from Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-lame-excuses-from-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 08:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-lame-excuses-from-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s that time of the month, and Dr. Lieberman has written another post, &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.pn.2013.9a7&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Change, Challenge and Opportunity: Psychiatry in Age of Reform and Enlightenment&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; on the APA&amp;rsquo;s website, Psychiatric News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He tells us that these are changing times, and that he, for one, is choosing to see these changes as positive.  He leads with a quote from Bob Dylan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The line it is drawn, The curse it is cast
The slow one now, Will later be fast
As the present now, Will later be past&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Neurology - A Merger in the Works?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-neurology---a-merger-in-the-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2013 06:29:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-neurology---a-merger-in-the-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of us on this side of the debate, who criticize psychiatry for medicalizing and drugging virtually every problem of human existence, sometimes ask the question:  If all these problems are truly illnesses of the brain, then why are they not being treated by neurologists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard psychiatric response to this question has been:  neurology deals with nervous system illnesses that result in problems of &lt;i&gt;movement&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;sensation&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;physical pain&lt;/i&gt;, etc.; psychiatry deals with nervous system problems that result in disordered &lt;i&gt;thinking,&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;feeling,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;general behavior&lt;/i&gt;.  Psychiatry has never produced the proof that these latter problems are caused by illnesses of the brain/nervous system, but that&amp;rsquo;s a separate issue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman is Back</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 05:45:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FearLoathingBTX&#34;&gt;Carl Elliott via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s latest post on Psychiatric News. It&amp;rsquo;s called – believe it or not – &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1723795&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Time to Re-Engage With Pharma? &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;dated August 1, 2013.  And it&amp;rsquo;s classic Dr. Lieberman sleight of hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His opening statement, for instance, reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drug companies aren’t held in high esteem by the public these days.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This may or may not be true.  But note what he&#39;s done.  The issue here is the long-standing and corrupt relationship &lt;i&gt;between psychiatry and the manufacturers of drugs&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;But from his first sentence, Dr. Lieberman has taken psychiatry out of the equation.  He has also lumped the makers of legitimate medicines in with the makers of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Is Back!  More Of The Same</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back-more-of-the-same/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 08:36:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back-more-of-the-same/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, thanks to a tweet from&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GingerBreggin&#34;&gt; Ginger Breggin&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Jeffrey Lieberman entitled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1715655&#34;&gt;Psychiatry: Nothing to Be Defensive About&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Dr. Lieberman is president of the APA, and has gone on record more than once as saying that all these dreadful criticisms of psychiatry are very unfair, and that psychiatrists are good guys who have the high moral ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, he&amp;rsquo;s back, and his current article is about on a par with previous efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Has the Moral High Ground (According to Jeffrey Lieberman)</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 05:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I suppose everyone knows by now, psychiatry has been on the receiving end of some very serious criticism in recent years.  The criticism has come from many sources, including: survivors of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; non-psychiatric mental health practitioners, journalists, the general public, and even from some psychiatrists themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the criticisms has been equally varied, and includes:  that the concept of mental illness is fundamentally spurious and devoid of explanatory significance; that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; (i.e. drugging people) is ineffective, physically damaging and disempowering; that psychiatry has forged and continues to maintain corrupt and corrupting relationships with the pharmaceutical industry with regards to the peddling of drugs and the hijacking of research for commercial ends; etc…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: How to Salvage a Shipwreck</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 05:48:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 was published on May 18, 2013, amidst great criticism.  The fundamental criticism was, and is, that the &lt;b&gt;problems listed in the manual are not &lt;i&gt;illnesses&lt;/i&gt; in any ordinary sense of the term&lt;/b&gt;.  Other critics focused on the pathologizing of normality, the expansion of the diagnostic net by the lowering of thresholds, and the lack of reliability of the so-called diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response from the psychiatric community has been mixed.  Some, probably most, psychiatrists are keeping their heads down, getting on with the business of selling pills, and hoping that the gravy train won&#39;t derail.  Others are busy at damage control&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Doesn&#39;t Get It</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 3-4 June, the Institute of Psychiatry in London hosted an international conference to mark the publication of DSM-5.  On June 10, Sir Simon Wessely, a department head at the Institute, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slam.nhs.uk/our-blog/brcu/dsm-5-at-the-iop&#34;&gt;DSM-5 at the IoP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The paper is a summary of the conference proceedings, and also, in many respects, a defense of DSM-5.  The article touches on many issues that are central to the current anti-psychiatry debate, and for this reason, I thought it might be helpful to take a close look at the piece.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 08:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 27, David Brooks, a New York Times columnist, wrote a piece on psychiatry called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/28/opinion/brooks-heroes-of-uncertainty.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Heroes of Uncertainty&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting and somewhat contradictory article.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As the handbook’s [DSM-5] many critics have noted, psychiatrists use terms like &#39;mental disorder&#39; and &#39;normal behavior,&#39; but there is no agreement on what these concepts mean.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;What psychiatrists call a disease is usually just a label for a group of symptoms.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Attempt to Defend DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 06:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 April, The Conversation ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/mental-disorders-debunking-some-myths-of-the-dsm-5-12047&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental disorders: debunking some myths of the DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Perminder Sachdev, MD.  Dr. Sachdev is a psychiatrist, and was a member of the DSM-5&amp;rsquo;s Neurocognitive Disorders Work Group.  He works at the School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Australia.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davetraxson&#34;&gt;Dave Traxson&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANALYSIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the title.  &amp;ldquo;…debunking some myths of the DSM-5.&amp;rdquo;  This sounds good.  You might get the impression that he&amp;rsquo;s going to address the myth of mental illness – the myth that all human problems are illnesses and are best treated by drugs.  But – alas – you would be mistaken.  Dr. Sachdev lists four myths that he plans to debunk.  He refers to these as the &amp;ldquo;…four key criticisms about DSM-5…&amp;rdquo;  Let&amp;rsquo;s examine what he says about these one by one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Strikes Back:  APA Responds to NIMH</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-apa-responds-to-nimh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 09:16:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-apa-responds-to-nimh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 3, 2013, David Kupfer MD (DSM-5 Task Force Chair) responded to Thomas Insel&amp;rsquo;s April 29&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; unequivocal attack on the validity and usefulness of DSM.  You can see Dr. Kupfer&amp;rsquo;s response &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Statement-from-dsm-chair-david-kupfer-md.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Essentially Dr. Insel said that the categories set out in the DSM did not correspond to anything in the real world, and that NIMH would no longer be using these categories as the basis for their research program.  This statement did not, however, represent any significant movement away from the biomedical model on the part of NIMH.  In fact, if anything, it was a movement towards an even &lt;i&gt;more&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;deeply entrenched&lt;/i&gt; medical model.  But it was a huge hit on DSM and on the APA, who tout the catalog as the basis to their claim to scientific credibility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
