<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Over-Medicalization of Everyday Life on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/over-medicalization-of-everyday-life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Over-Medicalization of Everyday Life on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 05:30:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/over-medicalization-of-everyday-life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances and the Increasing Use of Antidepressants</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 05:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-and-the-increasing-use-of-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 16, 2018, the prestigious and venerable psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, gave an interview to Christiane Amanpour on CNN.  You can see the video &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/videos/tv/2018/05/17/amanpour-allen-frances-antidepressants-interview.cnn&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;em&gt;How Antidepressant Withdrawal &amp;ldquo;Can Trap People&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how the interview opened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;CA:  &#34;So you know, I just wanted to start by saying that who knew that antidepressants were addictive.  It&#39;s not what you associate with things like antidepressants.  You think of pain-killers, obviously, and drugs and alcohol, and cigarettes.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are &#39;Psychiatric Disorders&#39; Brain Diseases?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-disorders-brain-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 05:30:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/are-psychiatric-disorders-brain-diseases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steven Reidbord MD is a board-certified psychiatrist who practices in San Francisco.  He writes a blog called Reidbord&amp;rsquo;s Reflections.  On December 12, 2015, he posted an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.stevenreidbordmd.com/?p=1107&#34;&gt;Are psychiatric disorders brain diseases?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting and thought-provoking piece, with many twists and turns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes, interspersed with my comments and reflections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Of the conditions deemed inherently psychiatric, some seem rooted in biological brain dysfunction.  Schizophrenia, autism, bipolar disorder, and severe forms of obsessive compulsive disorder and melancholic depression are often cited.  It’s important to note that their apparently biological nature derives from natural history and clinical presentation, not from diagnostic tests, and not because we know their root causes.  Schizophrenia, for example, runs in families, usually appears at a characteristic age, severely affects a diverse array of mental functions, looks very similar across cultures, and brings with it reliable if non-specific neuroanatomical changes.  Even though schizophrenia cannot be diagnosed under the microscope or on brain imaging, it is plausible that a biological mechanism eventually will be found.  (The same type of reasoning applied to AIDS before the discovery of HIV, and to many other medical diseases.)  A similar argument can be made for other putatively biological psychiatric disorders.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants:  Drugs, Not Medication</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 05:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-drugs-not-medication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 7, John Read, PhD, a psychologist at Swinburne University of Technology in Melbourne, published a short article on Mad in America.  The title is:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/04/largest-survey-date-finds-high-rates-emotional-interpersonal-adverse-effects-antidepressants/&#34;&gt;Largest Survey of Antidepressants Finds High Rates of Adverse Emotional and Interpersonal Effects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article presents the results of a survey conducted in New Zealand and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy-journal.com/article/S0165-1781%2814%2900083-3/abstract&#34;&gt;published online&lt;/a&gt; in February, 2014 in Psychiatry Research.  The survey involved 1,827 individuals who were taking antidepressants.  Dr. Read is widely published. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization or Compromise</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/polarization-or-compromise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/polarization-or-compromise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 2, Robert Whitaker published an article on Mad in America.  The title is &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/02/disability-mood-disorders-age-prozac/&#34;&gt;Disability and Mood Disorders in the Age of Prozac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  The article echoes and updates one of the themes of his 2010 book &#34;Anatomy of an Epidemic&#34;:  that the steady increase in the numbers of people receiving disability benefits for depression and mania is driven largely by the corresponding increase in the use of antidepressant drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Use of Neuroleptic Drugs As Chemical Restraints in Nursing Homes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-use-of-neuroleptic-drugs-as-chemical-restraints-in-nursing-homes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-use-of-neuroleptic-drugs-as-chemical-restraints-in-nursing-homes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the July-August 2014 issue of the AARP Bulletin.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aarp.org/health/drugs-supplements/info-2014/antipsychotics-overprescribed.html&#34;&gt;Drug Abuse: Antipsychotics in Nursing Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;and was written by Jan Goodwin.  AARP is the American Association of Retired Persons.   Jan Goodwin is an investigative journalist whose career, according to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Goodwin&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;…has been committed to focusing attention on social justice and human rights…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is essentially a condemnation of the widespread and long-standing practice of using neuroleptic drugs to suppress &amp;ldquo;difficult&amp;rdquo; behavior in nursing home residents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blame the Clients?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blame-the-clients/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 05:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blame-the-clients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 6, I wrote a post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/06/06/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry DID Promote the Chemical Imbalance Theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/06/psychiatry-promote-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;published on Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;, and generated a number of comments on that site, five of which were from TherapyFirst, who in his first comment identified himself as Joel Hassman, MD, a practicing psychiatrist.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hassman did not argue with the general notion that psychiatric practice today consists almost exclusively of the prescription of drugs.  Indeed, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantmedicatelife.com/2013/06/16/an-open-letter-to-graduating-psychiatry-residents/&#34;&gt;one of his own blog posts&lt;/a&gt; on June 16, 2013, he wrote in an open letter to newly qualified psychiatrists:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driving Under the Influence of Stimulants</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 05:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/driving-under-the-influence-of-stimulants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 22, I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/04/22/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on this general topic.  In that article I pointed out that the notion of stimulant prescription drugs improving the driving of people who &amp;ldquo;have ADHD&amp;rdquo; was gaining traction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since than I have come across two articles on this subject from Australia.  (Thanks to Nanu Grewal for the links.)  Both articles appeared in the Sunshine Coast Daily, and you can see them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/hospital-launches-complaints-probe/1122551/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunshinecoastdaily.com.au/news/crackdowntoo-late-for-twins-slow-action-way-too-la/1960148/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2009, four people, including five-year-old twin girls, died in a two-car accident.  The driver of one of the cars had been prescribed dexamphetamine for the treatment of ADHD by a local psychiatrist, and was found to have had six times the prescribed dosage of dexamphetamine in his system at the time of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants Make Things Worse in the Long Term</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-make-things-worse-in-the-long-term/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 05:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/antidepressants-make-things-worse-in-the-long-term/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In June 2011, Rif El-Mallakh, MD, et al. published an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.toxicpsychiatry.com/storage/antidep%20El-Mallakh-tardivedysphoriadarticle1.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tardive dysphoria:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The role of long term antidepressant use in inducing chronic depression&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in Medical Hypotheses.  The article is a thorough and wide-ranging study review.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Here are some quotes from the abstract:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;Treatment-resistant and chronic depression appear to be increasing.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;Depressed patients who ultimately become treatment resistant frequently have had a positive initial response to antidepressants and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;invariably&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; have received these agents for prolonged time periods at high doses.&#34; [Emphasis added]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benzodiazepines: Disempowering and Dangerous</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-disempowering-and-dangerous/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 05:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-disempowering-and-dangerous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I recently read an article by Fredric Neuman, MD, Director of the Anxiety and Phobia Center at White Plains Hospital, NY.  The article is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/fighting-fear/201206/the-use-the-minor-tranquilizers-xanax-ativan-klonopin-and-valium&#34;&gt;The Use of the Minor Tranquilizers: Xanax, Ativan, Klonopin, and Valium&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and was published in June 2012 by Psychology Today.  Thanks to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/medskep&#34;&gt;Medicalskeptic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; for the link.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Neuman opens by telling us that benzodiazepines are &amp;ldquo;…very commonly prescribed for any sort of discomfort.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benzodiazepines:  Dangerous Drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-dangerous-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 05:58:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-dangerous-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On February 25, Kristina Fiore published an article on MedPage today.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medpagetoday.com/PainManagement/PainManagement/44481&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Killing Pain: Xanax Tops Charts&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The article is based on a study conducted by Jann M et al, and published in the February 2014 issue of the Journal of Pharmacy Practice.  The study is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24436437&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Benzodiazepines: a major component in unintentional prescription drug overdoses with opioid analgesics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;During 2003 to 2009, the 2 prescriptions drugs with the highest increase in death rates were oxycodone 264.6% and alprazolam 233.8%. Therefore, benzodiazepines have a significant impact on prescription drug unintentional overdoses second only to the opioid analgesics. The combination prescribing of benzodiazepines and opioid analgesics commonly takes place. The pharmacokinetic drug interactions between benzodiazepines and opioid analgesics are complex. The pharmacodynamic actions of these agents differ as their combined effects produce significant respiratory depression.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Psychology Going the Way of Psychiatry?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/is-psychology-going-the-way-of-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 05:45:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/is-psychology-going-the-way-of-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 7, Maria Bradshaw, co-founder of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.casper.org.nz/&#34;&gt;CASPER&lt;/a&gt;, published an interesting article on Mad in America.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/01/prescribing-rights-psychologists/&#34;&gt;Prescribing Rights for Psychologists&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and it suggests that psychology as a profession may be falling into some of the same errors that enmire psychiatry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria makes some very compelling points, and focuses particularly on the fact that psychologists have won prescribing rights in a number of jurisdictions, and are engaged in an ongoing effort to expand this aspect of their work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Human Behavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 05:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/understanding-human-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A couple of months ago I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/11/21/is-electroconvulsive-therapy-ect-effective/&#34;&gt;article concerning ECT&lt;/a&gt; which generated some controversy.  One of the issues that came up was the relationship between &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;biological &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;explanations of human activity and more global explanations, which, for want of a better term, I&amp;rsquo;ll call person-centered explanations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any human activity can be viewed from different levels of abstraction.  Suppose, for instance, that I am sitting in my living room reading a book.  Then I put the book down, stand up, and go outside.  If the question were to be asked:  why did he put the book down and go outside? A wide range of perspectives and answers are possible.  One could, for instance, focus on the fact that I am a biological organism, and one could develop a detailed and comprehensive flow sheet of every muscle movement, every heartbeat, every sensory input, neural impulse etc., that had occurred from the moment that I put the book down until I was standing outside.  Such an account might be more or less detailed.  There would, of course, be physical limitations on the amount of information of this sort that is attainable, but from a theoretical point of view, one could compile a detailed, complete, and accurate biological account of the actions in question.  And such an account would be a valid response to the question:  why did he put the book down and go outside.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sandcastle Continues to Crumble:  ADHD Does Not Exist</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 05:48:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-sandcastle-continues-to-crumble-adhd-does-not-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;BOOK PREVIEW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Richard C. Saul, MD
&lt;em&gt;ADHD Does Not Exist:  The Truth About Attention Deficit and Hyperactivity Disorder&lt;/em&gt;
Publication date:  February 18, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;************************&lt;/p&gt;
Those of us on this side of the psychiatry debate have been saying for decades that the condition known as ADHD is not an illness, but is rather an arbitrarily delineated cluster of vaguely defined problems that children have acquired in various ways.  We have also pointed out that psychiatry&#39;s labeling of this condition as an illness is simply another instance of their inexorable turf expansion, and that their widespread drugging of the individuals so labeled is destructive and disempowering.
&lt;p&gt;And, also for decades, psychiatry has been marginalizing us as unscientific mental illness deniers, who seek to put the clock back and deprive people suffering from this &amp;ldquo;illness&amp;rdquo; of the vital &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; that they so desperately need.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training the Psychiatrists of the Future (According to Dr. Lieberman): More Cheerleading</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 05:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA and Chair of Psychiatry at Columbia University, published a post on November 26 on Psychiatric News.  The article is called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1787247&#34;&gt;Training the Psychiatrists of the Future&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and is co-authored by Richard Summers, MD.  Dr. Summers is a Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Lieberman and Summers open by telling us that psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; roles &amp;ldquo;…are changing and will continue to change.&amp;rdquo;  That sounds great, but don&amp;rsquo;t expect too much.  There will still, they tell us, be a need for:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children: Harvard&#39;s Shame</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 05:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2012, Mark Olfson, MD, et al, published an article in the Archives of General Psychiatry.  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22868273&#34;&gt;National Trends in the Office-Based Treatment of Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The authors collected data from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Surveys for the period 1993-2009, and looked for trends in antipsychotic prescribing for children, adolescents, and adults in outpatient visits.  Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;&lt;!--
table { 	border: 1px solid gray;     	border-collapse: collapse;      	width: 500px;   	cellspacing: 0; } th {     	background-color: #eee;          border: 1px solid black; }  th#blank {     	background- color: #FFF;  }  th.colOne {         width: 100px; } td {     	text-align: center;  	border: 1px solid black; } table#diagnosis th.data {         width: 120px; }
--&gt;&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;antipsychoticRX&#34; cellspacing=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;colOne&#34;&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Increase in no. of antipsychotic prescriptions per 100 population (1993-2009)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0-13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.24-1.83 (almost 8-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;14-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.78-3.76 (almost 5-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;21+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25-6.18 (almost 2-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;The authors provide a breakdown of the diagnoses assigned to the children and adolescents during the antipsychotic visits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causes of High Mortality in People Labeled &#39;Mentally Ill&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 06:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ANOTHER VIDEO FROM DR. LIEBERMAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, made another video.  This one is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/813056&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;An Important Look at Mortality in Mental Illness: A Decade of Data on Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was made for Medscape.  You can see the transcript at the same site.  Medscape is a web resource for medical practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s commentary on an article that appeared in JAMA Psychiatry online on August 28:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1733743&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Comparative Mortality Risk in Adult Patients With Schizophrenia, Depression, Bipolar Disorder, Anxiety Disorders, and Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Participating in Psychopharmacology Clinical Trials&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Arif Khan, MD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Care For Your Mind (CFYM): A New Advocacy Group</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 06:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 27, Psychiatric Services, a journal of the APA, published an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1745505&#34;&gt;Blog Brings Doctors, Patients Together to Address MH Issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It was written by Vabren Watts, a Psychiatric News Journalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a booster piece for the recently-formed CFYM (Care For Your Mind):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…an online forum for people with mood disorders—along with their families and psychiatrists—to discuss the mental health care system and changes that may affect them under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Allen Frances – Lucy Johnstone Debate</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 05:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Allen Frances, MD, Chairperson of the DSM-IV task force, published an article on Psychology Today.  It is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201310/does-it-make-sense-scrap-psychiatric-diagnosis-0&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Does It Make Sense To Scrap Psychiatric Diagnosis?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and is essentially a response to the British Psychological Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Clinical Psychology&amp;rsquo;s (DCP) call to abandon the medical model in situations where it is not appropriate, and to embrace a psychosocial approach.  You can see a copy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;DCP&amp;rsquo;s May 13, 2013, statement here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Psychiatric Case Study.  A Sad Story</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-psychiatric-case-study-a-sad-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 06:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-psychiatric-case-study-a-sad-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the criticisms that I routinely make of psychiatry is that its primary agenda during initial evaluations is the assignment of a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis,&amp;rdquo; and that ongoing &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; consists of 15-minute &amp;ldquo;med checks,&amp;rdquo; during which drug regimens are changed and adjusted.  The essence of my criticism is that this kind of approach&lt;strong&gt; inevitably oversimplifies human problems, and in practice does more harm than good&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My contentions in this regard have from time to time been challenged.  It has been said that my portrayal of psychiatry is a kind of misleading caricature, and that in reality, psychiatrists do, in fact, concern themselves with human issues over and above &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and drugs.  This debate will, of course, continue, but I recently read an article on Psychiatric Times that has some bearing on the matter.  [Thanks to Nick Stuart for the link.]  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/ptsd/conduct-disorder-adhd%E2%80%94or-something-else-altogether?GUID=4FCB4641-7FC8-4BA6-B25E-F52C8AD7E802&amp;amp;rememberme=1&amp;amp;ts=17102013&#34;&gt;Conduct Disorder, ADHD – or Something Else Altogether?&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;The author is Steven Dilsaver, MD, and the piece is dated October 11, 2013.  The article is a case study of the psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of an eight-year-old boy (John).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Stigma Attached to &#39;Mental Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 06:30:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Monday, October 7, 2013, The Sun, a British tabloid newspaper ran the following headline:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/5183994/1200-killed-by-mental-patients-in-shock-10-year-toll.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1,200 Killed By Mental Patients.  Shock 10-year toll exposes care crisis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  It took up almost all of the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The headline precipitated a great deal of protest from politicians, advocacy groups, mental health professionals, and others.  The general points in most of these protests were that the headline was sensationalistic, misleading, and would serve to increase the stigma associated with &amp;ldquo;mental illness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overall Efficacy of Mental Health Treatment</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/overall-efficacy-of-mental-health-treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2013 08:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/overall-efficacy-of-mental-health-treatment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article by J. Sareen et al on Cambridge Journals Online, September 2013.  It&amp;rsquo;s call &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;amp;aid=8965169&amp;amp;fulltextType=RA&amp;amp;fileId=S003329171200284X&#34;&gt;Common mental disorder diagnosis and need for treatment are not the same: findings from a population-based survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  Five of the six authors are working at universities in Canada, the sixth at a university in California.  [Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/08/diagnosis-and-the-need-for-treatment-are-not-linked/&#34;&gt;Mad in America&lt;/a&gt; for the link to the abstract.  The full article is, unfortunately, behind a paywall.]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Burden of Mental &#39;Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 09:51:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GrahamCLDavey&#34;&gt;Graham Davey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/socratext&#34;&gt;Richard Pemberton&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link to an interesting article in the August 29, 2013 issue of the Lancet.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/GBD-Mental-2010-from-Lancet.pdf&#34;&gt;Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Harvey A. Whiteford, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Burden of Disease survey is a systematic, scientific attempt to quantify the comparative magnitude of disease, injuries, and risk factors by age, sex, and geography over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Madness Contested: An Outstanding Book</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 06:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/madness-contested-an-outstanding-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;i&gt;Madness Contested &lt;/i&gt;has recently been published by PCCS Books.  It&amp;rsquo;s a collection of articles, edited by Steven Coles, Sarah Keenan, and Bob Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a remarkable piece of work.  It covers just about every contentious concept in the present &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; debate, and brings to bear an abundance of new insights and up-to-date research findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 21 articles plus an introduction by the editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the name of each article with a brief quotation from each:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parental Influences</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/parental-influences/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 06:05:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/parental-influences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If we&amp;rsquo;re happy to take some of the credit for our children&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;successes&lt;/i&gt;, we should also accept a share of the responsibility when they &lt;i&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t do so well&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 70&amp;rsquo;s, I met an elderly gentleman in a social context.  I&amp;rsquo;ll call him James.  He was in his early 80&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got to talking, and found that we had a good deal in common – primarily a love for the land, the forests, gardening, and just generally being active.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Never Mind The Facts; Just Sell More Pills</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 05:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article, recently published in Journal of Contemporary Psychotherapy, on Springer Link.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10879-013-9244-x/fulltext.html&#34;&gt;Shooting the Messenger: The Case of ADHD&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and it was written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently some of the authors had noted in 1995 a marked increase in the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of the condition known as ADHD in southeastern Virginia.  This is a large urban conglomeration of six different cities, including Norfolk, Portsmouth, and Virginia Beach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Psycho-Pharma Drugs Have Any Legitimate Function?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-psycho-pharma-drugs-have-any-legitimate-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 06:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-psycho-pharma-drugs-have-any-legitimate-function/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last ten years or so, the anti-psychiatry movement has been gaining adherents, and has been growing more focused and more outspoken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we are not a unified group.  I, for instance, take what I think would be considered a fairly extreme position.  I believe that there are no mental illnesses; that the clusters of thoughts, feelings, and actions labeled as mental illnesses are better conceptualized as habits that have been acquired in accordance with the normal principles of behavior acquisition or as understandable responses to extreme life stressors.  I further believe that conceptualizing these problems as illnesses has been disastrous for the individuals involved, and for society in general.  In particular, I believe that psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s promotion of the idea that all problematic thinking, feeling, and behaving is caused by brain illnesses and can only be treated with drugs is causing extraordinary levels of physical damage to their clients.  It is also severely stigmatizing and disempowering.  As a culture, we are losing the notion that people can improve their lives through effort and application, and through mutual assistance and support.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics and Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-and-alzheimer-s-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 08:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-and-alzheimer-s-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned the CATIE study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/07/16/the-cafe-study-dr-liebermans-high-moral-ground/&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.  CATIE (Clinical Antipsychotic Trials of Intervention Effectiveness) was a NIMH-funded double blinded, randomized controlled trial comparing the effectiveness and side effects of newer-generation neuroleptics versus an older neuroleptic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/CATIE-AD.pdf&#34;&gt;CATIE-AD&lt;/a&gt; was a part of CATIE.  The AD stands for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease.  CATIE-AD was published in the New England Journal of Medicine in October 2006.  The results of the study were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;There were no significant differences among treatments with regard to the time to the discontinuation of treatment for any reason&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Intrinsically Flawed and Rotten</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter yesterday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobStamatakis&#34;&gt;Robert Stamatakis&lt;/a&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have to ask, I don&#39;t understand.  Do you work in the UK?  Your descriptions of psychiatry are nothing I recognize.  These descriptions of psychiatry are nothing like the practice I see on a daily basis.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
I am certainly a very outspoken critic of psychiatry, and in that regard Robert&#39;s question/challenge is a fair one, to which I will try to respond.
&lt;p&gt;My primary criticism of modern psychiatry – and indeed the criticism that underpins all the others – is that its fundamental concepts are spurious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry: The Science That Isn&#39;t</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-science-that-isn-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2013 13:37:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-science-that-isn-t/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very important article on Mad in America.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/07/does-nimh-follow-the-rules-of-science-a-startling-study-2/&#34;&gt;Does NIMH Follow the Rules of Science? A Startling Study&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;by Niall McLaren, MD, dated July 9, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. McLaren is an Australian psychiatrist who has relentlessly combed the literature for proof of the fundamental psychiatric claim – &amp;ldquo;…that a full understanding of the brain will give a full understanding of mental disorder, with no questions unanswered.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He found &lt;i&gt;nothing&lt;/i&gt; in the way of proof!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mid-Life Crisis</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mid-life-crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 14:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mid-life-crisis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently on Twitter, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ambtax1&#34;&gt;Disparity&lt;/a&gt; asked for my opinion on the term mid-life crisis, which &amp;ldquo;…is often treated as a mental health condition.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term mid-life crisis has no formal meaning in mental health, though as Disparity says, the concept does emerge from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original meaning of the word &lt;em&gt;crisis&lt;/em&gt; was a turning point in an illness.  In the past forty of fifty years, the connotation has extended to embrace almost any kind of challenging situation or adverse event.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptic Drugs and Children: Wrong Focus</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-children-wrong-focus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 04:13:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-children-wrong-focus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that psychiatry has done, and continues to do, a great deal of damage to people it claims to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the damage done by neuroleptic drugs is among the most severe.  The increasing use of these products ought to be a huge cause for concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;i&gt;particularly&lt;/i&gt; true in that &lt;strong&gt;these very toxic drugs are being administered with increasing frequency to &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; – even to children as young as two years old!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Has the Moral High Ground (According to Jeffrey Lieberman)</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 05:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I suppose everyone knows by now, psychiatry has been on the receiving end of some very serious criticism in recent years.  The criticism has come from many sources, including: survivors of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; non-psychiatric mental health practitioners, journalists, the general public, and even from some psychiatrists themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the criticisms has been equally varied, and includes:  that the concept of mental illness is fundamentally spurious and devoid of explanatory significance; that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; (i.e. drugging people) is ineffective, physically damaging and disempowering; that psychiatry has forged and continues to maintain corrupt and corrupting relationships with the pharmaceutical industry with regards to the peddling of drugs and the hijacking of research for commercial ends; etc…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blaenau Gwent, Wales: One in Six on Antidepressants!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 05:33:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blaenau-gwent-wales-one-in-six-on-antidepressants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a Mail Online article about &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2351291/One-people-town-anti-depressants-Is-local-GPs-fear-benefits.html&#34;&gt;high numbers of antidepressant prescriptions in Blaenau Gwent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The article is dated June 29, and was drawn to my attention by Nanu Grewal from Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is about a town in Wales where reportedly one sixth of the population is taking antidepressants.  That&amp;rsquo;s about 17%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So presumably all these people have brain disease.  Or perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s because the unemployment rate is double the national average.  That in itself is depressing, but to make matters even worse, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of depression can reportedly help a person qualify for additional government benefits – a strong temptation for people living below the poverty line.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: How to Salvage a Shipwreck</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 05:48:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-how-to-salvage-a-shipwreck/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DSM-5 was published on May 18, 2013, amidst great criticism.  The fundamental criticism was, and is, that the &lt;b&gt;problems listed in the manual are not &lt;i&gt;illnesses&lt;/i&gt; in any ordinary sense of the term&lt;/b&gt;.  Other critics focused on the pathologizing of normality, the expansion of the diagnostic net by the lowering of thresholds, and the lack of reliability of the so-called diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response from the psychiatric community has been mixed.  Some, probably most, psychiatrists are keeping their heads down, getting on with the business of selling pills, and hoping that the gravy train won&#39;t derail.  Others are busy at damage control&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRI&#39;s: The Down Side</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ssri-s-the-down-side/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2013 06:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ssri-s-the-down-side/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;David Healy, MD, is a controversial figure.  On the one hand, he is a fierce and determined opponent of the escalating use of antidepressant drugs.  On the other hand, he is one of the world&amp;rsquo;s leading proponents of electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the latter reason, I&amp;rsquo;m somewhat hesitant to quote his work, but he writes good anti-antidepressant articles, and his points are usually well-researched and compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://davidhealy.org/prozac-and-ssris-twenty-fifth-anniversary/&#34;&gt;Prozac and SSRIs: Twenty-fifth Anniversary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; which Dr. Healy wrote in February of this year.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What &lt;em&gt;Is&lt;/em&gt; Mental Illness?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 08:50:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/what-em-is-em-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently received the following question from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ambtax1&#34;&gt;Disparity&lt;/a&gt;, on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I&#39;m interested in all your posts, but they&#39;re always telling us what mental illness &#39;isn&#39;t.&#39;  Do you have many on what it &#39;is&#39;?&lt;/p&gt;
I referred him/her to the post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2012/06/01/there-are-no-mental-illnesses/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;There are No Mental Illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and received the following reply:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have read it a few times.  I largely agree with it.  But &#39;something&#39; happens to people.  Whatever the label.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
Questions of this sort arise fairly frequently, and I thought it might be helpful to write a post.
&lt;p&gt;WHAT HAPPENS TO PEOPLE?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going Against the Stream</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/going-against-the-stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 09:11:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/going-against-the-stream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AN INTERESTING STORY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I came across the following on Twitter from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Sectioned_&#34;&gt;Mental Health @Sectioned_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I just met someone who told me their remarkable story about falling down the rabbit hole into psychiatric sectioning and forced medication.  I listened with fascination to their intricate story in all its twists and turns, looping backwards and forwards with incredible details.  The longer we spoke the more was revealed, the crazier and more believable it sounded.  I was listening, probing for clarification, trying to grasp what happened and why.  First the overview, then the highlights, then more details, expanding out, backing round, drawing me in.  There were many parallels in our stories, and many contrasts.  It reminded me why I don&#39;t really talk in detail about what happened to me: because, if you&#39;ve not experienced it, it sounds unbelievable.  Unless you&#39;ve experienced the scorching reality of forced drugging, seclusion, assault by nurses and patients, it sounds like a mad fantasy.  It&#39;s too far outside most people&#39;s realities for them to contemplate it being true, and so quietly assume you&#39;re deluded.  So it smooths life&#39;s path to make light, to skirt over the details, to change the topic.  And sometimes, sometimes, when I meet someone who&#39;s been through something similar, I listen to their story and realize I&#39;m not the only one.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kinderman-Pies Debate</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 08:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-kinderman-pies-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 15, Peter Kinderman, PhD, of the University of Liverpool, posted an article on DxSummit.org.  It was called &lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/197&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;So…What Happens Next?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article was that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are conceptually spurious, unhelpful, and even hindersome in practice, and discourage practitioners from pursuing genuine explanations for the problems clients bring to their attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an excellent piece, and I did a short post in which I recommended it strongly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Attempt to Defend DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 06:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/an-attempt-to-defend-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 April, The Conversation ran an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.com/mental-disorders-debunking-some-myths-of-the-dsm-5-12047&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mental disorders: debunking some myths of the DSM-5&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Perminder Sachdev, MD.  Dr. Sachdev is a psychiatrist, and was a member of the DSM-5&amp;rsquo;s Neurocognitive Disorders Work Group.  He works at the School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Australia.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davetraxson&#34;&gt;Dave Traxson&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANALYSIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the title.  &amp;ldquo;…debunking some myths of the DSM-5.&amp;rdquo;  This sounds good.  You might get the impression that he&amp;rsquo;s going to address the myth of mental illness – the myth that all human problems are illnesses and are best treated by drugs.  But – alas – you would be mistaken.  Dr. Sachdev lists four myths that he plans to debunk.  He refers to these as the &amp;ldquo;…four key criticisms about DSM-5…&amp;rdquo;  Let&amp;rsquo;s examine what he says about these one by one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Still Under Fire</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-still-under-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 21:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-still-under-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mental Health Europe (MHE) is a non-governmental organization &amp;ldquo;… committed to the promotion of positive mental health and well-being, the prevention of mental health problems, the improvement of care, advocacy for social inclusion and the protection of the human rights of (ex)users of mental health services and their families and carers.&amp;rdquo;  It is composed of associations, organizations, and individuals who are active in the mental health field, including users and ex-users of services, volunteers, and professionals.  MHE subscribes to the following values: dignity and respect; equal opportunities; freedom of choice; non-discrimination, social inclusion, democracy and participation.  You can read more about them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mhe-sme.org/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 08:10:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of all the evils perpetrated by American psychiatry in the past 60 years, the administration of neuroleptic drugs to children is arguably the worst.  And it is a practice that is growing each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential purpose of these drugs is to make people more docile and more easily managed by &lt;strong&gt;destroying brain tissue&lt;/strong&gt;.  The side effects are devastating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently Gabrielle Carson, MD, a psychiatrist at Stony Brook Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital, wrote a paper on &lt;i&gt;The Dramatic Rise in Neuroleptic Use In Children: Why Do We Do It and What Does It Buy Us?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see Dr. Carlson&amp;rsquo;s commentary &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/carlson-on-neuroleptics_aaps.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yobluemama2&#34;&gt;yobluemama2&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for flagging the article.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with DSM</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 08:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-problem-with-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the NY Times Sunday review.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/12/opinion/sunday/why-the-fuss-over-the-dsm-5.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It was written by Sally Satel MD, a psychiatrist, currently a resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is called:  &amp;ldquo;Why the Fuss Over the DSM-5?&amp;rdquo;  Dr. Satel&amp;rsquo;s central point is that psychiatrists only treat &lt;i&gt;symptoms&lt;/i&gt; anyway and pay little attention to the DSM.  She expresses the belief that the manual&amp;rsquo;s diagnoses are &amp;ldquo;…passports to insurance coverage, the keys to special education and behavioral services in school and the tickets to disability benefits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talk Therapy for Schizophrenia</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 21:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/talk-therapy-for-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on Vermont&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Seven Days&lt;/i&gt;.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Burlington&amp;rsquo;s HowardCenter Tries a New Approach to Treating Mental Illness: More Talk, Fewer Meds.&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.7dvt.com/2013burlingtons-howardcenter-tries-new-approach-treating-mental-illness-more-talking-fewer-meds&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Steven_Coles_&#34;&gt;Steven Coles&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently Vermont&amp;rsquo;s Department of Mental Health is promoting a &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; kind of treatment for psychosis:  talk therapy.  The project leader is Dr. Sandra Steingard, who for most of her career accepted the orthodox view of schizophrenia and the need for neuroleptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s a Great Day for Humanity</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/it-s-a-great-day-for-humanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 22:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/it-s-a-great-day-for-humanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, after two years of deliberation, the Division of Clinical Psychology (which is part of the British Psychological Society)  issued a &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;Position Statement on the Classification of Behavior and Experience in Relation to Functional Psychiatric Diagnosis.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt; It is subtitled &amp;ldquo;Time for a Paradigm Shift.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DCP summarizes its paper as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The DCP is of the view that it is timely and appropriate to affirm publicly that the current classification system as outlined in DSM and ICD, in respect of the functional psychiatric diagnoses, has significant conceptual and empirical limitations. Consequently, there is a need for a paradigm shift in relation to the experiences that these diagnoses refer to, towards a conceptual system not based on a ‘disease’ model.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Article by Brett Jason Deacon</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/great-article-by-brett-jason-deacon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2013 08:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/great-article-by-brett-jason-deacon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the current issue of Clinical Psychology Review (April 8, 2013), you will find a very interesting article by Brett Jason Deacon, PhD, who is an Associate Professor of Psychology at the University of Wyoming.  The article is called &lt;i&gt;The Biomedical Model of Mental Disorder: A Critical Analysis of its Tenets, Consequences, and Effects on Psychotherapy Research&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/Deacon-biomedical-model-and-stigma-2013.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a critique of the biomedical model from a theoretical and a practical perspective.  The author has managed to elucidate a comprehensive range of criticisms of the biomedical model, and has blended them together into a coherent and compelling account.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – Embracing a Social Paradigm?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 07:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the May 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;The future of academic psychiatry may be social&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt;by Stefan Priebe, Tom Burns, and Tom K. J. Craig.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NSVo2eU9meHQtOUU/edit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The past 30 years have produced no discoveries leading to major changes in psychiatric practice. The rules regulating research and a dominant neurobiological paradigm may both have stifled creativity. Embracing a social paradigm could generate real progress and, simultaneously, make the profession more attractive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Distress Is Not An Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 06:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-distress-is-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uilleannair&#34;&gt;Sam Thompson&lt;/a&gt; (University of Liverpool) posted the following tweet on April 27:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Can anyone point me to a good, succinct summary of the case for equating mental distress with illness?  (serious, non-sarcastic question)&lt;/p&gt;
On the face of it, this looks like a straightforward question, and one might think that a straightforward answer could be found.  But this is not the case, because ultimately it boils down to a matter of definition.  And psychiatry is a field where &lt;strong&gt;definitions are notoriously fuzzy&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;MENTAL DISORDER&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transforming Diagnosis:  The Thomas Insel Article</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 21:06:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 29, Thomas Insel, Director of NIMH, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;Transforming Diagnosis&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/2013/130429NIMHTransformingDiagnosis.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Insel is critical of DSM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;While DSM has been described as a &#39;Bible&#39; for the field, it is, at best, a dictionary, creating a set of labels and defining each.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The weakness is its lack of validity.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This has created quite a stir, in that it appears to support the position of those of us who have been criticizing the DSM on these kinds of grounds for decades.  It also suggests a fundamental rift between the NIMH and the APA, two groups who up till now had appeared to be joined at the hip.
&lt;p&gt;The article has generated a great deal of comment.  So far, there&amp;rsquo;s been nothing from the APA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Effect of DSM</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 12:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep two dictionaries on my desk.  The first is a 1964 Webster&amp;rsquo;s; the second is a 2009 Webster&amp;rsquo;s.  This morning I looked up the word &amp;ldquo;depression&amp;rdquo; in both books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1964:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;n. &lt;b&gt;1.&lt;/b&gt; a depressing or being depressed.  &lt;b&gt;2.&lt;/b&gt; a depressed part or place; hollow or low place.  &lt;b&gt;3.&lt;/b&gt; low spirits; dejection.  &lt;b&gt;4.&lt;/b&gt; a decrease in force, activity, amount, etc.  &lt;b&gt;5.&lt;/b&gt; a period marked by slackening of business activity, much unemployment, falling prices and wages, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Mental Illness&#34; Under Fire</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-under-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-illness-under-fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a very interesting article by Paris Williams on Mad in America, &lt;i&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Mental Illness&amp;rdquo; Paradigm: An &amp;ldquo;Illness&amp;rdquo; That is out of Control.&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/05/the-mental-illness-paradigm-itself-an-illness-that-is-out-of-control/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author gives us a compelling critique of the &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; model, and also presents us with an &lt;strong&gt;alternative paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;… to see those conditions we generally refer to as &#39;mental illnesses&#39; as instead the natural manifestations of an individual’s struggles with the fundamental dilemmas inherent in simply being alive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Need More Mental Health Services?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-need-more-mental-health-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 12:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-need-more-mental-health-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Sandy Hook massacre, there were a great many calls for &amp;ldquo;more mental health services&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;better access to mental health services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us on this side of the fence groaned, because we knew that any official or private response to this call would be on the lines of more of the same.  The same &lt;strong&gt;spurious concepts&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;pseudo-illnesses&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;destructive drugging&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;destructive electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;; the same &lt;strong&gt;involuntary confinement&lt;/strong&gt;; and the same &lt;strong&gt;stigmatization and loss of empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bereavement:  An &#34;Opportunity&#34; for Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 10:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new post on Mick Bramham&amp;rsquo;s website called &amp;ldquo;A time to grieve, a time to console, and a time to profit?&amp;rdquo;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.mythsandrisks.info/2013/04/a-time-to-grieve-time-to-console-and.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have thought that, given the adverse publicity that pharma has been receiving in recent years, they would be easing up on their expansionist agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you would be wrong.  The &lt;strong&gt;APA has declared open season on bereavement&lt;/strong&gt;, and although DSM-5 won&amp;rsquo;t be released for a few more weeks, &lt;strong&gt;Eli Lilly is already grooming their SNRI Cymbalta as a &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for this pseudo illness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and the Other Professions</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 09:33:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-and-the-other-professions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t have precise figures, but I would guess that psychiatrists constitute less than 5% of the professional staff in the mental health system  The other 95% are psychologists, counselors, social workers, case managers, behavior analysts, case aides, art therapists, occupational therapists, job coaches, etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these other professions have specialized training, both theoretical and practical, and it is reasonable to suppose that they bring to their jobs a &lt;strong&gt;wide range of conceptual orientations&lt;/strong&gt;, and an equally &lt;strong&gt;wide range of practical skills.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Good Website:  by Mick Bramham</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 09:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-good-website-by-mick-bramham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across &lt;i&gt;Thinking About Mental Health: Myths, treatment risks &amp;amp; alternatives.&lt;/i&gt;  You can find it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s written by Mick Bramham, from Dorset, England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythsandrisks.info/chemical-imbalances.html&#34;&gt;Depression: Serotonin Imbalance?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The whole idea of antidepressants supposedly correcting chemical imbalances has more to do with drug company marketing than evidence-based science.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Unfortunately, drug companies are known to exaggerate the benefits of their products and to play down the risks;&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Anxiety Disorder: Now Also for Adults</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of separation anxiety disorder has been around since DSM-III.  In DSM-IV it is defined as &amp;ldquo;…excessive anxiety concerning separation from the home or from those to whom the person is attached.&amp;rdquo;  (DSM-IV-TR p 121).  The APA&amp;rsquo;s prevalence estimate is 4%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is listed under the heading: &amp;ldquo;Other Disorders of Infancy, Childhood, or Adolescence.&amp;rdquo;  One of the criteria is that the problem must begin before age 18, and in practice the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; was generally confined to children under the age of 10 or so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Major Tranquilizers Make Things Worse?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 09:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-major-tranquilizers-make-things-worse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 19 of this year an article by Martin Harrow and Thomas Jobe was published in the Schizophrenia Bulletin:  &lt;i&gt;Does Long-Term Treatment of Schizophrenia with Antipsychotic Medications Facilitate Recovery?&lt;/i&gt;  You can see it&lt;a href=&#34;http://femhc.org/Portals/2/Publications/FEMHC%20Grant%20Project%20Publications/2013_March19_Harrow_Jobe_SchizophreniaBulletin_Do%20Long-Term%20Tx%20of%20Schiz%20w%20Antipsychotics%20Facilitate%20Recovery.pdf&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.  The term &amp;ldquo;antipsychotics&amp;rdquo; embraces drugs such as Haldol, Risperdal, Thorazine, etc…  I prefer the term major tranquilizers, because it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Harrow and Job have conducted a long-term (15-20 year) study of people diagnosed with the condition known as schizophrenia. They found that individuals who had been given &amp;ldquo;anti-psychotics&amp;rdquo; continuously for these long periods showed &amp;ldquo;…considerable psychopathology and few sustained periods of recovery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survivor&#39;s Story:  The Dark Threads</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 09:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-survivor-s-story-the-dark-threads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just read &lt;em&gt;The Dark Threads,&lt;/em&gt; by Jean Davison (Accent Press Ltd, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s autobiographical, and describes with great detail and insight how a young woman of 18 years, whose only problem was acute shyness coupled with a yearning for some meaning in life, made the mistake of visiting a psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jean describes how she was &lt;strong&gt;bullied into accepting psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; She was &lt;strong&gt;drugged into a zombie-like stupor and given electric shock &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;  &lt;/strong&gt;She describes graphically the disempowering and humiliating aspects of &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; and the endless patronizing condescension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bereavement Exclusion and DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 14:09:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of major depressive &lt;i&gt;disorder&lt;/i&gt; is based on the presence of a major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;, in turn, is defined by the presence of five or more items from the following list during a two-week period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) depressed mood most of the day, nearly every day, as indicated by either subjective report (e.g., feels sad or empty) or observation made by others (e.g., appears tearful). Note&lt;b&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; In children and adolescents, can be irritable mood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPs Prescribe More Psychotropic Drugs than Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 10:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/gps-prescribe-more-psychotropic-drugs-than-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Psychiatrists, when challenged about the massive increase in psychotropic drug prescriptions, sometimes point out that the bulk of this prescribing is done – not by them – but by primary care doctors (GPs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; claim in this regards may be true, it is also somewhat misleading.  The &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; for which these drugs are being prescribed were &lt;i&gt;invented&lt;/i&gt; by psychiatrists, and &lt;strong&gt;it is these inventions that legitimize the prescribing activity&lt;/strong&gt;.  And, of course, as the psychiatrists invent more illnesses, the prescription rates increase proportionately.  Without the perceived legitimacy of the DSM, GPs simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t dish out antidepressants, anxiolytics, and stimulants on the scale seen today, if for no other reason than the fear of lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now – by Popular Demand – Ritalin for the Elderly!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 10:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the old days, which I well remember, misbehavior in school was considered a disciplinary problem.  This included not paying attention, fidgeting, not applying oneself to one&amp;rsquo;s work, talking, interrupting the teacher, etc., etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the APA decided that these various activities were really symptoms of a mental illness, and thereby created the ever-burgeoning market for Ritalin and other drugs which, we are falsely told, correct the &amp;ldquo;chemical imbalance&amp;rdquo; in these children&amp;rsquo;s brains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Somatic Symptom Disorder in DSM-5: You&#39;re Crazy to Worry about Your Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 09:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, there is a category called Somatoform Disorders, the common feature of which is a preoccupation with &amp;ldquo;… physical symptoms that suggest a general medical condition …and are not fully explained by a general medical condition…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four of the &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; in this category will be retired in DSM-5 and will be replaced by a new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo;:  &lt;em&gt;somatic symptom disorder&lt;/em&gt;.  The four superseded &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;1.  somatization disorder
2.  hypochondriasis
3.  pain disorder
4.  undifferentiated somatoform disorder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pills, Pills, Pills</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pills-pills-pills/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 10:40:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pills-pills-pills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Alice Keys before on this blog.  She&amp;rsquo;s a psychiatrist who laments the fact that psychiatry has become virtually synonymous with drug pushing, and has expressed her concerns from time to time on Robert Whitaker&amp;rsquo;s Mad in America website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alice has a new post up today, called &lt;em&gt;Winners of the American Dream&lt;/em&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/04/winners-of-the-american-dream/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  She has decided to quit psychiatry.  &amp;ldquo;Pills are the only thing left in psychiatry.  So I stopped working.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marketing Psychotropic Drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 10:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/marketing-psychotropic-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://involuntarytransformation.blogspot.com/2011/04/fishing-lessons-from-my-son.html#.UWBNjZOG0eU&#34;&gt;nice article at Involuntary Transformation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Nathan, poses a very interesting question:  since drugs cause damage to children and there are many better alternatives, &lt;strong&gt;why do so many parents choose the drug option&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan goes on to suggest that the reason lies in the effort that the pharmaceutical industry invests in marketing, and he calls for &amp;ldquo;…complete and total transparency in all Mental Health Services.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Children Gives Them the Wrong Message</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 10:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The routine drugging of children for the ordinary problems of childhood is destructive for two reasons:  firstly because of the toxic effects of the pharmaceutical products, and secondly because it &lt;strong&gt;conveys to the child the message that drugs are an acceptable way to deal with life&amp;rsquo;s problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This latter kind of damage is graphically illustrated in a tragic NY Times article by Ted Gup.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/03/opinion/diagnosis-human.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Ted is a fellow of the Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freudian Psychoanalysis is Better than Drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 10:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/freudian-psychoanalysis-is-better-than-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I received a short comment from Ruth Elliot on my post&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/26/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/#.UVt4fZOG0eU&#34;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psychiatric &amp;ldquo;Diagnoses&amp;rdquo; for Children&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Ruth linked to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://claudiamgoldmd.blogspot.com/2013/01/towards-new-or-return-to-old-paradigm.html#comment-form&#34;&gt;article by Claudia Gold, MD&lt;/a&gt;.  Claudia is a Freudian psychoanalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ideological orientation is behavioral, and if you were to ask people in this business:  what is the opposite of a behaviorist? you would probably get the answer:  a Freudian psychoanalyst.  And vice versa.  They are two very different ways of conceptualizing human activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petition on Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/petition-on-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting new article by Paula Caplan &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/science-isnt-golden/201303/comedy-history-and-the-future-mental-disorder-labels&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It discusses the harmful effects of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the fact that because of these labels, people have lost their &amp;ldquo;… jobs, custody of children, health insurance, and the right to make decisions about their medical and legal affairs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paula also mentions a petition she created in December 2011 calling for &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Congressional Hearings about Psychiatric Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  The petition is still up. You can find it&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.change.org/petitions/everyone-who-cares-about-the-harm-done-by-psychiatric-diagnosis-endorse-the-call-for-congressional-hearings-about-psychiatric-diagnosis&#34;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Marketing Ploy: Promoting Mental Health Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 05:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Hersteltalent on Twitter, I came across this newspaper article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/03/12/mental-health-checkups/1981495/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Doctors Urge Mental Health Screenings with Physicals&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It appeared in USA Today, and was written by Jessica Contrera of the Lafayette, Indiana Journal and Courier.  Dateline March 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article, which is written for the general public, is that when you go in to your doctor for a check-up, you should ask for a mental evaluation as well.  The article reminds us that &amp;ldquo;25% of American adults suffer from some form of mental illness each year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benzo Withdrawal: Another Story</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzo-withdrawal-another-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 08:11:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzo-withdrawal-another-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s another benzo withdrawal story on Mad in America:  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/reality-clash-when-benzo-withdrawal-meets-parenthood/&#34;&gt;The 99&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Mile: When Benzo Withdrawal Meets Parenthood&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt; by Melissa Bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melissa recounts that when her Down&amp;rsquo;s syndrome son was 18 months old and her baby daughter was three months, she consulted a physician because of problems with insomnia and consequent exhaustion.  He prescribed 2 mg of Ativan daily, which he increased to 6 mg within six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melissa describes in detail the problems of withdrawal, and the extreme measures she had to take to cope with this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Benzodiazepine Withdrawal</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzodiazepine-withdrawal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 09:03:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-on-benzodiazepine-withdrawal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/17/withdrawal-from-benzodiazepines/#.UUknoxyG0eU&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; on this topic, I mentioned that benzo withdrawal can be dangerous, but it&amp;rsquo;s been drawn to my attention, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, that perhaps I didn&amp;rsquo;t adequately stress &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; dangerous it can be in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you click &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/01/21/benzodetoxdangers/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, you can read Monica&amp;rsquo;s own account of her experience in a detox center in Florida.  It&amp;rsquo;s a thought-provoking article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because for many years benzos were dished out so liberally, there is still a &lt;strong&gt;mistaken perception that they are relatively safe and benign&lt;/strong&gt;, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-psychotic Drugs in Nursing Homes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/anti-psychotic-drugs-in-nursing-homes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 10:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/anti-psychotic-drugs-in-nursing-homes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2013/feb/21/elderly-care-antipsychotics-sharp-rise&#34;&gt;article from the Manchester Guardian&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.  The article is by Sarah Boseley, and is a review of a UK study in the Journal of the American Geriatric Society written by Aideen Maguire, C. Hughes, Chris Cardwell, and Dermot O&amp;rsquo;Reilly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers examined the Northern Ireland prescribing database and discovered that when people were admitted to nursing homes, the &lt;strong&gt;rate at which they were prescribed anti-psychotic drugs increased from 1.1% to 20.3%!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muddled Thinking and Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until just a few years ago, the spurious nature of mental illness received little or no attention either in professional circles or in the general media. There were a few of us &amp;ldquo;cranks&amp;rdquo; who poked away at the issue, but peer condemnation was usually swift and outspoken.  On one occasion I was called an &amp;ldquo;anti-science Nazi&amp;rdquo; for daring to suggest that the condition known as ADHD might have more to do with ineffective parental discipline than with brain chemistry.  We were voices in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Thoughts on Dr. Novella&#39;s Articles</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 09:55:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/more-thoughts-on-dr-novella-s-articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/#.USd7W6WG0eU&#34;&gt;Steven Novella M.D. and Mental Illness Denial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/mental-illness-denial-part-i/&#34;&gt;Mental Illness Denial Part I&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Novella makes the point that various parts of the brain enable us to do certain things, and that if we are doing these things dysfunctionally, or not well, or perhaps not at all, then clearly there is something wrong with that part of the brain.  The example he gives is the activity of paying attention – but I think this is provided as an example, and that Dr. Novella intended his comments to apply to the full range of problems embraced by the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism of DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 10:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/criticism-of-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lane, author of &lt;i&gt;Shyness: How Normal Behavior Became a Sickness,&lt;/i&gt; has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201302/dsm-5-has-gone-press-containing-major-scientific-gaffe&#34;&gt;new post&lt;/a&gt;, in which he attacks the APA for including somatic symptom disorder (SSD) in the upcoming DSM-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lane quotes from Allen Francis (former DSM guru who has now seen the light) and Suzy Chapman, a UK health advocate.  Both of these commentators attack the new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; as invalid, unreliable, and potentially over-inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>If Depression Is Not An Illness, What Is It?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/if-depression-is-not-an-illness-what-is-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 11:20:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/if-depression-is-not-an-illness-what-is-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2009/07/28/depression/#.URp1BKVEEeU&#34;&gt;Elsewhere on this site&lt;/a&gt;, I have argued that depression is not an illness, but rather is an&lt;strong&gt; adaptive mechanism that encourages us to make changes &lt;/strong&gt;in our habits or our circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written about what I call the seven natural anti-depressants:  good nutrition; fresh air; sunshine (in moderation); physical activity; purposeful activity; good relationships; and adequate and regular sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the question has often been posed:  Why does this adaptive mechanism apparently not work in some cases?  Why is it that for some people the unpleasant feeling fails to act as a spur to make changes, and instead the person sinks further into despondency and inactivity?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Strikes Back: Psychiatry Responds</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-psychiatry-responds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 14:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-empire-strikes-back-psychiatry-responds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By now I guess everybody knows that psychiatry is under attack.  The attack is four-pronged:  the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are spurious&lt;/strong&gt;; the &lt;strong&gt;drugs are damaging&lt;/strong&gt;; the &lt;strong&gt;deception is blatant and deliberate&lt;/strong&gt;; and the &lt;strong&gt;ties to Big Pharma&lt;/strong&gt; are corrupting.  I have discussed all of these topics in great detail throughout the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I&amp;rsquo;ve come across interesting responses from two different psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Adrian Preda, MD, from California.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmj.com/content/346/bmj.f191?tab=responses&#34;&gt;Dr. Preda apparently attributes&lt;/a&gt; at least some of the anti-psychiatry groundswell to the ignorance of the general public and the bias of the media, whom he contrasts to the well-informed experts who understand the nuances.  The article is brief and vague, but by &lt;i&gt;experts&lt;/i&gt; I think he means psychiatrists!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 18:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late adolescence and early adulthood is arguably the most difficult period of life.  Transitioning from childhood to adulthood entails many challenges.  The young person (male or female) is expected to emancipate successfully from parents; launch a career; and find a partner – all in the space of a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some individuals cope remarkably well.  Others squeak through, and a small minority “crash and burn.”  The latter group usually return home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Under Scrutiny</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-under-scrutiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 12:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-under-scrutiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Duncan Double is a British psychiatrist who has a website called &lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Critical Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 12 he published a post under the heading:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://criticalpsychiatry.blogspot.com/2012/10/the-majority-of-psychiatrists-think.html&#34;&gt;“The majority of psychiatrists think adult ADHD is an example of the over-medicalisation of everyday life.” &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;“When I trained, adult ADHD was never mentioned - it&#39;s a relatively new concept, gaining popularity in the 1990s. Many psychiatrists don&#39;t feel happy diagnosing a condition in adults that they were taught children generally grow out of.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
