<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Expansion of Psychiatric Turf on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/expansion-of-psychiatric-turf/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Expansion of Psychiatric Turf on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 05:30:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/categories/expansion-of-psychiatric-turf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Elimination of the Bereavement Exclusion:  History and Implications</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/elimination-of-the-bereavement-exclusion-history-and-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 05:30:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/elimination-of-the-bereavement-exclusion-history-and-implications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bereavement exclusion was formally eliminated in the spring of 2013, with the publication of DSM-5.  The exclusion was a provision in earlier editions, that a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis of major depressive disorder&amp;rdquo; could not be assigned to a bereaved person, even though he or she met the criteria, unless certain additional considerations were met.  The history of its elimination provides an interesting example of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s relentless expansion of its net. The issues involved take us right to the heart of the psychiatric hoax.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health First Aid: Another Psychiatric Expansionist Tool</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On December 25, 2016, the Baltimore Sun published an excellent article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/oped/bs-ed-youth-overmedication-20161225-story.html&#34;&gt;Drug companies prey on children&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Patrick D. Hahn, PhD.  Dr. Hahn is an affiliate professor of biology at Loyola University, Maryland.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I recently attended Youth Mental Health First Aid Training at a local public school. It was an eye-opening experience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Youth Mental Health First Aid Training, sponsored by the National Council for Behavioral Health, is intended to enable teachers, parents and others in contact with young people to identify potential &#39;mental illnesses&#39; in order to facilitate early detection and treatment by our mental health care system. My fellow attendees were surprisingly open about their own experiences with that system. One mentioned that her son became manic after being diagnosed for ADHD. Another said that both she and her roommate became bipolar after being diagnosed for depression. Neither our facilitators nor anyone else present pointed out that mania and bipolar disorder are toxic effects of medications commonly prescribed for ADHD and depression.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murphy Bill Being Sneaked Into House Legislation</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/murphy-bill-being-sneaked-into-house-legislation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 13:02:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/murphy-bill-being-sneaked-into-house-legislation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I received an email from Oldhead, who has been active in opposing the Murphy Bill.  Here are two quotes from the email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As succinctly as possible -- the main language from MURPHY (including AOT funding) has been consolidated with another bill, the 21ST CENTURY CURES bill, which is being introduced as a House Amendment to the Senate Amendment to H.R. 34, Tsunami Warning, Education and Research Act of 2015.&#39;  In other words, Murphy is being slipped through on another bill’s coattails, if Murphy, Jaffee &amp;amp; Co. have their say.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mental Health Reform Act of 2016 (SB 2680) Would Be a Huge Step Backwards</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 6, HB 2646 (the Tim Murphy Bill) passed the US House and was sent to the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the present time, a related bill is working its way through the Senate.  This is SB 2680, The Mental Health Reform Act 2016.  It is sponsored by Lamar Alexander (R-TN), Patty Murray (D-WA), Bill Cassidy (R-LA), Chris Murphy (D-CT), David Vitter (R-LA), and Al Franken (D-MN).  The wording of the bill was finalized in March of this year, and it passed out of committee on March 16.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration of Physical and Mental Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/integration-of-physical-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 05:30:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/integration-of-physical-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Integration of physical and &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; care has been a popular topic in psychiatric circles in recent years.  During his term as President of the APA, the very eminent psychiatrist Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, made frequent references to this matter in his posts on Psychiatric News (the APA&amp;rsquo;s online newspaper).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/doi/full/10.1176%2Fappi.pn.2013.12a30&#34;&gt;December 6, 2013&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Lieberman, with co-author Richard Summers, MD, wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The momentum for patient-centered care, the medical home, and &lt;em&gt;integration of behavioral health with primary care&lt;/em&gt; creates a new role for psychiatrists.&#34; [Emphasis added]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermittent Explosive Disorder:  The &#39;Illness&#39; That Goes On Growing</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/intermittent-explosive-disorder-the-illness-that-goes-on-growing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 05:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/intermittent-explosive-disorder-the-illness-that-goes-on-growing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the APA, intermittent explosive disorder is characterized by angry aggressive outbursts that occur in response to relatively minor provocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular label has an interesting history in successive editions of the DSM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSM I  (1952)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intermittent explosive disorder does not appear as such in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/dsm-1952.pdf&#34;&gt;first edition of DSM&lt;/a&gt;, but the general concept is clearly discernible in &amp;ldquo;passive-aggressive personality, aggressive type&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;A persistent reaction to frustration with irritability, temper tantrums, and destructive behavior is the dominant manifestation.&#34; (p 37)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances Saving Psychiatry From Itself?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 05:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/allen-frances-saving-psychiatry-from-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 12, 2014, the eminent psychiatrist Allen Frances, MD, participated in a panel discussion at the Mad In America film festival in Gothenburg, Sweden.  After the festival, he wrote an article – &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/allen-frances/finding-a-middle-ground-between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry_b_6010890.html&#34;&gt;Finding a Middle Ground Between Psychiatry and Anti-Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;– for the Huffington Post Blog, summarizing the positions he had discussed at the festival. The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/10/between-psychiatry-and-anti-psychiatry-mad-in-america-opens-a-dialogue/&#34;&gt;re-published on MIA&lt;/a&gt; on October 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is ostensibly an attempt to find common ground between psychiatry and its critics, but the piece contains numerous distortions and omissions which I think need to be identified and discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Use of Neuroleptic Drugs As Chemical Restraints in Nursing Homes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-use-of-neuroleptic-drugs-as-chemical-restraints-in-nursing-homes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 05:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-use-of-neuroleptic-drugs-as-chemical-restraints-in-nursing-homes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the July-August 2014 issue of the AARP Bulletin.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aarp.org/health/drugs-supplements/info-2014/antipsychotics-overprescribed.html&#34;&gt;Drug Abuse: Antipsychotics in Nursing Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;and was written by Jan Goodwin.  AARP is the American Association of Retired Persons.   Jan Goodwin is an investigative journalist whose career, according to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Goodwin&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;…has been committed to focusing attention on social justice and human rights…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is essentially a condemnation of the widespread and long-standing practice of using neuroleptic drugs to suppress &amp;ldquo;difficult&amp;rdquo; behavior in nursing home residents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blame the Clients?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blame-the-clients/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 05:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/blame-the-clients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 6, I wrote a post titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2014/06/06/psychiatry-did-promote-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry DID Promote the Chemical Imbalance Theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  The article was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/06/psychiatry-promote-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;published on Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;, and generated a number of comments on that site, five of which were from TherapyFirst, who in his first comment identified himself as Joel Hassman, MD, a practicing psychiatrist.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hassman did not argue with the general notion that psychiatric practice today consists almost exclusively of the prescription of drugs.  Indeed, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantmedicatelife.com/2013/06/16/an-open-letter-to-graduating-psychiatry-residents/&#34;&gt;one of his own blog posts&lt;/a&gt; on June 16, 2013, he wrote in an open letter to newly qualified psychiatrists:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Social Functioning Predicts Adult Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorder.  Or Does It?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-social-functioning-predicts-adult-schizophrenia-spectrum-disorder-or-does-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 05:58:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-social-functioning-predicts-adult-schizophrenia-spectrum-disorder-or-does-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2013, the journal Schizophrenia Research published a paper by Tsuji, T. et al. titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Tsuji%2C+Schiffman%2C+Kline+2013&#34;&gt;Premorbid teacher-rated social functioning predicts adult schizophrenia-spectrum disorder: A high-risk prospective investigation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Here’s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Social functioning deficits are a core component of schizophrenia spectrum disorders, and may emerge years prior to the onset of diagnosable illness. The current study prospectively examines the relation between teacher-rated childhood social dysfunction and later mental illness among participants who were at genetic high-risk for schizophrenia and controls (n=244). The teacher-rated social functioning scale significantly predicted psychiatric outcomes (schizophrenia-spectrum vs. other psychiatric disorder vs. no mental illness). Poor premorbid social functioning appears to constitute a marker of illness vulnerability and may also function as a chronic stressor potentially exacerbating risk for illness.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Services and Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-services-and-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 05:58:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-services-and-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The controversy surrounding Justina Pelletier and her family has expanded its scope in recent months, and has now become a general public scrutiny of Massachusetts&amp;rsquo;s Department of Children and Families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 29, State Governor Deval Patrick gave a press conference in which he announced the resignation of DCF Commissioner Olga Roche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there&amp;rsquo;s a very real risk of confusing some issues here.  The sad fact is that, despite the enormous strides we have made as a society, there are still a great many children who are abused and neglected.  Every state in the US has a social services department, one of whose statutory responsibilities is to investigate reports of abuse and/or neglect.  The case workers who conduct the investigations are required to follow set procedures.  Often they find that the allegation is unfounded, and the investigation is terminated.  When they do find probable cause, they are required by law to present their findings to a judge, who scrutinizes the evidence in accordance with the normal judicial procedures.  The social services department, the parents, and the child are usually represented by attorneys.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;ADHD&#39; and Dangerous Driving</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 05:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Laurence Jerome, a Canadian psychiatrist, and two colleagues wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/ADHD-and-Driving-Jerome-et-al-ccap15_3p105.pdf&#34;&gt;What We Know About ADHD and Driving Risk: A Literature Review, Meta-Analysis and Critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It was published in the Journal of the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry in August, 2006. The primary result of the meta-analysis was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Current data support the utility of stimulant medication in improving driving performance in younger ADHD drivers.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The study is lengthy and well-referenced, but in keeping with standard psychiatric practice, it conceptualizes and presents ADHD as a &#34;…common psychiatric disorder…&#34; with symptoms of &#34;…inattention, impulsiveness and hyperactivity…&#34;  In other words, they present ADHD as something that a person &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; rather than as something that a person &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; The problem with this approach is that it creates the impression that meaningful or significant correlations/effects have been found, where in fact all that has happened is an elucidation of the terms used.
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the authors refer to a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Fried%2C+R.%2C+Petty%2C+C.R.%2C+Surman%2C+C.B.%2C+Reimer%2C+B.%2C+Aleardi%2C+M.%2C+Martin%2C+J.M.+2006&#34;&gt;Fried et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2006) and state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justina Pelletier: The Debate Continues</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-debate-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2014 05:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-debate-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On April 1, 2014, Slate published an online article titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/medical_examiner/2014/04/justina_pelletier_s_mitochondrial_disease_boston_children_s_hospital_suspects.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Mitochondrial Disease or Medical Child Abuse?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;  The author is Brian Palmer.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/slate_fare/2006/08/about_us.html&#34;&gt;Slate&lt;/a&gt; is a daily, general interest web magazine, founded in 1996, that provides &amp;ldquo;analysis and commentary about politics, news, business, technology and culture,&amp;rdquo; and is a subsidiary of the Washington Post.  Brian Palmer is Slate&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;chief explainer.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title suggests, the article tries to explore the central question in Justina&amp;rsquo;s case:  does she have mitochondrial disease or is she a victim of medical child abuse?  The author does a good job of defining the various terms, unraveling the issues, and presenting both sides of the argument, though on balance he comes down in favor of Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justina Pelletier: The Case Continues</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-case-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 05:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-the-case-continues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 25, Joseph Johnston, Juvenile Court Justice in Boston, Massachusetts, issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://c.o0bg.com/rw/Boston/2011-2020/2014/03/25/BostonGlobe.com/HealthScience/Graphics/SCAN.pdf&#34;&gt;disposition order&lt;/a&gt; in the case: Care and protection of Justina Pelletier.  The background to the case is well-known.  Justina is 15 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Johnston did not return Justina to the care of her parents, but instead granted permanent custody to the Massachusetts Department of Children and Families (DCF), with a right to review in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In paragraph 4, the disposition order states: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perfect Psychiatrist</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 05:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-perfect-psychiatrist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On March 19, a new article was posted on Aeon Magazine.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/magazine/being-human/have-psychiatrists-lost-perspective-on-mental-illness/&#34;&gt;A Mad World&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; and was written by Joseph Pierre, MD, who works in Log Angeles as a psychiatric practitioner and professor.  Dr. Pierre has authored more than fifty papers, and has received several awards.  He has lectured nationally and internationally, and would, I think, be considered an eminent psychiatrist.  I am grateful to several readers for the link to the article.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Misusing the Political Process</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-misusing-the-political-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 10:33:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-misusing-the-political-process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On March 27, the US House of Representatives approved by a voice vote &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;with no debate &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;a Medicare bill, HR 4302, Protecting Access to Medicare Act of 2014.  The purpose of the bill is to avoid cutting Medicare payments to physicians, and there was, and is, general agreement on both side of the aisle that the bill needed to pass.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tacked onto the bill was a rider which authorized $60 million to &lt;i&gt;expand&lt;/i&gt; involuntary outpatient commitment (IOC) in states that already have provision for commitments of this sort.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robert Whitaker: Looking Back and Looking Ahead</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-looking-back-and-looking-ahead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 05:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/robert-whitaker-looking-back-and-looking-ahead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On March 5, Bruce Levine, PhD, published an interesting article on Mad in America  titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/03/psychiatry-admits-wrong-big-ways-can-change-chat-robert-whitaker/&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Psychiatry Now Admits It&amp;rsquo;s Been Wrong in Big Ways – But Can It Change?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Bruce had interviewed Robert Whitaker, and most of the article is the transcript of this interview.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce begins by noting that Robert, in his book &lt;em&gt;Mad in America&lt;/em&gt;, had challenged some fundamental tenets of psychiatry, including the validity of its &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; and the efficacy (especially the &lt;i&gt;long-term&lt;/i&gt; efficacy) of its treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benzodiazepines:  Dangerous Drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-dangerous-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 05:58:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/benzodiazepines-dangerous-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On February 25, Kristina Fiore published an article on MedPage today.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medpagetoday.com/PainManagement/PainManagement/44481&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Killing Pain: Xanax Tops Charts&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The article is based on a study conducted by Jann M et al, and published in the February 2014 issue of the Journal of Pharmacy Practice.  The study is titled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24436437&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Benzodiazepines: a major component in unintentional prescription drug overdoses with opioid analgesics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;.  Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&#34;During 2003 to 2009, the 2 prescriptions drugs with the highest increase in death rates were oxycodone 264.6% and alprazolam 233.8%. Therefore, benzodiazepines have a significant impact on prescription drug unintentional overdoses second only to the opioid analgesics. The combination prescribing of benzodiazepines and opioid analgesics commonly takes place. The pharmacokinetic drug interactions between benzodiazepines and opioid analgesics are complex. The pharmacodynamic actions of these agents differ as their combined effects produce significant respiratory depression.&#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justina Pelletier and Boston Children&#39;s Hospital</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-and-boston-children-s-hospital/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 05:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/justina-pelletier-and-boston-children-s-hospital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Justina Pelletier is the 15-year-old girl who is at the center of a dispute between her parents and the Psychiatry Department at Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justina, who lived with her parents in Connecticut, had been diagnosed with mitochondrial disease, a rare and debilitating illness, and had been receiving treatment for this from Mark Korson, MD, Chief of Metabolism Services at Tufts Medical Center in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February of last year, Justina&amp;rsquo;s parents took her to Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital with flu-like symptoms.  Dr. Korson had recommended an admission to Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s so that Justina could be seen by Alex Flores, MD, a gastrointestinal specialist who had recently transferred from Tufts to BCH.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADHD:  Are We Helping Or Harming?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 06:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/adhd-are-we-helping-or-harming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In November 2013, the British Medical Journal published &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://charlesmarsan.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Overdiagnosis-ADHD.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: are we helping or harming?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Rae Thomas, PhD, Psychologist, Australia; Geoffrey K. Mitchell, MB BS, FRACGP, PhD, Professor of General Practice, Australia; and Laura Batstra, PhD, Psychologist, Netherlands.  The article is part of a series on the dangers of overdiagnosis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Prevalence and prescribing rates for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) have risen steeply over the past decade, partly in response to concerns about underdiagnosis and undertreatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Still Passing the Buck: Psychiatry Is Blameless</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 05:47:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-still-passing-the-buck-psychiatry-is-blameless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has expressed concern about the rise in the number of people being assigned a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of ADHD.  He has put up a video on Medscape, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/819298&#34;&gt;Explaining the Rise in ADHD&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;There is a transcript with the video.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is responding to a December 14, 2013, New York Times article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/15/health/the-selling-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;The Selling of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;by Alan Schwarz, and a December 18 editorial in the same paper titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/19/opinion/an-epidemic-of-attention-deficit-disorder.html&#34;&gt;An Epidemic of Attention Deficit Disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affluenza: A New Mental Illness?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/affluenza-a-new-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 05:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/affluenza-a-new-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A short editorial piece by James Bradshaw in the current issue (Jan/Feb) of the National Psychologist discusses the trial of a 16-year-old male who killed four people and severely injured two others while driving under the influence of Valium (diazepam) and alcohol.  He had stolen the alcohol from a store earlier, and his blood alcohol level was three times the legal adult limit.  He was driving 70 mph in a 40 mph zone at the time of the incident.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Not Based On Valid Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 05:58:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-not-based-on-valid-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 23, I wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/23/dsm-5-dimensional-diagnoses-more-conflicts-of-interest/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  In the article I sketched out the role of David Kupfer, MD, in promoting the concept of dimensional assessment in DSM-5, and I speculated that at least part of his motivation in this regard might have stemmed from the fact that he is a major shareholder in a company that is developing a computerized assessment instrument.  I ended the piece with a general criticism of psychiatry:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Person-first Terminology Doesn&#39;t Validate Psychiatric Diagnoses</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/person-first-terminology-doesn-t-validate-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 05:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/person-first-terminology-doesn-t-validate-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;On January 3, on CommonHealth I saw the following headline:  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commonhealth.wbur.org/2014/01/renounce-term-the-mentally-ill&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A Phrase To Renounce For 2014:  &amp;lsquo;The Mentally Ill&amp;rsquo;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;, written by Carey Goldberg.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first impression was that the author was debunking the concept of mental illness, but I was sadly mistaken.  The theme of the article was the so-called person-first terminology that has been promoted by various bodies and agencies since about the mid-eighties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that one shouldn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;a developmentally disabled child.&amp;rdquo;  Instead, one should say &amp;ldquo;a child with a developmental disability.&amp;rdquo;  Similarly, a person should not be referred to as an &amp;ldquo;alcoholic,&amp;rdquo; but rather as a &amp;ldquo;person with alcoholism.&amp;rdquo;  And so on.  The idea is to avoid giving the impression that the individual is to be &lt;i&gt;defined by &lt;/i&gt; the presence of a disabling condition.  The individual is first and foremost a &lt;i&gt;person,&lt;/i&gt; and the problem or disability is semantically tacked on to indicate that it is a &lt;i&gt;quality&lt;/i&gt; of the person rather than the defining feature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murphy&#39;s Mental Health Bill:  An Update</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 10:01:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/murphy-s-mental-health-bill-an-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, December 26, at 8:25 p.m., the following comment was posted on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/16/murphys-mental-health-bill/#comment-1177912457&#34;&gt;December 16 post&lt;/a&gt; on the Murphy Mental Health Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Read the article in today&#39;s Wall Street Journal (12/26/13), &#39;A Mental-Health Overhaul&#39;, and you cannot help but be in favor of the Murphy Bill. It is a huge misrepresentation to say it is about &#39;coercive tactics&#39;. Take the bill piece by piece and debate it. If you have experienced the mental healthcare system you would recognize that this legislation is badly needed and long over due.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 05:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 20, JAMA Psychiatry (formerly Archives of General Psychiatry) published an interesting letter.  It was headed: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleID=1780020&amp;amp;utm_source=Silverchair%20Information%20Systems&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=JAMAPsychiatry%3AOnlineFirst11%2F20%2F2013&#34;&gt;Failure to Report Financial Disclosure Information&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and was signed by Robert D. Gibbons PhD, David J Weiss PhD, Paul A. Pilkonis PhD, Ellen Frank, PhD , and David J. Kupfer MD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is an apology for failing to disclose a financial interest in an article, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3551289/&#34;&gt;Development of a Computerized Adaptive Test for Depression&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; that had appeared in Archives of General Psychiatry a year earlier (November 2012).  The article described a computerized questionnaire for depression (the CAT-DI) and was generally positive with regards to the potential usefulness of the test in clinical settings.  In the article, the authors had clearly stated that they had &lt;i&gt;no conflicts of interest&lt;/i&gt;, but that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Money For Mental Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-money-for-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2013 05:56:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/new-money-for-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On December 10, Vice President Joe Biden announced that $100 million of new Federal money is to be injected into the US mental health system  &amp;ldquo;…to expand community-based services and treatment centers.&amp;rdquo;  There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-politics/wp/2013/12/10/biden-announces-new-money-for-mental-health/?wprss=rss_politics&amp;amp;clsrd&#34;&gt;short article&lt;/a&gt; about this in the Washington Post.  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Scott Wilson, the Post&amp;rsquo;s chief White House correspondent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article states that the  &amp;ldquo;…inadequacy of mental health and addiction care…&amp;rdquo;  is a topic that  &amp;ldquo;…gained urgency after the school shooting in Newtown, Connecticut, a year ago, a crime carried out by a mentally disturbed gunman.&amp;rdquo;  This is a reference to 20-year-old Adam Lanza, who killed 20 children and 6 adult staff, himself, and his mother in the incident.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training the Psychiatrists of the Future (According to Dr. Lieberman): More Cheerleading</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 05:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/training-the-psychiatrists-of-the-future-according-to-dr-lieberman-more-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA and Chair of Psychiatry at Columbia University, published a post on November 26 on Psychiatric News.  The article is called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1787247&#34;&gt;Training the Psychiatrists of the Future&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and is co-authored by Richard Summers, MD.  Dr. Summers is a Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drs. Lieberman and Summers open by telling us that psychiatrists&amp;rsquo; roles &amp;ldquo;…are changing and will continue to change.&amp;rdquo;  That sounds great, but don&amp;rsquo;t expect too much.  There will still, they tell us, be a need for:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children: Harvard&#39;s Shame</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 05:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2012, Mark Olfson, MD, et al, published an article in the Archives of General Psychiatry.  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22868273&#34;&gt;National Trends in the Office-Based Treatment of Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The authors collected data from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Surveys for the period 1993-2009, and looked for trends in antipsychotic prescribing for children, adolescents, and adults in outpatient visits.  Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;&lt;!--
table { 	border: 1px solid gray;     	border-collapse: collapse;      	width: 500px;   	cellspacing: 0; } th {     	background-color: #eee;          border: 1px solid black; }  th#blank {     	background- color: #FFF;  }  th.colOne {         width: 100px; } td {     	text-align: center;  	border: 1px solid black; } table#diagnosis th.data {         width: 120px; }
--&gt;&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;antipsychoticRX&#34; cellspacing=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;colOne&#34;&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Increase in no. of antipsychotic prescriptions per 100 population (1993-2009)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0-13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.24-1.83 (almost 8-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;14-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.78-3.76 (almost 5-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;21+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25-6.18 (almost 2-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;The authors provide a breakdown of the diagnoses assigned to the children and adolescents during the antipsychotic visits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Care For Your Mind (CFYM): A New Advocacy Group</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 06:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/care-for-your-mind-cfym-a-new-advocacy-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 27, Psychiatric Services, a journal of the APA, published an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1745505&#34;&gt;Blog Brings Doctors, Patients Together to Address MH Issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It was written by Vabren Watts, a Psychiatric News Journalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a booster piece for the recently-formed CFYM (Care For Your Mind):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…an online forum for people with mood disorders—along with their families and psychiatrists—to discuss the mental health care system and changes that may affect them under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman and &#39;60 Minutes&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-and-60-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 23, Psychiatric News (the APA&amp;rsquo;s media outlet) ran an article titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=1762017&#34;&gt;‘60 Minutes’ Interviews APA President on Schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The article was written by Mark Moran, a Psychiatric News reporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece opens with a quote from Jeffrey Lieberman, MD (President of the APA):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;&#39;60 Minutes&#39; showed a genuine interest beyond simply producing what was expected to be a popular segment and indicated a desire to do follow-up reporting on psychosis and violence.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/protecting-the-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/protecting-the-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dxsummit.org/archives/1636&#34;&gt;Safeguarding a Generation of Children from Over-diagnosis and Prescription of Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It&amp;rsquo;s written by Dave Traxson, who works as an Educational Psychologist in the UK, and is posted on the  DxSummit website, an online platform for rethinking mental health, a forum in which the concepts underlying pharma-psychiatry are questioned and challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I view the trend towards mass medication of children with mind altering and potentially toxic drugs and ‘drug cocktails’ as a form of psycho-economic imperialism. By that I mean that young peoples’ developing minds are being colonized, using biochemicals, for huge commercial profit and in effect, increased social control. This has resulted from carefully constructed ‘business plans’ in boardrooms which some years ago saw the population of children in the western world as a great market expansion opportunity. The pharmaceutical companies have reaped the huge financial rewards of this rich and very bitter harvest ever since.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Allen Frances – Lucy Johnstone Debate</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 05:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-allen-frances-lucy-johnstone-debate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Allen Frances, MD, Chairperson of the DSM-IV task force, published an article on Psychology Today.  It is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/saving-normal/201310/does-it-make-sense-scrap-psychiatric-diagnosis-0&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Does It Make Sense To Scrap Psychiatric Diagnosis?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and is essentially a response to the British Psychological Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Clinical Psychology&amp;rsquo;s (DCP) call to abandon the medical model in situations where it is not appropriate, and to embrace a psychosocial approach.  You can see a copy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/DCP-Position-Statement-on-Classification.pdf&#34;&gt;DCP&amp;rsquo;s May 13, 2013, statement here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APA Attempting To Export Its Errors</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/apa-attempting-to-export-its-errors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2013 07:09:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/apa-attempting-to-export-its-errors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article by Christopher Lane, PhD, in his blog site Side Effects, on Psychology Today.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/side-effects/201310/crazy-us-how-the-us-exports-its-models-illness&#34;&gt;Crazy like Us: How the U.S. Exports Its Models of Illness&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and is dated October 9.  Christopher Lane is the author of &lt;em&gt;Shyness: How Normal Behavior Became a Sickness&lt;/em&gt;.  I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2010/04/15/the-so-called-mental-illnesses-are-not-illnesses/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; in April of 2010 that referenced this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the opening paragraph from the Psychology Today article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The fears of many European psychiatrists may soon be realized. Earlier this week, Psychiatric News reported that the American Psychiatric Association has begun petitioning the various agencies overseeing changes to the ICD, or International Classification of Diseases, to request that they adopt its most-controversial changes in DSM-5.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Stigma Attached to &#39;Mental Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 06:30:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-stigma-attached-to-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Monday, October 7, 2013, The Sun, a British tabloid newspaper ran the following headline:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/5183994/1200-killed-by-mental-patients-in-shock-10-year-toll.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1,200 Killed By Mental Patients.  Shock 10-year toll exposes care crisis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  It took up almost all of the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The headline precipitated a great deal of protest from politicians, advocacy groups, mental health professionals, and others.  The general points in most of these protests were that the headline was sensationalistic, misleading, and would serve to increase the stigma associated with &amp;ldquo;mental illness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Health Care Reform and Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 05:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/health-care-reform-and-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an APA article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1748304&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Change, Challenge, and Opportunity: Psychiatry in the Age of Health Care Reform&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It was co-authored by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, and Howard Goldman, MD, PhD, and dated October 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article discusses the implications of the Affordable Care Act (Obamacare) for psychiatry, and also reviews progress of the 2008 Mental Health Parity Act.  The latter mandated that insurance coverage for &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses&amp;rdquo; be essentially on a par with coverage for general medical problems, but the act has not yet been implemented in its entirety.  The authors also point out that there are provisions in the ACA that focus on reform of the actual health care services, as well as the reform of health care insurance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Proposed Mental Health School Program</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-proposed-mental-health-school-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 06:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/a-proposed-mental-health-school-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 30, the Wisconsin State Journal posted an article online.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://host.madison.com/news/local/govt-and-politics/county-executive-joe-parisi-proposes-new-mental-health-program-for/article_7dc57b3e-4940-56ac-8b83-9f5a9be9617e.html&#34;&gt;County Executive Joe Parisi proposes new mental health program for county school district&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; and was written by Andrea Anderson.  [Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;S. Randolph Kretchmar on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that Joe Parisi, the County Executive of Dane County, Wisconsin, is proposing to allocate $90,000 each to two school districts &amp;ldquo;…to treat student mental health…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should Medical Insurance Cover Mental Health?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/should-medical-insurance-cover-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 06:26:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/should-medical-insurance-cover-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 27, the New York Times published an article called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/29/business/lacking-rules-insurers-balk-at-paying-for-intensive-psychiatric-care.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0&#34;&gt;Lacking Rules, Insurers Balk at Paying for Intensive Psychiatric Care&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The author is Reed Abelson.  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;S. Randolph Kretchmar on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article describes the kinds of conflicts that can occur between people with &amp;ldquo;mental illnesses&amp;rdquo; wanting &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; and insurance companies who sometimes are reluctant to pay for this &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is fairly balanced.  It presents a number of actual cases of people who were experiencing difficulty.  But it also tries to do justice to the insurance company&amp;rsquo;s position:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Spin on the Navy Yard Murders</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 05:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-s-spin-on-the-navy-yard-murders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, has written a guest post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.everydayhealth.com/columns/health-answers/in-the-wake-of-the-navy-yard-shooting-a-way-forward/&#34;&gt;In the Wake of the Navy Yard Shooting: A Way Forward&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;on EverydayHealth.  Everyday Health Inc. is a media company which operates for-profit websites on health and related matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been confirmed that the Navy Yard shooter had been taking trazadone, an antidepressant of the serotonin antagonist and reuptake inhibitor (SARI) class, and the House Committee on Veterans&amp;rsquo; Affairs has indicated that it &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenewamerican.com/usnews/crime/item/16595-did-psychiatric-meds-cause-navy-yard-tragedy&#34;&gt;plans to investigate&lt;/a&gt; to what extent the drug might have been a causative factor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugs Out: Brain Stimulators In:  Psychiatry&#39;s Next Assault On Our Humanity?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugs-out-brain-stimulators-in-psychiatry-s-next-assault-on-our-humanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 05:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugs-out-brain-stimulators-in-psychiatry-s-next-assault-on-our-humanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 21, the Guardian/Observer (UK) ran an online article by Vaughan Bell titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/science/2013/sep/22/brains-neuroscience-prozac-psychiatric-drugs&#34;&gt;Changing brains: why neuroscience is ending the Prozac era&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pmace&#34;&gt;Paul Mace on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is that although the use of psycho-pharmaceutical products is at an all-time high and is still rising in most parts of the world, the psychiatric promise of &lt;i&gt;drug&lt;/i&gt;-induced happiness may be at, or close to, its peak.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Concept of Mental Illness:  Spurious or Valid?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 05:35:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-concept-of-mental-illness-spurious-or-valid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 17, 2013, Peter Kinderman, PhD, Professor of Clinical Psychology at the University of Liverpool, wrote an article titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-20986796&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Grief and Anxiety are not mental illnesses&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 4, 2013, Steven Novella, MD, wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/dsm-v-mental-illness-vs-normal-behavior/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Kinderman&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 20, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/02/20/steven-novella-m-d-and-mental-illness-denial/&#34;&gt;critique of Dr. Novella&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, on September 17, Dr. Novella wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/more-on-mental-illness-denial-and-how-not-to-argue/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;More On Mental Illness Denial and How Not to Argue&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a critique of my critique.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jon Rappoport&#39;s Blog</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 05:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/jon-rappoport-s-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Jon Rappoport&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, please take a look.  Here are two quotes from his September 22 post, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jonrappoport.wordpress.com/2013/09/22/psychiatry-targets-college-students-for-destruction/&#34;&gt;Psychiatry targets college students for destruction&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The concept called &#39;mental disorder&#39; is a sales pitch backed up by extraordinary PR, money, academic gibberish, and government-granted official status.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;People need to wake up to the fact that the whole panoply of human suffering has been co-opted, taken over, redefined, re-translated into a lexicon of pseudoscience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman&#39;s Latest</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 07:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-lieberman-s-latest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 12, Jeffry Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, posted an article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1738168&#34;&gt;IPS to Feature Patrick Kennedy, Celebrate Community Psychiatry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is a preview of an APA conference scheduled for October 10-13 in Philadelphia: &amp;ldquo;Transforming Psychiatric Practice, Reforming Health Care Delivery.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman tells us that he is very excited about the conference, and that the theme is particularly relevant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;…given the changes we are experiencing in the profession and some of the exciting program events that I hope will support APA’s goal of being in the forefront of changes in the profession under health care reform.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Burden of Mental &#39;Illness&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 09:51:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-burden-of-mental-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GrahamCLDavey&#34;&gt;Graham Davey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/socratext&#34;&gt;Richard Pemberton&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the link to an interesting article in the August 29, 2013 issue of the Lancet.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/GBD-Mental-2010-from-Lancet.pdf&#34;&gt;Global burden of disease attributable to mental and substance use disorders: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;and was written by Harvey A. Whiteford, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Burden of Disease survey is a systematic, scientific attempt to quantify the comparative magnitude of disease, injuries, and risk factors by age, sex, and geography over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics and Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-and-alzheimer-s-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 08:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/neuroleptics-and-alzheimer-s-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned the CATIE study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/07/16/the-cafe-study-dr-liebermans-high-moral-ground/&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.  CATIE (Clinical Antipsychotic Trials of Intervention Effectiveness) was a NIMH-funded double blinded, randomized controlled trial comparing the effectiveness and side effects of newer-generation neuroleptics versus an older neuroleptic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/CATIE-AD.pdf&#34;&gt;CATIE-AD&lt;/a&gt; was a part of CATIE.  The AD stands for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease.  CATIE-AD was published in the New England Journal of Medicine in October 2006.  The results of the study were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;There were no significant differences among treatments with regard to the time to the discontinuation of treatment for any reason&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Intrinsically Flawed and Rotten</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter yesterday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobStamatakis&#34;&gt;Robert Stamatakis&lt;/a&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have to ask, I don&#39;t understand.  Do you work in the UK?  Your descriptions of psychiatry are nothing I recognize.  These descriptions of psychiatry are nothing like the practice I see on a daily basis.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
I am certainly a very outspoken critic of psychiatry, and in that regard Robert&#39;s question/challenge is a fair one, to which I will try to respond.
&lt;p&gt;My primary criticism of modern psychiatry – and indeed the criticism that underpins all the others – is that its fundamental concepts are spurious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PTSD:  The Spurious Medicalization of Painful Memories</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 04:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/ptsd-the-spurious-medicalization-of-painful-memories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read &lt;i&gt;Crazy Like Us: The Globalization of the American Psyche,&lt;/i&gt; by Ethan Watters (Free Press, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, the theme of which is that western countries, especially America, are &lt;strong&gt;exporting the medicalization of human problems to less developed regions of the world&lt;/strong&gt;.  The new &amp;ldquo;illnesses&amp;rdquo; are being avidly promoted as if they had the same kind of reality as pneumonia or cancer, and are being foisted on vulnerable populations, with little regard for their impact on the cultures, ideas, sensitivities, and health of the recipients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FDA Goes Against Its Advisory Panel</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/fda-goes-against-its-advisory-panel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 04:38:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/fda-goes-against-its-advisory-panel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The FDA recently approved paroxetine (which in higher doses is marketed as the antidepressant Paxil) as a nonhormonal treatment for hot flashes in menopausal women.  The drug will be marketed as Brisdelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a New York Times article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/29/business/fda-approves-a-drug-for-hot-flashes.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;F.D.A. Approves a Drug for Hot Flashes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;the approval was granted despite the fact that FDA&amp;rsquo;s own advisory committee voted 10 to 4 last March &lt;i&gt;against approval.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reported reason for the negative vote was that in clinical trials, &lt;strong&gt;Brisdelle proved only minimally effective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Has the Moral High Ground (According to Jeffrey Lieberman)</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 05:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-has-the-moral-high-ground-according-to-jeffrey-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I suppose everyone knows by now, psychiatry has been on the receiving end of some very serious criticism in recent years.  The criticism has come from many sources, including: survivors of psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment,&amp;rdquo; non-psychiatric mental health practitioners, journalists, the general public, and even from some psychiatrists themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the criticisms has been equally varied, and includes:  that the concept of mental illness is fundamentally spurious and devoid of explanatory significance; that psychiatric &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; (i.e. drugging people) is ineffective, physically damaging and disempowering; that psychiatry has forged and continues to maintain corrupt and corrupting relationships with the pharmaceutical industry with regards to the peddling of drugs and the hijacking of research for commercial ends; etc…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Still Doesn&#39;t Get It</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-still-doesn-t-get-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 3-4 June, the Institute of Psychiatry in London hosted an international conference to mark the publication of DSM-5.  On June 10, Sir Simon Wessely, a department head at the Institute, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slam.nhs.uk/our-blog/brcu/dsm-5-at-the-iop&#34;&gt;DSM-5 at the IoP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  The paper is a summary of the conference proceedings, and also, in many respects, a defense of DSM-5.  The article touches on many issues that are central to the current anti-psychiatry debate, and for this reason, I thought it might be helpful to take a close look at the piece.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Really Want to Expand Mental Health Services?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 08:02:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/do-we-really-want-to-expand-mental-health-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT&amp;rsquo;S SPEECH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 3, President Obama delivered a &lt;a href=&#34;http://m.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2013/06/03/remarks-president-national-conference-mental-health&#34;&gt;speech on the expansion of mental health services&lt;/a&gt;.  The occasion was the National Conference on Mental Health, which was held at the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The truth is,&#34; the President told us, &#34;in any given year, one in five adults experience a mental illness — one in five.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
In most human endeavors something is true only if it can be shown to be so.  In psychiatry and politics, however, a statement becomes true if it&#39;s repeated often enough.  For the past 60 years, the APA has been systematically expanding their diagnostic net until – surprise, surprise – it now envelops 20% of the population.  With the lowering of thresholds in DSM-5, we can be sure that this number will continue to rise, and whoever is President then will be able to tell us that one in &lt;i&gt;four&lt;/i&gt; of the population has a mental illness.  Gosh!
&lt;p&gt;Note also that the President uses the term &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;mental disorder.&amp;rdquo;  The APA use the latter term in their manual to make the concept somehow more acceptable.  But these &amp;ldquo;disorders&amp;rdquo; always morph into illnesses in application.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Insel Changes His Mind</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-insel-changes-his-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 14:33:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dr-insel-changes-his-mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, as I guess everybody knows by now, Dr. Insel has changed his mind.  On April 29, he stated that the weakness of DSM &amp;ldquo;…is its lack of validity.&amp;rdquo;  He went on to express the view that his agency, NIMH, (the US government&amp;rsquo;s mental health research arm) &amp;ldquo;…cannot succeed if we use DSM categories…&amp;rdquo;  You can see his full statement &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/about/director/2013/transforming-diagnosis.shtml&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement was widely interpreted as a significant rift between NIMH and the APA.  But apparently they&amp;rsquo;ve made up their differences and are pals again.  On May 13, just two weeks after his divorce statement, Dr. Insel and Dr. Lieberman, APA president elect, have issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2013/dsm-5-and-rdoc-shared-interests.shtml?utm_source=rss_readers&amp;amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;amp;utm_campaign=rss_summary&#34;&gt;joint statement&lt;/a&gt; in which they express the belief that the DSM &amp;ldquo;…represents the best information currently available for clinical diagnosis of mental disorders.&amp;rdquo;  Patients, families and insurers, we are told, &amp;ldquo;…can be confident that effective treatments are available and that the DSM is the key resource for delivering the best available care.&amp;rdquo;  It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe that this is the same DSM that he earlier criticized as &lt;i&gt;lacking validity!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – Embracing a Social Paradigm?</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 07:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-embracing-a-social-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article in the May 2013 issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;The future of academic psychiatry may be social&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt;by Stefan Priebe, Tom Burns, and Tom K. J. Craig.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NSVo2eU9meHQtOUU/edit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The past 30 years have produced no discoveries leading to major changes in psychiatric practice. The rules regulating research and a dominant neurobiological paradigm may both have stifled creativity. Embracing a social paradigm could generate real progress and, simultaneously, make the profession more attractive.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transforming Diagnosis:  The Thomas Insel Article</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 21:06:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/transforming-diagnosis-the-thomas-insel-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 29, Thomas Insel, Director of NIMH, published a paper called &lt;i&gt;Transforming Diagnosis&lt;/i&gt;.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychrights.org/2013/130429NIMHTransformingDiagnosis.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Insel is critical of DSM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;While DSM has been described as a &#39;Bible&#39; for the field, it is, at best, a dictionary, creating a set of labels and defining each.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The weakness is its lack of validity.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This has created quite a stir, in that it appears to support the position of those of us who have been criticizing the DSM on these kinds of grounds for decades.  It also suggests a fundamental rift between the NIMH and the APA, two groups who up till now had appeared to be joined at the hip.
&lt;p&gt;The article has generated a great deal of comment.  So far, there&amp;rsquo;s been nothing from the APA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Effect of DSM</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 12:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/social-effect-of-dsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep two dictionaries on my desk.  The first is a 1964 Webster&amp;rsquo;s; the second is a 2009 Webster&amp;rsquo;s.  This morning I looked up the word &amp;ldquo;depression&amp;rdquo; in both books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1964:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;n. &lt;b&gt;1.&lt;/b&gt; a depressing or being depressed.  &lt;b&gt;2.&lt;/b&gt; a depressed part or place; hollow or low place.  &lt;b&gt;3.&lt;/b&gt; low spirits; dejection.  &lt;b&gt;4.&lt;/b&gt; a decrease in force, activity, amount, etc.  &lt;b&gt;5.&lt;/b&gt; a period marked by slackening of business activity, much unemployment, falling prices and wages, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bereavement:  An &#34;Opportunity&#34; for Psychiatry</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 10:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new post on Mick Bramham&amp;rsquo;s website called &amp;ldquo;A time to grieve, a time to console, and a time to profit?&amp;rdquo;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.mythsandrisks.info/2013/04/a-time-to-grieve-time-to-console-and.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have thought that, given the adverse publicity that pharma has been receiving in recent years, they would be easing up on their expansionist agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you would be wrong.  The &lt;strong&gt;APA has declared open season on bereavement&lt;/strong&gt;, and although DSM-5 won&amp;rsquo;t be released for a few more weeks, &lt;strong&gt;Eli Lilly is already grooming their SNRI Cymbalta as a &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for this pseudo illness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internet Addiction: A Bad Habit, Not An Illness</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 17:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/internet-addiction-a-bad-habit-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSM-5 drafting committee considered including Internet addiction in the upcoming revision, but eventually backed off, at least for now.  Apparently they decided to put it in the category &amp;ldquo;requiring further study.&amp;rdquo;  So it&amp;rsquo;ll be in DSM-6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, people are being given the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; anyway – and of course, the &amp;ldquo;treatment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AN ILLUSTRATIVE CASE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt; for sending me a link to a recent article in the UK&amp;rsquo;s MailOnline.  It was written by Rebecca Seales and Eleanor Harding.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2312429/Four-year-old-girl-Britains-youngest-iPad-ADDICT-Shocking-rise-children-hooked-using-smartphones-tablets.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Anxiety Disorder: Now Also for Adults</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/separation-anxiety-disorder-now-also-for-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of separation anxiety disorder has been around since DSM-III.  In DSM-IV it is defined as &amp;ldquo;…excessive anxiety concerning separation from the home or from those to whom the person is attached.&amp;rdquo;  (DSM-IV-TR p 121).  The APA&amp;rsquo;s prevalence estimate is 4%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is listed under the heading: &amp;ldquo;Other Disorders of Infancy, Childhood, or Adolescence.&amp;rdquo;  One of the criteria is that the problem must begin before age 18, and in practice the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; was generally confined to children under the age of 10 or so.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bereavement Exclusion and DSM-5</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 14:09:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-bereavement-exclusion-and-dsm-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, a &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; of major depressive &lt;i&gt;disorder&lt;/i&gt; is based on the presence of a major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major depressive &lt;i&gt;episode&lt;/i&gt;, in turn, is defined by the presence of five or more items from the following list during a two-week period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;(1) depressed mood most of the day, nearly every day, as indicated by either subjective report (e.g., feels sad or empty) or observation made by others (e.g., appears tearful). Note&lt;b&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; In children and adolescents, can be irritable mood.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now – by Popular Demand – Ritalin for the Elderly!</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 10:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/now-by-popular-demand-ritalin-for-the-elderly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the old days, which I well remember, misbehavior in school was considered a disciplinary problem.  This included not paying attention, fidgeting, not applying oneself to one&amp;rsquo;s work, talking, interrupting the teacher, etc., etc., etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the APA decided that these various activities were really symptoms of a mental illness, and thereby created the ever-burgeoning market for Ritalin and other drugs which, we are falsely told, correct the &amp;ldquo;chemical imbalance&amp;rdquo; in these children&amp;rsquo;s brains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric Spin</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-spin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 09:43:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-spin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago (March 23), the New York Times did a feature on &amp;ldquo;Defining Mental Illness.&amp;rdquo;  They invited Ronald Pies, MD (a psychiatry professor at SUNY Upstate Medical University and Tufts University) to submit a brief paper on this topic.  Various people with opposing views were allowed to respond, and finally Dr. Pies presented a much longer summary and rebuttal.  You can see the entire print version &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/24/opinion/sunday/sunday-dialogue-defining-mental-illness.html?ref=opinion&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Somatic Symptom Disorder in DSM-5: You&#39;re Crazy to Worry about Your Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 09:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/somatic-symptom-disorder-in-dsm-5-you-re-crazy-to-worry-about-your-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In DSM-IV, there is a category called Somatoform Disorders, the common feature of which is a preoccupation with &amp;ldquo;… physical symptoms that suggest a general medical condition …and are not fully explained by a general medical condition…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four of the &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; in this category will be retired in DSM-5 and will be replaced by a new &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo;:  &lt;em&gt;somatic symptom disorder&lt;/em&gt;.  The four superseded &amp;ldquo;diagnoses&amp;rdquo; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;1.  somatization disorder
2.  hypochondriasis
3.  pain disorder
4.  undifferentiated somatoform disorder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drugging Children Gives Them the Wrong Message</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 10:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/drugging-children-gives-them-the-wrong-message/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The routine drugging of children for the ordinary problems of childhood is destructive for two reasons:  firstly because of the toxic effects of the pharmaceutical products, and secondly because it &lt;strong&gt;conveys to the child the message that drugs are an acceptable way to deal with life&amp;rsquo;s problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This latter kind of damage is graphically illustrated in a tragic NY Times article by Ted Gup.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/03/opinion/diagnosis-human.html?_r=1&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Ted is a fellow of the Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In DSM-5, A-D-H-D Still Spells Misbehavior</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/in-dsm-5-a-d-h-d-still-spells-misbehavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a central theme of this website that there are no mental illnesses/disorders, and that the psychiatric medicalization of ordinary human problems is arbitrary, spurious, and destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread acceptance of ADHD as a mental illness/chemical imbalance has no scientific underpinning, but rather is based on marketing and promotion.  The ADHD &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; is particularly destructive, in that it targets &lt;i&gt;children&lt;/i&gt;, and serves as the justification for &amp;ldquo;treating&amp;rdquo; these children with dangerous drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 Inter-Rater Reliability is Low</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-inter-rater-reliability-is-low/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/the-dsm-5-field-trials-inter-rater-reliability-ratings-take-a-nose-dive/&#34;&gt;article by Jack Carney&lt;/a&gt;, DSW, on this topic on Mad in America.  Jack refers to the DSM-5 field trials published earlier this year in the American Journal of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inter-rater reliability is measured by a statistic called a kappa score.  A score of 1 means perfect inter-rater agreement; a score of 0 indicates zero agreement.  In psychosocial research a kappa score of 0.7 or above is generally considered good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34; for Children</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatric-diagnoses-for-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BeyondMeds&#34;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;, I came across an article by Marilyn Wedge, PhD.  It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;i&gt;Six Problems with Psychiatric Diagnosis for Children. &lt;/i&gt;  You can read it &lt;a href=&#34;http://beyondmeds.com/2012/10/08/psych-dx-for-children/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Psychiatric diagnoses contained in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders are not classified by causes like genuine medical diseases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Perhaps worst of all, a child who has been labeled with a psychiatric diagnosis grows up believing that there is something wrong with her, that she is somehow “abnormal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Murders and Mental Health</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 12:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mass-murders-and-mental-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Newtown mass murders have generated widespread demand for improved &amp;ldquo;mental health&amp;rdquo; services, and even for mandatory mental health screenings for schoolchildren.  The notion embedded in these demands is that the perpetrators are &amp;ldquo;mentally ill,&amp;rdquo; and that early identification will enable psychiatrists to treat (i.e. drug) them before they can do any damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve said many times, the APA&amp;rsquo;s definition of a mental disorder is essentially:  any human activity that entails significant problems.  So, of course, provided we accept this definition, all the mass murderers are mentally ill.  But all we&amp;rsquo;re saying here is that mass murder is problematic behavior.  (Wow – such wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 08:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that the initial drafts of DSM-5 received a great deal of negative comment.  It&amp;rsquo;s also known that some of the more controversial proposals have been scrapped, but that others have been retained and sent for printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this was fairly predictable.  The APA&amp;rsquo;s agenda is to widen the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net to include as many people as possible.  But they&amp;rsquo;re not complete fools.  They know that there&amp;rsquo;s a good deal of anti-psychiatry feeling out there, so in my view, they floated some very contentious proposals, fully accepting that these would be withdrawn under pressure, thereby creating the perception that they are reasonable folk just trying to do what&amp;rsquo;s right.  Meanwhile, other proposals go under the wire unscathed, and the &amp;ldquo;diagnostic&amp;rdquo; net is widened.  Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schizophrenia – Two Short Stories</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 08:25:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/schizophrenia-two-short-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;First story&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 70&amp;rsquo;s I worked in Grendon Prison in England.  The facility was run on the lines of a therapeutic community – lots of meetings, groups, etc&amp;hellip;  One of the prisoners – let&amp;rsquo;s call him William – was serving time for burglary.  He was about 24 years old, and during his intake interviews he told us that he was a member of a small quasi-religious sect who believed that doomsday was imminent and that they would be the chosen few.  He talked about these matters openly and with a good measure of passion, and after a few weeks the other prisoners were describing him as &amp;ldquo;crazy&amp;rdquo; and a &amp;ldquo;nutcase.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and the Law</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 14:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-the-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The central theme of this website is that there are no mental illnesses, and that the widespread medicalization of ordinary human problems is spurious and destructive.  These concepts have been around for decades, but in the last four or five years have &amp;ldquo;taken off,&amp;rdquo; and are finding a good deal of acceptance among practitioners, academics, clients, and the general public.  Change is in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A matter that is sometimes overlooked, however, is that the &lt;strong&gt;concept of &amp;ldquo;mental illness&amp;rdquo; and its &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; by psychiatrists and other professionals is deeply embedded in the legal system of most states and countries&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-psychotic Drugs in Nursing Homes</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/anti-psychotic-drugs-in-nursing-homes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 10:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/anti-psychotic-drugs-in-nursing-homes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2013/feb/21/elderly-care-antipsychotics-sharp-rise&#34;&gt;article from the Manchester Guardian&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.  The article is by Sarah Boseley, and is a review of a UK study in the Journal of the American Geriatric Society written by Aideen Maguire, C. Hughes, Chris Cardwell, and Dermot O&amp;rsquo;Reilly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers examined the Northern Ireland prescribing database and discovered that when people were admitted to nursing homes, the &lt;strong&gt;rate at which they were prescribed anti-psychotic drugs increased from 1.1% to 20.3%!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma and Mental Health: Hand-in-Glove</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 19:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another interesting article:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/02/24/academic-integrity-in-ireland-and-the-uk-is-there-any-such-thing/&#34;&gt;Academic Integrity in Ireland and the UK: Is there any such thing?&lt;/a&gt; at Leonie fennells&amp;rsquo; Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about financial ties between pharmaceutical companies and psychiatrists.  Same old story; different location.  It&amp;rsquo;s worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Becky @yobluemama2 on Twitter for drawing my attention to this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muddled Thinking and Psychiatric &#34;Diagnoses&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:14:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/muddled-thinking-and-psychiatric-diagnoses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until just a few years ago, the spurious nature of mental illness received little or no attention either in professional circles or in the general media. There were a few of us &amp;ldquo;cranks&amp;rdquo; who poked away at the issue, but peer condemnation was usually swift and outspoken.  On one occasion I was called an &amp;ldquo;anti-science Nazi&amp;rdquo; for daring to suggest that the condition known as ADHD might have more to do with ineffective parental discipline than with brain chemistry.  We were voices in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold-blooded Killers</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 14:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday our local newspaper ran an article called &amp;ldquo;Mental Health Needs Reform.&amp;rdquo;  It was written by a psychologist, and the main thrust of the piece was that if &amp;ldquo;serious mental health care reform&amp;rdquo; is not implemented, we will see more mass murders similar to those at Aurora and Newtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article contained several unwarranted assumptions, and recommended that mental hospitals &amp;ldquo;rebuild facilities for treating those patients.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position, of course, is that there are no mental illnesses, and that cold-blooded killers are not sick in any meaningful sense of the term, but are, rather, individuals who have not internalized an age-appropriate respect for the lives and welfare of other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dangerous People</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dangerous-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 18:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/dangerous-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the Connecticut mass murders of last month, a great deal of attention, official and otherwise, is being focused on the “mentally ill.”  Politicians of all persuasions are proclaiming that we need more funding for the so-called mental health services, and predictably, the various practitioners and centers are lining up with their hands outstretched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spurious logic, of course, is never identified, or if it is, it gets lost in the rhetoric.  Mental illness is presented (and accepted) as the proximate cause of the violence.  If one were to ask a mental health practitioner why an individual was so crazy and acted so brutally, the reply would be:  Because he has a mental illness.  But if one were to press the matter and ask:  How do you know he has a mental illness? the only possible response is: Because he is so crazy and acted so brutally.  The only evidence for the so-called illness is the very behavior it purports to explain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and World Politics</title>
      <link>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-world-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 22:45:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/posts/mental-health-and-world-politics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year the World Health Assembly, the decision-making body of the World Health Organization, an agency of the UN, passed a resolution “to develop a comprehensive action plan covering services, policies, plans, strategies, programs and legislation to enable persons with mental disorders to live a full and productive life in the community.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution recommends several strategies to promote mental health, including the integration of “…mental health into broader health policies and strategies…” and the promotion of “…mental health by targeting early childhood years, aging, prevention of domestic violence and abuse, workplace stress and suicide prevention programs.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
