<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Conflict of Interest on Behaviorism and Mental Health</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/conflict-of-interest/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conflict of Interest on Behaviorism and Mental Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.146.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 05:30:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/conflict-of-interest/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The &#34;Essential Principles&#34; of Psychiatric Practice: More Psychiatric Cheerleading</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-essential-principles-of-psychiatric-practice-more-psychiatric-cheerleading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 05:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-essential-principles-of-psychiatric-practice-more-psychiatric-cheerleading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the May 2018 issue of Current Psychiatry, there&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/The-DNA-of-Psychiatric-Practice.pdf&#34;&gt;editoria&lt;/a&gt;l by Henry Nasrallah, MD.  Dr. Nasrallah is a highly renowned psychiatrist, and is Editor-in-Chief of the journal.  He is also chair of the St. Louis University Department of Psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the opening paragraph of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;As the end of the academic year approaches, I always think of one last message to send to the freshly minted psychiatrists who will complete their 4 years of post-MD training. This year, I thought of emphasizing the principles of psychiatric practice, which the graduates will deliver for the next 4 to 5 decades of their professional lives. Those essential principles are coded in the DNA of psychiatric practice, just as the construction of all organs in the human body is coded within the DNA of the 22,000 genes that comprise our 23 chromosomes.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robert Whitaker Refutes Jeffrey Lieberman; But Is Psychiatry Reformable?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 05:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/robert-whitaker-refutes-jeffrey-lieberman-but-is-psychiatry-reformable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 5, 2017, Donald Goff, MD and seven other psychiatrists, including the very eminent Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, published an article in the American Journal of Psychiatry.  The title is: &lt;span style=&#34;color: #000080;&#34;&gt;&lt;span lang=&#34;zxx&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.16091016&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Long-Term Effects of Antipsychotic Medication on Clinical Course in Schizophrenia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Concerns have been raised that treatment with antipsychotic medication might adversely affect long-term outcomes for people with schizophrenia. The evidence cited for these concerns includes the association of antipsychotic treatment with brain volume reduction and with dopamine receptor sensitization, which might make patients vulnerable to relapse and illness progression. An international group of experts was convened to examine findings from clinical and basic research relevant to these concerns. Little evidence was found to support a negative long-term effect of initial or maintenance antipsychotic treatment on outcomes, compared with withholding treatment. Randomized controlled trials strongly support the efficacy of antipsychotics for the acute treatment of psychosis and prevention of relapse; correlational evidence suggests that early intervention and reduced duration of untreated psychosis might improve longer-term outcomes. Strategies for treatment discontinuation or alternative nonpharmacologic treatment approaches may benefit a subgroup of patients but may be associated with incremental risk of relapse and require further study, including the development of biomarkers that will enable a precision medicine approach to individualized treatment.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health First Aid: Another Psychiatric Expansionist Tool</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 05:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-first-aid-another-psychiatric-expansionist-tool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On December 25, 2016, the Baltimore Sun published an excellent article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/oped/bs-ed-youth-overmedication-20161225-story.html&#34;&gt;Drug companies prey on children&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Patrick D. Hahn, PhD.  Dr. Hahn is an affiliate professor of biology at Loyola University, Maryland.  Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I recently attended Youth Mental Health First Aid Training at a local public school. It was an eye-opening experience.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Youth Mental Health First Aid Training, sponsored by the National Council for Behavioral Health, is intended to enable teachers, parents and others in contact with young people to identify potential &#39;mental illnesses&#39; in order to facilitate early detection and treatment by our mental health care system. My fellow attendees were surprisingly open about their own experiences with that system. One mentioned that her son became manic after being diagnosed for ADHD. Another said that both she and her roommate became bipolar after being diagnosed for depression. Neither our facilitators nor anyone else present pointed out that mania and bipolar disorder are toxic effects of medications commonly prescribed for ADHD and depression.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mental Health Reform Act of 2016 (SB 2680) Would Be a Huge Step Backwards</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 05:30:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-mental-health-reform-act-of-2016-sb-2680-would-be-a-huge-step-backwards/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 6, HB 2646 (the Tim Murphy Bill) passed the US House and was sent to the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the present time, a related bill is working its way through the Senate.  This is SB 2680, The Mental Health Reform Act 2016.  It is sponsored by Lamar Alexander (R-TN), Patty Murray (D-WA), Bill Cassidy (R-LA), Chris Murphy (D-CT), David Vitter (R-LA), and Al Franken (D-MN).  The wording of the bill was finalized in March of this year, and it passed out of committee on March 16.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Response To Dr. Pies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/my-response-to-dr-pies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 05:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/my-response-to-dr-pies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Behavioar-Therapist-Oct-2015.pdf&#34;&gt;October 2015 issue of the Behavior Therapist&lt;/a&gt; (pages 206-213), Jeffrey Lacasse, PhD, and Jonathan Leo, PhD, published an article titled &lt;em&gt;Antidepressants and the Chemical Imbalance Theory of Depression: A Reflection and Update on the Discourse&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the article had particular merit, and I drew attention to it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/11/02/more-on-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;a post dated November 2&lt;/a&gt;.  The post, &lt;em&gt;More on the Chemical Imbalance Theory, &lt;/em&gt;was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2015/11/more-on-the-chemical-imbalance-theory/&#34;&gt;published on Mad in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that post, I quoted a number of passages from the Behavior Therapist article, including:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances &#39;Replies&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-replies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 05:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-replies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 19, 2015, I published a post titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2015/06/19/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-and-johnson/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allen Frances&amp;rsquo; Ties to Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that post, I set out some very serious allegations against Dr. Frances.  I drew these allegations from a document titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Rothman.pdf&#34;&gt;Special Witness Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; dated October 15, 2010.  The report was written by David Rothman, PhD, Professor of Social Medicine at Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rothman&amp;rsquo;s report was produced in the context of a lawsuit filed by the State of Texas against Janssen Pharmaceutica, a subsidiary of Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Allen Frances&#39; Ties to Johnson &amp; Johnson</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 05:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/allen-frances-ties-to-johnson-johnson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an article titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uottawa.scholarsportal.info/ottawa/index.php/aporia/article/view/3486/3195&#34;&gt;Diagnosisgate: Conflict of Interest at the Top of the Psychiatric Apparatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Paula Caplan, PhD.  The article was published in Aporia, the University of Ottawa nursing journal, in January 2015.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oa.uottawa.ca/journals/aporia/about_aporia.jsp?lang=&#34;&gt;Aporia&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;a peer-reviewed, bilingual, and open access journal dedicated to scholarly debates in nursing and the health sciences.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr, Caplan is a clinical and research psychologist, and an Associate at Harvard&amp;rsquo;s DuBois Institute.  She worked as a consultant to the DSM-IV task force in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s, but resigned from this position after two years.    Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from her February 2014 post on Mad in America &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2014/02/great-crazy-cover-harm-results-rewriting-history-dsm/&#34;&gt;The Great “Crazy” Cover-up: Harm Results from Rewriting the History of DSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptic Drugs And Mortality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-mortality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 05:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptic-drugs-and-mortality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November of last year, the Schizophrenia Bulletin published online a research study:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25422511&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antipsychotic Treatment and Mortality in Schizophrenia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Minna Torniainen et al.  The research was conducted in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors offer the following background for the study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;It is generally believed that long-term use of antipsychotics increases mortality and, especially, the risk of cardiovascular death. However, there are no solid data to substantiate this view.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
and the following conclusions:
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Among patients with schizophrenia, the cumulative antipsychotic exposure displays a U-shaped curve for overall mortality, revealing the highest risk of death among those patients with no antipsychotic use. These results indicate that both excess overall and cardiovascular mortality in schizophrenia is attributable to other factors than antipsychotic treatment when used in adequate dosages.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressant Drugs and Suicide Rates</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-drugs-and-suicide-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/antidepressant-drugs-and-suicide-rates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2010, Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica published a study by Göran Isacsson et al.  The paper was titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20384599&#34;&gt;Antidepressant medication prevents suicide in depression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Here&#39;s the conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;The finding that in-patient care for depression did not increase the probability of the detection of antidepressants in suicides is difficult to explain other than by the assumption that a substantial number of depressed individuals were saved from suicide by postdischarge treatment with antidepressant medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma-funded Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-funded-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 05:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-funded-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On August 20, 2014, P&lt;em&gt;sychiatry Advisor&lt;/em&gt; published an article on its website.  The article was written by Leslie Citrome, MD, a professor of psychiatry at New York Medical College in Valhalla, NY, and a member of the Board of Directors of the American Society of Clinical Psychopharmacology.  The article is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psychiatryadvisor.com/is-bias-against-pharma-funded-research-fair/article/367248/&#34;&gt;Is Bias Against Pharma-Funded Research Fair?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;  This is an interesting title, because bias, by its very definition, is unfair.  So the very wording of the question begs the question – which strikes me as unfair.  But let&amp;rsquo;s put that aside.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Hell to Hope</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/from-hell-to-hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2014 05:58:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/from-hell-to-hope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-1519&#34; src=&#34;../../images/tell-your-story.png&#34; alt=&#34;This post was submitted by a reader.&#34; width=&#34;247&#34; height=&#34;209&#34; /&gt;   &lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Can.you tell I have a cat just by looking at me?  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Can you tell I have a mental illness just by looking at me?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I began to change in my early teens, be it hormones and my shifting &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;brain chemistry, or the stress of my parents seperating. Something &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;stressor from the outside flipped on the switch to a new life filled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;with major mood swings out of my control.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Low self extreme kept me from meeting or caring about being social. I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;only went to school because I had to. Luckily one day two high school &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;girls came to my 8th grade health class and talked to us about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;everything from Stress to Smoking to Sex even Suicide. They asked us &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;to write thrm a question about these topics and others. I wrote &amp;ldquo;I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;want to die&amp;quot;It was the first time I admitted to myself or anyone else &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that I had these thouhts constantly. When class was over the girls &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;kindly asked if I would like to talk to the counselor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;That day was just the beginning of my journey towards understanding &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;mental illness, and ultimately accepting mental Wellness. Over the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;next few years I spent time in psychiatric hospitals, tried medication &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;that would hopefully be the missing puzzle piece of chemistry my brain &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;needed. Most of the medications tried their best but caused the worst. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I never once stopped taking the medication I was prescribed, for I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;never wanted to feel so completely out of control again. I realized I &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;was accepting my chemical imbalance and each day I began to understand &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;myself and my issues in a much lighter, hopeful way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;The support I recieved on my journey towards wholness helped me &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;acknowledge I was a person not a problem. My mother was my life &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;support at times. She learned all she could about mood disorders and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;educated our family so as not to judge me, but be very proud. I also &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;met some peers within the mental health community that I still keep in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;touch with regularly. It was a blessing to know I was not alone in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;issues I faced. And that I would be accepted by my peers, for they had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experienced similar challenges.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;I knew I had a message and a story to tell. I wanted to share my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;experience From Hell to Hope with students. That is where my journey &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;began. So , with a father whose son has schizophrenia, and I, with my &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;rapid cycling moods we have spoken to over 4,000 high school students &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;since 2006.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34; /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;My hope is to stop stigma, treating people badly because they seem &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;different. I want to promote education of mental illness so people &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #222222;&#34;&gt;suffering and their loved ones will believe recovery is real.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FDA:  The Fox Guards the Hen House</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 05:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-fda-the-fox-guards-the-hen-house/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In their Fall 2013 issue, the Journal of Law, Medicine, and Ethics published a symposium of papers by members of the Harvard&amp;rsquo;s Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics.  The symposium was called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ethics.harvard.edu/lab/featured/325-jlme-symposium&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption and Pharmaceutical Policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The symposium focuses on pharmaceutical products generally, but all the material is relevant and important in the context of psychiatric drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will highlight one of these papers:  &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Light-et-al-document-from-Safra-Institue-on-corruption-1.pdf&#34;&gt;Institutional Corruption of Pharmaceuticals and the Myth of Safe and Effective Drugs&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; by Donald W. Light, Joel Lexchin, and Jonathan J. Darrow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sluggish Cognitive Tempo - A New Diagnosis?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 05:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sluggish-cognitive-tempo---a-new-diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 11, 2014, journalist Alan Schwarz (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Schwarz&#34;&gt;brief bio here&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the New York Times on this topic, titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/12/health/idea-of-new-attention-disorder-spurs-research-and-debate.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;Idea of New attention Disorder Spurs Research, and Debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;  Alan has written extensively on the rising rates of the condition known as ADHD, and on the abuse of the drugs that are used to &amp;ldquo;treat&amp;rdquo; this condition. He has drawn a good deal of criticism from psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s believers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;ADHD&#39; and Dangerous Driving</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 05:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adhd-and-dangerous-driving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Laurence Jerome, a Canadian psychiatrist, and two colleagues wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/ADHD-and-Driving-Jerome-et-al-ccap15_3p105.pdf&#34;&gt;What We Know About ADHD and Driving Risk: A Literature Review, Meta-Analysis and Critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  It was published in the Journal of the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry in August, 2006. The primary result of the meta-analysis was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Current data support the utility of stimulant medication in improving driving performance in younger ADHD drivers.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
The study is lengthy and well-referenced, but in keeping with standard psychiatric practice, it conceptualizes and presents ADHD as a &#34;…common psychiatric disorder…&#34; with symptoms of &#34;…inattention, impulsiveness and hyperactivity…&#34;  In other words, they present ADHD as something that a person &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; rather than as something that a person &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; The problem with this approach is that it creates the impression that meaningful or significant correlations/effects have been found, where in fact all that has happened is an elucidation of the terms used.
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the authors refer to a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Fried%2C+R.%2C+Petty%2C+C.R.%2C+Surman%2C+C.B.%2C+Reimer%2C+B.%2C+Aleardi%2C+M.%2C+Martin%2C+J.M.+2006&#34;&gt;Fried et al.&lt;/a&gt; (2006) and state:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of Dan Markingson&#39;s Death</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/investigation-of-dan-markingson-s-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 05:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/investigation-of-dan-markingson-s-death/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I have written on Dan Markingson&amp;rsquo;s death in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/10/28/cover-up-of-a-wrongful-death/&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, and I encourage readers who are not familiar with the case to have a look.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;It is generally accepted by those of us on this side of the debate that psychiatry does more harm than good, and is organizationally and individually responsible for a great many deaths worldwide every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;These deaths, however, are seldom laid at psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s feet.  Coroners return verdicts of suicide, homicide, heart attacks, choking, etc…  Occasionally psychiatric practice is mentioned as a contributory factor, but not often.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justina Pelletier and Boston Children&#39;s Hospital</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/justina-pelletier-and-boston-children-s-hospital/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 05:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/justina-pelletier-and-boston-children-s-hospital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Justina Pelletier is the 15-year-old girl who is at the center of a dispute between her parents and the Psychiatry Department at Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justina, who lived with her parents in Connecticut, had been diagnosed with mitochondrial disease, a rare and debilitating illness, and had been receiving treatment for this from Mark Korson, MD, Chief of Metabolism Services at Tufts Medical Center in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February of last year, Justina&amp;rsquo;s parents took her to Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital with flu-like symptoms.  Dr. Korson had recommended an admission to Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s so that Justina could be seen by Alex Flores, MD, a gastrointestinal specialist who had recently transferred from Tufts to BCH.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Blood Test for Schizophrenia with 83% Accuracy?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-blood-test-for-schizophrenia-with-83-accuracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 05:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/a-blood-test-for-schizophrenia-with-83-accuracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An NBC online News article dated October 15, 2010, carried the noteworthy title &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nbcnews.com/id/39686973/ns/health-mental_health/t/new-blood-test-may-help-detect-schizophrenia/#.UxVbXvldXwl&#34;&gt;New blood test may help detect schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;Thanks to Francesca for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article was written by Natasha Allen, a freelance medical journalist.  The gist of the article is that there is a new blood test called VeriPsych which &amp;ldquo;researchers say&amp;rdquo; is 83% accurate in discriminating people who are &amp;ldquo;schizophrenic&amp;rdquo; from people who are not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5:  Dimensionality:  Conflicts of Interest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-dimensionality-conflicts-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 06:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5-dimensionality-conflicts-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/23/dsm-5-dimensional-diagnoses-more-conflicts-of-interest/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;DSM-5 – Dimensional Diagnoses – More Conflicts of Interest?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; which I posted on December 23, 2013, I drew attention to the fact that David Kupfer, MD, in his position as head of the DSM-5 Task Force, was vigorously promoting a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;dimensional&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; model of assessment while at the same time was positioning himself to benefit financially if such a system were to be adopted by psychiatry generally.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Of Psychiatrists: What The Future Holds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/training-of-psychiatrists-what-the-future-holds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 06:06:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/training-of-psychiatrists-what-the-future-holds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;Joel Yager, MD, is a Professor of Psychiatry, University of Colorado at Denver School of Medicine.  He started his career as a US Army psychiatrist in 1969, and has held a wide range of clinical and teaching positions in the intervening years.  He has received numerous awards, including lifetime achievement awards from the National Eating Disorders Association (2008) and from the Association for Academic Psychiatry (2009).  He has published more than 200 peer-reviewed papers, many of which are concerned with the training of psychiatrists.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry&#39;s Over Reliance On Pharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-over-reliance-on-pharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 05:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-s-over-reliance-on-pharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;I recently read &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/data/Journals/AJP/4236/appi.ajp.2011.11010039.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;The NIMH-CATIE Schizophrenia Study: What Did We Learn?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height: 1.5em;&#34;&gt; by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, and T. Scott Stroup, MD, MPH.  The article was published in the American Journal of Psychiatry 168:8, August 2011.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;When the CATIE study was designed in 1999-2000, the prevailing opinion of researchers and clinicians alike was that the newer (second-generation) antipsychotic drugs were vastly superior to the older (first-generation) antipsychotic drugs in efficacy and safety. This largely reflected the results of studies sponsored by the manufacturers of the new drugs…, marketing messages of pharmaceutical companies and the hopes of many who wanted better treatments.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman Thanks Dr. Scully</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-thanks-dr-scully/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 05:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-thanks-dr-scully/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my regular readers know, I am a big fan of Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, eminent President of the American Psychiatric Association.  I study his bulletins on Psychiatric News avidly, not only for the insights they provide in the areas of human frailty and self-deception, but also for their literary qualities of obfuscation and semantic distortion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, therefore, with some alarm that I confess that I missed the good doctor&amp;rsquo;s epistle of December 13.  This was pointed out to me by a reader, who was also kind enough to say that without my clarificatory commentary, he is simply unable to fathom Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s insights and erudition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DSM-5 - Dimensional Diagnoses - More Conflicts of Interest?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 05:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dsm-5---dimensional-diagnoses---more-conflicts-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 20, JAMA Psychiatry (formerly Archives of General Psychiatry) published an interesting letter.  It was headed: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleID=1780020&amp;amp;utm_source=Silverchair%20Information%20Systems&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=JAMAPsychiatry%3AOnlineFirst11%2F20%2F2013&#34;&gt;Failure to Report Financial Disclosure Information&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and was signed by Robert D. Gibbons PhD, David J Weiss PhD, Paul A. Pilkonis PhD, Ellen Frank, PhD , and David J. Kupfer MD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is an apology for failing to disclose a financial interest in an article, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3551289/&#34;&gt;Development of a Computerized Adaptive Test for Depression&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/i&gt; that had appeared in Archives of General Psychiatry a year earlier (November 2012).  The article described a computerized questionnaire for depression (the CAT-DI) and was generally positive with regards to the potential usefulness of the test in clinical settings.  In the article, the authors had clearly stated that they had &lt;i&gt;no conflicts of interest&lt;/i&gt;, but that:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAFÉ Study: Real Science or Marketing Exercise?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/caf%C3%A9-study-real-science-or-marketing-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 05:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/caf%C3%A9-study-real-science-or-marketing-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 8,  I received the following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/12/06/u-of-minnesota-faculty-senate-vote-to-review-dan-markingsons-death/&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; from a reader:  (The subject matter is the controversial CAFÉ – Comparisons of Atypicals in First Episode of Psychosis - study.  This was the study in which Dan Markingson committed suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;It appears that there was no head-to-head with a control group taking a placebo pill. Nor was there a control group featuring &#39;old&#39; types of &#39;antipsychotic&#39;. If that was the case then it is very poor study. If you are just looking at 3 &#39;new&#39; subtypes of a &#39;new&#39; class - then what on earth can you hope to show from the data.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuroleptics for Children: Harvard&#39;s Shame</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 05:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/neuroleptics-for-children-harvard-s-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2012, Mark Olfson, MD, et al, published an article in the Archives of General Psychiatry.  The title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22868273&#34;&gt;National Trends in the Office-Based Treatment of Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;The authors collected data from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Surveys for the period 1993-2009, and looked for trends in antipsychotic prescribing for children, adolescents, and adults in outpatient visits.  Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;&lt;!--
table { 	border: 1px solid gray;     	border-collapse: collapse;      	width: 500px;   	cellspacing: 0; } th {     	background-color: #eee;          border: 1px solid black; }  th#blank {     	background- color: #FFF;  }  th.colOne {         width: 100px; } td {     	text-align: center;  	border: 1px solid black; } table#diagnosis th.data {         width: 120px; }
--&gt;&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table id=&#34;antipsychoticRX&#34; cellspacing=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;colOne&#34;&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Increase in no. of antipsychotic prescriptions per 100 population (1993-2009)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0-13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.24-1.83 (almost 8-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;14-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.78-3.76 (almost 5-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;21+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.25-6.18 (almost 2-fold)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;p&gt;The authors provide a breakdown of the diagnoses assigned to the children and adolescents during the antipsychotic visits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causes of High Mortality in People Labeled &#39;Mentally Ill&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 06:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/causes-of-high-mortality-in-people-labeled-mentally-ill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ANOTHER VIDEO FROM DR. LIEBERMAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 28, Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, President of the APA, made another video.  This one is titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/813056&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;An Important Look at Mortality in Mental Illness: A Decade of Data on Psychotropic Drugs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and was made for Medscape.  You can see the transcript at the same site.  Medscape is a web resource for medical practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s commentary on an article that appeared in JAMA Psychiatry online on August 28:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1733743&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Comparative Mortality Risk in Adult Patients With Schizophrenia, Depression, Bipolar Disorder, Anxiety Disorders, and Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Participating in Psychopharmacology Clinical Trials&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Arif Khan, MD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dangers of SSRI&#39;s</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 06:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-dangers-of-ssri-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SSRI&amp;rsquo;S AND SUICIDE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Fiddaman has a post up today called &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.com/2013/11/mhra-consultant-calls-for.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;MHRA Consultant Calls for Antidepressant Use in Young&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  The article highlights some of the dangers associated with SSRI&amp;rsquo;s, and also describes some of the attempts to suppress or discount the significance of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently in 2010, Swedish psychiatrist Göran Isacsson, MD, PhD, published a paper in Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica.  The piece was titled &lt;i&gt;Antidepressant medication prevents suicide in depression,&lt;/i&gt; and reported that of a group of 1,077 depressed people who had committed suicide, only 15.2% had measurable amounts of antidepressants in the blood stream at the time of the suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The New Holy Grail: Dysfunctional Neural Circuits</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 06:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-new-holy-grail-dysfunctional-neural-circuits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new article on Psychiatric News titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org//newsArticle.aspx?articleid=1758579&#34;&gt;Change, Challenge, and Opportunity: Psychiatry Through the Looking Glass of Research&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/i&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s dated October 17, and was authored  by Steven Hyman, MD, and Jeffrey Lieberman, MD.  Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MentalHealthLaw&#34;&gt;Mental Health Law on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lieberman is President of the APA.  Dr. Hyman was Director of NIMH from 1996 to 2001, and is now the Director of the Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research at the Broad Institute.  The Broad Institute is affiliated with Harvard University, and Dr. Hyman is a Harvard Distinguished Service Professor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tide Has Turned</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-tide-has-turned/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 05:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-tide-has-turned/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Those of us on this side of the psychiatric debate have long maintained that there is a link between the so-called antidepressant drugs and the mass murders that have become an increasingly common feature of American society in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call for a formal investigation of this link, however, has been consistently resisted, and instead there has been a well-orchestrated medical campaign clamoring for more mental health services and more active outreach and prevention services.  As an example, see Jeffrey Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s guest post on Everyday Health, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.everydayhealth.com/columns/health-answers/in-the-wake-of-the-navy-yard-shooting-a-way-forward/&#34;&gt;In the Wake of the Navy Yard Shooting: A Way Forward&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Disclosing Financial Relationships</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-ethics-of-disclosing-financial-relationships/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 06:29:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-ethics-of-disclosing-financial-relationships/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Carl Elliott &lt;a href=&#34;http://loathingbioethics.blogspot.com/2013/08/the-moreno-opinion.html&#34;&gt;posted a link&lt;/a&gt; to a statement written by Jonathan Moreno, PhD, a renowned bioethicist at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scribd.com/doc/162952070/Jonathan-Moreno-affadavit-in-Biotronik-conflict-of-interest-case&#34;&gt;Dr. Moreno&amp;rsquo;s statement&lt;/a&gt; was in reference to an Oregon court case.  The Oregon Department of Justice had accused two cardiologists of concealing information from patients.  Apparently the cardiologists had put heart implants into patients without informing the patients that they (the cardiologists) had financial ties to the manufacturer of the implants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Never Mind The Facts; Just Sell More Pills</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 05:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/never-mind-the-facts-just-sell-more-pills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article, recently published in Journal of Contemporary Psychotherapy, on Springer Link.  It&amp;rsquo;s titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10879-013-9244-x/fulltext.html&#34;&gt;Shooting the Messenger: The Case of ADHD&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt; and it was written by Gretchen LeFever Watson, PhD, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently some of the authors had noted in 1995 a marked increase in the &amp;ldquo;diagnosis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo; of the condition known as ADHD in southeastern Virginia.  This is a large urban conglomeration of six different cities, including Norfolk, Portsmouth, and Virginia Beach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Lieberman is Back</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 05:45:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/dr-lieberman-is-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FearLoathingBTX&#34;&gt;Carl Elliott via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently read Dr. Lieberman&amp;rsquo;s latest post on Psychiatric News. It&amp;rsquo;s called – believe it or not – &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleID=1723795&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Time to Re-Engage With Pharma? &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;dated August 1, 2013.  And it&amp;rsquo;s classic Dr. Lieberman sleight of hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His opening statement, for instance, reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;Drug companies aren’t held in high esteem by the public these days.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
This may or may not be true.  But note what he&#39;s done.  The issue here is the long-standing and corrupt relationship &lt;i&gt;between psychiatry and the manufacturers of drugs&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;But from his first sentence, Dr. Lieberman has taken psychiatry out of the equation.  He has also lumped the makers of legitimate medicines in with the makers of psychiatry&amp;rsquo;s drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are The Second Generation Neuroleptics Good For the Brain?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/are-the-second-generation-neuroleptics-good-for-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2013 06:02:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/are-the-second-generation-neuroleptics-good-for-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an editorial by Henry Nasrallah, MD, in last month&amp;rsquo;s edition of &lt;em&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt;.  Dr. Nasrallah is the journal&amp;rsquo;s editor-in-chief.  The title of the article is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/uploads/media/007_0713CP_FromTheEditor_FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;Haloperidol clearly is neurotoxic.  Should it be banned?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt; Haloperidol is marketed under the brand name Haldol, but its patent has long expired, and a generic version is available and inexpensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from Dr. Nasrallah&amp;rsquo;s article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;If clinicians who use these decades old drugs were to keep up with medical research and advances in knowledge, we would realize what a travesty it is to use a brain-unfriendly drug such as haloperidol when we have many safer alternatives. A massive volume of knowledge has emerged over the past 15 years about the neurotoxicity of older neuroleptics, especially haloperidol—knowledge that was completely unknown before.   Second-generation antipsychotics have been shown to be much safer for the brain than their older-generation counterparts (although they are not more efficacious).&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CAFE Study: Dr. Lieberman&#39;s High Moral Ground</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-cafe-study-dr-lieberman-s-high-moral-ground/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2013 06:10:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-cafe-study-dr-lieberman-s-high-moral-ground/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CAFE Study, conducted by Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, et al between 2002 and 2005, has been the subject of much comment.  Carl Elliott, in particular, has written extensively on the matter, including his article &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.motherjones.com/environment/2010/09/dan-markingson-drug-trial-astrazeneca?page=1&#34;&gt;The Deadly Corruption of Clinical Trials&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;in Mother Jones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to address the issues involved in the CAFE study, we must first take a brief look at the CATIE study.  This was also conducted by Dr. Lieberman et al (not the same et al as CAFE, but with some overlap).  CATIE was conducted between 2001 and 2004.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry Is Intrinsically Flawed and Rotten</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-intrinsically-flawed-and-rotten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter yesterday, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RobStamatakis&#34;&gt;Robert Stamatakis&lt;/a&gt; commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;I have to ask, I don&#39;t understand.  Do you work in the UK?  Your descriptions of psychiatry are nothing I recognize.  These descriptions of psychiatry are nothing like the practice I see on a daily basis.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
I am certainly a very outspoken critic of psychiatry, and in that regard Robert&#39;s question/challenge is a fair one, to which I will try to respond.
&lt;p&gt;My primary criticism of modern psychiatry – and indeed the criticism that underpins all the others – is that its fundamental concepts are spurious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Payments to Psychiatrists</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2013 05:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-payments-to-psychiatrists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 12 of this year, the Los Angeles Daily News ran an article by Susan Abram titled:  &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailynews.com/ci_22751458/california-doctors-report-prescription-drug-company-payments-speaking-engagements&#34;&gt;Doctors report big pharma payouts for drug endorsements&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;  It discusses the financial ties between physicians and drug companies in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;In fact, hundreds of physicians, psychiatrists, and medical school faculty members across California are on the payroll of major drug companies, earning tens of thousands of dollars for speaking to other medical professionals at events held by industry leaders that make drugs such as Advair, Cymbalta, Viagra and Zoloft.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma Dollars Behind Mental Health Websites</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-dollars-behind-mental-health-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2013 05:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-dollars-behind-mental-health-websites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article on MINNPOST, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.minnpost.com/second-opinion/2013/05/many-mental-illness-websites-show-drug-company-bias-study-finds&#34;&gt;Many mental-illness websites show drug-company bias, study finds&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;dated May 16.  The article is by Susan Perry, and presents the results of a Web survey of mental health websites conducted by John Read and A. Cain from the University of Auckland, New Zealand.  The original study was published in Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica.  You can see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acps.12146/abstract&#34;&gt;abstract here&lt;/a&gt;.  The full article is behind a paywall.  (Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/leoniefen&#34;&gt;Leonie Fennell&lt;/a&gt; for the link.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Empire Still Fighting Back: Dr. Lieberman</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 11:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-empire-still-fighting-back-dr-lieberman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Lieberman, MD, is president-elect of the APA, and is scheduled to take over the reins from Dr. Dilip Jeste this month.  Never in its history has the APA been subject to such scrutiny or criticism from such diverse sources, and one might reasonably have expected Dr. Lieberman to open on a conciliatory note, promising investigations, reforms, etc….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no!  He&amp;rsquo;s in the ring slugging furiously from the opening bell.  Two days ago (May 20) he published an article in Scientific American titled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/mind-guest-blog/2013/05/20/dsm-5-caught-between-mental-illness-stigma-and-anti-psychiatry-prejudice/&#34;&gt;DSM-5: Caught between Mental Illness Stigma and Anti-Psychiatry Prejudice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bereavement:  An &#34;Opportunity&#34; for Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 10:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bereavement-an-opportunity-for-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a new post on Mick Bramham&amp;rsquo;s website called &amp;ldquo;A time to grieve, a time to console, and a time to profit?&amp;rdquo;  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.mythsandrisks.info/2013/04/a-time-to-grieve-time-to-console-and.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have thought that, given the adverse publicity that pharma has been receiving in recent years, they would be easing up on their expansionist agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you would be wrong.  The &lt;strong&gt;APA has declared open season on bereavement&lt;/strong&gt;, and although DSM-5 won&amp;rsquo;t be released for a few more weeks, &lt;strong&gt;Eli Lilly is already grooming their SNRI Cymbalta as a &amp;ldquo;treatment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for this pseudo illness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum Depression Not an Illness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 09:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/postpartum-depression-not-an-illness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of the bio-psychiatric-pharma faction is to &lt;strong&gt;expand turf and sell more drugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is a multi-faceted endeavor, one component of which is disease mongering.  This consists of using marketing techniques to persuade large numbers of people that they have an illness which needs to be treated with drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to postpartum depression, it is an obvious fact that some mothers do indeed experience a measure of depression in the period after giving birth.  The term postpartum depression has in the past been generally understood to mean that the problem had something to do with hormones.  Today brain chemicals are blamed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry is a Lost Cause</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 10:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-is-a-lost-cause/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is easy to vilify psychiatrists.  Their spurious conceptual framework, toxic &amp;ldquo;treatments&amp;rsquo; and blatantly corrupt links to pharma make them easy targets.  Their destructive activities, to which they resolutely cling, invite criticism which they steadfastly ignore.  Any thoughts that perhaps they had seen the errors of their ways have been dashed by the soon-to-be published DSM-5, which promises to be business as usual, only more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOW DID THEY GET THIS WAY?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Conflicts of Interest in Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 11:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come across an article by Lisa Cosgrove et al entitled &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jep.12016/abstract&#34;&gt;Conflicts of interest and the quality of recommendations in clinical guidelines.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;It was published in the Journal of &lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Evaluation in Clinical Practice in December of last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone knows, the APA publishes the DSM, but they also publish &amp;ldquo;Clinical Practice Guidelines&amp;rdquo; for various &amp;ldquo;diagnoses,&amp;rdquo; including the condition known as major depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cosgrove and her colleagues examined the guidelines for major depression to see if the authors had financial or intellectual conflicts of interest.  An example of a financial conflict of interest would be recommending drug treatment when one is on the payroll of a drug company.  An example of an intellectual conflict of interest would be relying on and citing a poor quality study in support of a position in which one had a stake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The International DSM-5 Response Committee</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 10:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-international-dsm-5-response-committee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a post called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.behaviorismandmentalhealth.com/2013/03/16/dsm-5-another-step-in-the-wrong-direction/#.UU3-8xyG0eU&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;DSM-5: Another Step in the Wrong Direction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article I argued that DSM-5 was simply another step in the APA&amp;rsquo;s ongoing agenda to medicalize &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; human problems and to legitimize the administration of drugs as the front line &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; to these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also expressed concern that the widely publicized movement to develop an alternative diagnostic system might not look all that different from what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma&#39;s Subtle but Pernicious Marketing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-s-subtle-but-pernicious-marketing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alice Keys, MD, has recently written a short article for Mad in America.  You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/03/he-who-pays-the-piper/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Keys points out that to maintain a medical license, one must accumulate continuing education credits, and that these credits have to be approved by state licensing boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s widely known that pharmaceutical companies have largely hijacked this process in recent decades, and that their &amp;ldquo;educational&amp;rdquo; presentations might be better described as infomercials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Marketing Ploy: Promoting Mental Health Evaluations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 05:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/another-marketing-ploy-promoting-mental-health-evaluations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, courtesy of Hersteltalent on Twitter, I came across this newspaper article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/03/12/mental-health-checkups/1981495/&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Doctors Urge Mental Health Screenings with Physicals&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  It appeared in USA Today, and was written by Jessica Contrera of the Lafayette, Indiana Journal and Courier.  Dateline March 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article, which is written for the general public, is that when you go in to your doctor for a check-up, you should ask for a mental evaluation as well.  The article reminds us that &amp;ldquo;25% of American adults suffer from some form of mental illness each year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Tests for Psychiatric Disorders – More Promises</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 09:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/lab-tests-for-psychiatric-disorders-more-promises/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently come across (courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TallaTrialogue&#34;&gt;Tallaght Trialogue&lt;/a&gt;) an article in &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt; (Feb 2013) on this topic.  The author is Henry A. Nasrallah, M.D., and you can see it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.currentpsychiatry.com/article_pages.asp?aid=11050&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nasrallah, who is Editor-in-Chief of &lt;i&gt;Current Psychiatry&lt;/i&gt;, states that there are 273 bio-markers for schizophrenia.  But wait.  Dr. Nasrallah goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&#34;None of the individual 273 biomarkers alone can serve as a diagnostic tool for the schizophrenias because there will be high rates of false positives and false negatives.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health After Newtown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:13:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mental-health-after-newtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 5, 2013, a bipartisan panel of leading mental health experts and parents of children with &amp;ldquo;mental disorders&amp;rdquo; held a conversation (that&amp;rsquo;s newspeak for meeting) in Washington D.C. on the topic: Violence and Severe Mental Illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invited panelists were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;Thomas Insel, MD, Director of NIMH
Harold Koplewicz, MD, President of Child Mind Institute
E. Fuller Torrey, MD, Founder of Treatment Advocacy Center
Michael Welner, MD, Founder and Chairman of The Forensic Panel
Michael Fitzpatrick, MSW, Director of NAMI
And three parents of &#34;diagnosed&#34; children&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Involuntary Commitment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 11:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/more-on-involuntary-commitment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent times a good deal of criticism has been directed towards the practice of involuntarily committing individuals to state and private mental hospitals.  Most of this criticism focuses on the lack of effective due process; conflicts of interest in the case of private facilities; and failure to adequately explore alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my view, all of these criticisms are valid, and warrant attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is another side to the story that is seldom aired outside the mental health centers.  A great many clients &lt;i&gt;like&lt;/i&gt; going to the mental hospital; they plan their trips in advance and &amp;ldquo;freak out&amp;rdquo; at the appointed time, knowing that the knee-jerk response of the mental health center will be a court-ordered admission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play Therapy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 10:17:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/play-therapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting article &lt;a href=&#34;http://fiddaman.blogspot.co.nz/2013/02/psychiatric-medication-or-play-therapy.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Psychiatric Medication or Play Therapy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Bob Fiddaman, a New Zealand writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article compares the efficacy and dangers of play therapy vs. pharmaceutical products for children with various problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;…play therapy outcome studies support the efficacy of this intervention with children suffering from various emotional and behavioral difficulties.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Pharmaceutical companies spend billions on marketing psychiatric medication.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt; &#34;Front groups that purport to fly the mental health flag are, in fact, nothing more than agents, pimps for the pharmaceutical industry.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pharma and Mental Health: Hand-in-Glove</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 19:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pharma-and-mental-health-hand-in-glove/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another interesting article:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://leoniefennell.wordpress.com/2013/02/24/academic-integrity-in-ireland-and-the-uk-is-there-any-such-thing/&#34;&gt;Academic Integrity in Ireland and the UK: Is there any such thing?&lt;/a&gt; at Leonie fennells&amp;rsquo; Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about financial ties between pharmaceutical companies and psychiatrists.  Same old story; different location.  It&amp;rsquo;s worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Becky @yobluemama2 on Twitter for drawing my attention to this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry and Big Pharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 22:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-and-big-pharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have written frequently on this website about the hand-in-glove relationship between psychiatrists and the pharmaceutical companies.  It is my general position that the business-first orientation of the pharmaceutical companies, coupled with their willingness to pay large sums of money to co-operative psychiatrists, has been, and continues to be, a corrupting influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently come across two articles by Carl Elliot, MD, PhD. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/how-to-get-away-with-academic-misconduct-at-the-university-of-minnesota/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;How to Get Away with Academic Misconduct at the University of Minnesota,&amp;rdquo; &lt;/a&gt;and&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.madinamerica.com/2013/01/and-thats-the-news-from-the-department-of-psychiatry-where-all-the-nurses-are-supportive-of-research-and-all-the-patients-are-reviewed-for-possible-research-candid/&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;And That’s the News from the Department of Psychiatry.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mandatory Mental Health Screenings for Schoolchildren</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 19:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mandatory-mental-health-screenings-for-schoolchildren/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A regular commenter to this website has drawn my attention to a bill that has been proposed in the Connecticut state legislature.  The bill would require public school and homeschooled children to be assessed by mental health practitioners at grades 6, 8, 10, and 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bill, sponsored by Senator Toni Harp and Representative Toni Walker, is in response to the recent Sandy Hook murders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it starts.  Given the built-in vagueness of the DSM, and the inclusiveness bias of the mental health business, the outcome of these screenings (should the bill become law) is predictable: more and more parents disempowered with regards to their parenting responsibilities; more drugged children, and, tragically, more mass murders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold-blooded Killers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 14:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cold-blooded-killers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday our local newspaper ran an article called &amp;ldquo;Mental Health Needs Reform.&amp;rdquo;  It was written by a psychologist, and the main thrust of the piece was that if &amp;ldquo;serious mental health care reform&amp;rdquo; is not implemented, we will see more mass murders similar to those at Aurora and Newtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article contained several unwarranted assumptions, and recommended that mental hospitals &amp;ldquo;rebuild facilities for treating those patients.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My position, of course, is that there are no mental illnesses, and that cold-blooded killers are not sick in any meaningful sense of the term, but are, rather, individuals who have not internalized an age-appropriate respect for the lives and welfare of other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Childhood Bipolar Disorder</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/childhood-bipolar-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prior to about 1994, childhood bipolar disorder was virtually unheard of.  DSM-III-R (1987), in the section on manic episode, states, “…studies indicate that the mean age at onset is in the early 20s.  However…a sizable number of new cases appear after age 50.”(p 216)  Of course a &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; age of onset in the early 20’s could include young children.  The section on major depressive episode, however, contains the following:  “The average age of onset is in the late 20s, but a major depressive episode may begin at any age, including infancy.” (p 220)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Psychiatry – The Sham Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/psychiatry-the-sham-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting article in last month’s issue of the British Journal of Psychiatry.  The article, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NMTF2MVBfU1paOUk/edit&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychiatry beyond the current paradigm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was authored by Pat Bracken, an Irish psychiatrist, and 28 other British and Irish psychiatrists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the piece is that the &lt;strong&gt;current psychiatric paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;, which the authors describe as “applied neuroscience,” is &lt;strong&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/strong&gt; and needs to be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghostwriting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ghostwriting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 11:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ghostwriting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent commenter, Dan, suggested I check out some of Jeffrey Lacasse’s articles on ghostwriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read two of Jeffrey’s articles: &lt;a href=&#34;http://chronicle.com/article/GhostwritingAcademic/123613/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghostwriting and Academic Medicine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/pdf/1756-0500-4-27.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowledge of ghostwriting and financial conflicts-of-interest reduces the perceived credibility of biomedical research &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(both co-authored with Jonathan Leo), and found them excellent.  Ghostwriting in this context, for readers not familiar with the term, works like this.  A pharmaceutical company does a piece of research which establishes that their product is effective and safe.  (There are various ways to ensure this result, and the pharmaceutical companies know them all.)  Then they get one of their own technical writers to write the research up, but this writer’s name does not go on the report.  Instead, the pharmaceutical company gets an eminent medical academic who has a financial link to the company to put his name on the piece, as if he were indeed the researcher and the author.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conflicts of Interest in Psychiatry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 14:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/conflicts-of-interest-in-psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting article recently in the International Journal of Law and Psychiatry,&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B5cLaT3gdm9NbDRWTTdFR1hBOTg/edit&#34;&gt; “Exposing conflict in psychiatry: Does transparency matter?”&lt;/a&gt; by Chimonas, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the article is as follows.  Senator Chuck Grassley of Iowa has devoted a great deal of time and effort to exposing conflicts of interest in psychiatry.  He has focused particularly on undisclosed financial relationships between psychiatric researchers and pharmaceutical companies.  His efforts resulted in the passage of the Physician Payments Sunshine Act, which requires manufacturers to disclose payments over $100 annually to physicians and teaching hospitals.  The act requiring this will become active in 2014.  The hope is that exposure will reduce the incidence of problems.  It was this particular hypothesis that the researchers wanted to test.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
